<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <info>
    <title>Author Reference</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>authoring</keyword>
      <keyword>exist</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>This article describes the conventions for writing articles for the eXist-db documentation
    set. The eXist-db documentation set is (since beginning 2018) based on a subset of the Docbook 5
    content model. If you want to contribute an article (please do) it must conform to the standards
    described here.</para>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="writing-guidelines">
    <title>General guidelines</title>

    <para>Here are some general writing (and tagging) guidelines:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Please start of with a short introduction of your article in one or a few paragraphs
          before diving in. These paragraphs must be placed <emphasis>before</emphasis> the first
            <tag>sect1</tag>.</para>
        <para>Describe what the article is about and for whom. What is the subject? Is it for total
          novices, beginners, advanced programming gurus in Java hyperspace? Prevent readers from
          diving in and find out that it's not for them.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Presenting longer listings can best be done by storing these in separate documents and
          linking them (see <xref linkend="listings"/>). This makes maintenance easier (ever edited
          a large CDATA section with XML inside?).</para>
        <para>An additional reason is that somewhere in the future we intend to enable running
          code-examples directly from the documentation app. For this these examples must be in
          separate documents. So make sure that at least runnable examples are separated from your
          text.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Of course all the normal technical writing guidelines apply: Keep your target group in
          mind (what do they know and, more importantly, what not), write correct English, use
          plenty of examples, split the article in sections and sub-sections that make sense,
          etc.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sect2>
      <title>Patterns to avoid</title>

      <para>The following patterns tend to occur again and again in writing documentation. Please
        try to avoid them…</para>
      <para>The examples exaggerated, but that's for illustration purposes, not to offend
        anyone.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Avoid the difficult and explain the easy</title>

        <para>It is very tempting to skip quickly over some hard parts of the documentation and
          instead describe some of the easy parts in length. For instance:</para>
        <example>
          <title/>
          <para>To configure the <emphasis>xyz</emphasis> extension you have to create an XML
            configuration file. Here is an example:</para>
          <programlisting>(some skimpy example of a complicated configuration file that is supposed to speak for itself
but does not because its too simple)</programlisting>
          <para>To work with the user interface open this, click here, enter the password twice,
            click ok, bla bla bla, going on for multiple paragraphs…</para>
        </example>

        <para>Well, your reader isn't stupid and hasn't seen a GUI for the first time. So telling
          him/her that a password needs to be entered twice and that ok must be clicked is
          completely superfluous. Just point your reader to the GUI and maybe to the right menu but
          that's all. Believe me, they know how to fill in a dialog box.</para>
        <para>But they do not know what all these elements and attributes in the configuration file
          mean. Even if the names speak for themselves, some explanation will be necessary. Best to
          describe them all, mention defaults, examples, etc.</para>
        <para>And yes, that's hard work, both in thinking and writing. But if you want your xyz
          extension to be used and useful (that's what you wrote it for, right?) its part of the
          job.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Being overly polite</title>

        <para>Sometimes writers try to be very polite to both the reader and, strangely enough, the
          system. Since the reader wants it clear and you can't offend a system, don't.</para>

        <table>
          <title>Table title</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec/>
            <colspec/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Polite version</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Straight version</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>The logfile should appear.</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>The logfile appears.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>You may enter ...</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Enter ...</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>If you wish you can also...</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>It is also possible to ...</para>
                  <para>Also: ...</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Please navigate to...</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Navigate to ...</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Using thus instead of therefore</title>
        <para>Somehow there seems to be a preference among eXist-db's documentation writers for the
          word "thus" when "therefore" is meant. Thus is almost always wrong in this kind of prose,
          so please default to therefore. If you want to know more read on <link xlink:href="https://painintheenglish.com/case/4452/" condition="_blank">here</link>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Java isn't always interesting</title>
        <para>Some articles that explain stuff about things in the XQuery realm keep rambling on
          about stuff in Java or in eXist-db's architecture: Servlets that execute, methods that are
          called, etc.</para>
        <para>Yes, because <emphasis>you</emphasis> are a Java programmer its probably interesting
          to you. But when the intended audience of the article is XQuery programmers, don't bother
          them with this. And if you really (really!) think it is necessary information for some of
          them, add it to a separate section at the bottom.</para>
      </sect3>

    </sect2>


  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Technical guidelines</title>

    <para>More information about Docbook itself can be found on the <link xlink:href="http://docbook.org/" condition="_blank">official Docbook site</link>.</para>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Collection (directory) structure</title>
      <itemizedlist xml:id="test-list-for-ref" xreflabel="directory structure list">
        <listitem>
          <para>A single article must be stored in a collection on its own, the
              <emphasis>article-collection</emphasis>. Related assets or other files will be stored
            in sub-collections of this. This setup ensures that everything belonging to a single
            article stays together. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>In the eXist documentation app, the article-collection will become a sub-collection
            of the <code>data</code> collection. So an article-collection called
              <code>new-cool-feature</code> will become
              <code>/db/apps/doc/data/new-cool-feature</code>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The name of the article-collection should be the same as the document-name of the
            article itself. So if your article is called <code>new-cool-feature.xml</code>, store it
            as <code>new-cool-feature/new-cool-feature.xml</code>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Any binary assets (images, etc.) referenced by your article must be stored in a
            sub-collection <code>assets</code>. So in our example in
              <code>new-cool-feature/assets</code>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Any non-binary assets (usually included program/text listings) referenced by your
            article must be stored in a sub-collection <code>listings</code>. So in our example in
              <code>new-cool-feature/listings</code>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <note>
        <para>All rules regarding collection names are not there for technical reasons but to
          promote consistency. If you deviate and make sure all references are correct it will still
          work. However, to keep things maintainable it is strongly recommended to follow the rules
          stated above (or, if you really think they're stupid, apply for a rule change).</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Overall XML structure</title>
      <para>Here is an example how an article for this documentation set looks like:</para>
      <programlisting xlink:href="listings/structure.xml" language="xml"/>
      <para>Both the processing instructions at the top are optional but strongly recommended.
        They're present to guide tools like oXygen in validating the document and provide authoring
        hints.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Article information</title>
      <para>Here is an example the article's mandatory information section:</para>
      <programlisting xlink:href="listings/info.xml" language="xml"/>
      <para>The following rules and guidelines apply:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>There <emphasis>must</emphasis> be a title present in a <tag>title</tag> element.
            This is the main title of the document. It will be displayed at the top of the
            page.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Optional but strongly recommended is a date in the <tag>date</tag> element. This
            will be displayed below the title and provide the reader with some clue on how old this
            information is. We all know that sometimes articles get outdated but are not removed...
            You don't have to provide an exact date. Just month and year will do, or some indication
            like 1Q18.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>We use keywords to mark an article for certain subject areas. See <xref linkend="keyword-usage"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>You can add more information in <tag>info</tag> to your heart's desire but the
            renderer won't use nor display it.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <sect3 xml:id="keyword-usage">
        <title>Keyword usage</title>

        <para>The <tag>info</tag> element must contain at least one keyword. This is used to create
          an index on subject. Multiple keywords can be specified by repeating the
            <tag>keyword</tag> element.</para>
        <para>Keywords are always written <emphasis>lower-case</emphasis> and must not contain
          spaces.</para>
        <para>The following keywords are in use:</para>
        <table>
          <title>Keyword usage</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colwidth="30%"/>
            <colspec/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Keyword</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Meaning</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <!-- Please keep in alphabetical order. -->
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    <code>application-development</code>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Information related to using eXIst-db as an application platform.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    <code>exist</code>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Anything related to eXist-db itself, like legal statements, how to send in
                    bugs, etc.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    <code>getting-started</code>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Basic information on how to get eXist-db up and running.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    <code>java-development</code>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Information about programming Java for or in eXist-db.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    <code>indexing</code>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Information related to eXist-db's indexes.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    <code>installation</code>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Information about installing eXist-db</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    <code>interfaces</code>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Information about specific interfaces eXist-db provides</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    <code>operations</code>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>How to keep eXist-db up and running, not from a programmer's but from a
                    system maintenance point of view.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    <code>xquery</code>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Information related to XQuery (or XPath) in general or eXist-db's specific
                    features of the language.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <warning>
          <para>Tables like the one above tend to get outdated sooner or later (because somebody
            adds/deletes a keyword and forgets to update it). To see all the keywords actually in
            use, look at the index-by-subject section of the <link xlink:href="documentation">main documentation page</link>.</para>
          <para>Watch out: For legibility reasons the keywords there are presented
              <emphasis>capitalized</emphasis>. Remember that in the article documents the keywords
            must be stated in <emphasis>lower-case</emphasis>!</para>
        </warning>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Supported block elements</title>

      <para>The following Docbook 5 block level elements are supported for the eXist-db
        documentation set. Unsupported elements will be flagged when the content is rendered (you'll
        see a bold red error message in the middle of your story).</para>

      <variablelist spacing="compact">

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Paragraphs</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use <tag>para</tag> to tag text as a paragraph.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Section levels</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>You can use <tag>sect1</tag> up to <tag>sect3</tag> as section levels. Only
                <tag>sect1</tag> and <tag>sect2</tag> will appear in the table of contents. Markup
              in titles is ignored.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Lists</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>You can use either <tag>itemizedlist</tag> (with bullets) or
                <tag>orderedlist</tag> (with numbers).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Variable list</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A <tag>variablelist</tag> is a bit of a misnomer. It creates lists like this one
              (the list of block elements you're looking at now), so it's useful for much more than
              variables.</para>
            <para>If you want a narrow left column (like this one), add
                <code>spacing="compact"</code>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Notes</term>
          <listitem>
            <note>
              <title>About notes</title>
              <para>The <tag>note</tag> element creates a noticeable layout like this. The title is
                optional.</para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Warnings</term>
          <listitem>
            <warning>
              <para>Both the <tag>warning</tag> and <tag>important</tag> element produce a layout
                like this. The only difference is the text of the header. You can optionally add a
                title.</para>
            </warning>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Examples</term>
          <listitem>
            <example>
              <title>An example of an example</title>
              <para>The <tag>example</tag> element produces an example in a layout like this. It
                must have a <tag>title</tag> element, which is displayed at the bottom:</para>
            </example>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry xml:id="listings" xreflabel="Listings">
          <term>Listings</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Anything you want to present as a program listing or other fixed text (e.g. a
              sequence of commands) must be enclosed in a <tag>programlisting</tag> element. There
              are two ways to provide the actual contents of the listing:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Simply enclose the text in the <tag>programlisting</tag> element. Use CDATA if
                  necessary. Any markup will be ignored.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Add an <code>xlink:href</code> attribute
                    (<code>xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"</code>) with a reference to a
                  file containing the text. This must be a <emphasis>relative</emphasis> reference
                  (e.g. <code>xlink:href="listings/mylisting.txt"</code>). The contents of the
                  element will be ignored.</para>
                <para>Using the <code>xlink:href</code> attribute is definitely
                    <emphasis>not</emphasis> the proper way to do this. It should be done by using
                  an <tag>xi:include</tag> element inside <tag>programlisting</tag>. However,
                  current XInclude limitations in eXist prevent this from working properly (it can
                  only include XML, not text). So therefore this workaround.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Listings have two display modes:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>If it's a listing in some language (like XML), add a <code>language</code>
                  attribute with the name of the language. The render will try to add some color
                  coding (if it recognizes it). Here is a listing with
                  <code>language="xml"</code>:</para>
                <programlisting xlink:href="listings/example-xml.xml" language="xml"/>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>For a straight listing, don't add a <code>language</code> attribute. Here is
                  the same listing as above without:</para>
                <programlisting xlink:href="listings/example-xml.xml"/>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Figures</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use <tag>figure</tag> or <tag>informalfigure</tag> to add an asset. The effect of
              both elements is almost the same, the only difference is that an informal figure has
              no title. Docbook prescribes an elaborate XML construction, here is an example:</para>
            <programlisting xlink:href="listings/figure.xml" language="xml"/>
            <para>This produces:</para>
            <figure>
              <title>Figure title here</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="assets/powered-by-exist.gif" width="50%"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>The <code>width</code> attribute is the only size-related attribute used. It sets
              the width relative to the available horizontal space. If you don't specify a width a
              default of 75% is used.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Tables</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use <tag>table</tag> or <tag>informaltable</tag> to add a table. The effect of
              both elements is almost the same, the only difference is that an informal table has no
              title. Table layout is kept simple and straight. Here is how a simple table looks
              like:</para>
            <programlisting xlink:href="listings/table.xml" language="xml"/>
            <para>And this is the result:</para>
            <table>
              <title>Table title</title>
              <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colwidth="30%"/>
                <colspec/>
                <thead>
                  <row>
                    <entry>
                      <para>Col 1</para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                      <para>Col 2</para>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry>
                      <para>Bla</para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                      <para>More bla</para>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>
                      <para>Blegh</para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                      <para>More blegh</para>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Supported inline elements</title>
      <para>The following inline elements are supported:</para>
      <warning>
        <para>Inline elements in <tag>title</tag> elements are <emphasis>not</emphasis> supported.
          Any markup in titles is ignored.</para>
      </warning>

      <variablelist spacing="compact">

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Emphasis</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use <tag>emphasis</tag> for <emphasis>emphasizing</emphasis>.</para>
            <para>Although discouraged, you can request a specific emphasis type:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Use <code>role="bold"</code> for <emphasis role="bold">bold
                    emphasis</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Use <code>role="underline"</code> for <emphasis role="underline">underlined
                    emphasis</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Use <code>role="italic"</code> for <emphasis role="italic">italic
                    emphasis</emphasis>. This looks the same as no <code>role</code> attribute but
                  produces an <tag>i</tag> instead of an <tag>em</tag>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>GUI Items</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use <tag>guimenuitem</tag> around anything referring to choices in a GUI, for
              instance <guimenuitem>menu</guimenuitem> choices. The effect is now simple italic but
              that might change later.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Code</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use <tag>code</tag> or <tag>literal</tag> for literals, pieces of code, commands,
              etc. The result will be <code>mono-spaced</code>.</para>
            <para>The general guideline is to use this for everything that lists pieces of code,
              attributes, variable names, etc. For elements use <tag>tag</tag>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Tags</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A <tag>tag</tag> element surrounds its content with &lt; and &gt; and formats it
              like code. Meant to make life easier: <code><![CDATA[<tag>xxx</tag>]]></code> is the
              shorter version of <code><![CDATA[<code>&lt;xxx&gt;</code>]]></code>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Figures</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use the <tag>inlinemediaobject</tag> to add an asset inline in the text. Docbook
              prescribes an elaborate XML construction, here is an example of a paragraph with an
              inline figure:</para>
            <programlisting xlink:href="listings/inlinefigure.xml" language="xml"/>
            <para>This produces:</para>
            <para>There is an asset <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="assets/webstart.small.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
              </inlinemediaobject> here.</para>
            <para>The <code>width</code> attribute is the only size-related attribute recognized and
              used.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Internal links</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>You can create a link to any block level element with the <tag>xref</tag> element.
              To do so, give the target an identifier by using <code>xml:id="..."</code> and mention
              this identifier in the <code>linkend</code> attribute of the <tag>xref</tag>. </para>
            <para>You can generate a specific link text by adding an <code>xreflabel</code>
              attribute to the <emphasis>target</emphasis> element, like here: <xref linkend="test-list-for-ref"/>. If this attribute is not present on the target its
              title is used, like this: <xref linkend="writing-guidelines"/>. If there is no title,
              the name of the element is presented.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>External links</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Links to external sources are done with the <tag>link</tag> element. Place the
              target's full URI in the <code>xlink:href</code> attribute. For instance,
                <code><![CDATA[<link xlink:href="http://exist-db.org/exist/apps/homepage/index.html">]]></code>
              links to the <link xlink:href="http://exist-db.org/exist/apps/homepage/index.html" condition="_blank">eXist home page</link>.</para>
            <para>To open the link on a new page, add <code>condition="_blank"</code>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Article links</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>To create a link to another article in this documentation set, also use the
                <tag>link</tag> element. However, use the target's document name (without the
                <code>.xml</code> extension) as the link address. For instance,
                <code><![CDATA[<link xlink:href="documentation">]]></code> links to the <link xlink:href="documentation">documentation home page</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Generating indexes</title>

      <para>Indexes can be automagicly generated. For examples have a look at the <link xlink:href="documentation">documentation home page</link>. There are three
        variations:</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Alphabetical index on title</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Add a <code>role="indexontitle"</code> attribute to a <tag>para</tag> element. An
              index on title will be generated after it.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Index on keyword, all</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Add a <code>role="indexonkeyword"</code> attribute to a <tag>para</tag> element.
              An index on keywords (as specified in the <tag>info</tag> element, see <xref linkend="keyword-usage"/>) will be generated after it.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Index on keyword, single</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Add a <code>role="indexonkeyword:somekeyword"</code> attribute to a
                <tag>para</tag> element to generate a list of articles with this specific keyword
              (as specified in the <tag>info</tag> element, see <xref linkend="keyword-usage"/>).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Additional tools</title>

    <para>There are two additional pages in the documentation app to help authors and
      editors:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
                    <link xlink:href="editorial-view.html" condition="_blank">Editorial view</link>
                </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The editorial view provides an overview of all the articles and their incoming and
            outgoing links.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
                    <link xlink:href="diagnostics.html" condition="_blank">Diagnostics</link>
                </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Performs limited diagnostics. Checks whether the outgoing links in articles
            to other articles, listings and assets are ok. Also checks whether there are
            unreferenced (and therefore superfluous) listings and assets.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

  </sect1>

</article>
