<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>Using collections in eXist-db</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>getting-started</keyword>
      <keyword>application-development</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>eXist supports the concept of document collections. Collections are groupings of both XML
    documents, binary documents and other collections, much like directories on disk. This document
    describes some design considerations deciding what collections to use and how to partition your
    data into XML files.</para>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Using collections to group your XML documents</title>

    <para>eXist organizes its documents in collections, like file systems use directories. </para>
    <para> By convention the root collection of eXist is called <code>/db</code>, much like
        <code>/</code> is the root collection of a UNIX file system. Users create sub-collections
      under <code>/db</code> collection to store data. </para>
    <para> Collections contain two types of things, files or sub-collections. Files in eXist are
      called "resources". Well-formed XML documents are indexed by eXist. Non XML files are stored
      as binary objects. </para>
    <para> In general, you can group XML data files into sub-collections in whatever way is most
      convenient and meaningful to your organization. For example, if you are collecting daily sales
      data in XML format you can place daily sales orders for each month into a separate collection
      for that year and month. Sales for October 2012 would for instance be in
        <code>/db/sales/data/2010/10</code>. Using dates to separate your data is quite common. This
      allows you to remove old records by simply removing a year or month-level collection.</para>
    <para>eXist-db can query all XML documents in any collection or any sub-collection to find a
      document. Unlike a file system, you don't need to know what year or month the data is in. You
      only need to know the root collection to start your queries. eXist will find your documents
      from there.</para>
    <para>How you create collections should reflect the logical structure of your data. You can
      store tens of thousands of XML files in a single collection without a problem. However this
      makes viewing the files challenging using a folder-interface. Therefore collections with under
      ~1,000 XML files are preferred by most collection designers.</para>
    <para>Collections allow you to create database triggers for the documents within a collection.
      These triggers are executed when a document is created, updated, deleted or viewed. </para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Partitioning data</title>

    <para>eXist-db is designed to be flexible with the amount of data stored in a collection or XML
      file. It works equally well if you have a single file with 10,000 sales transactions or 10,000
      individual transaction files. The query you write won't need to be changed if you alter how
      the files are grouped, as long as you reference the root collection of your documents. </para>
    <para>There are however some design considerations when you're performing concurrent reads and
      writes on a document collection. eXist-db only guarantees atomic operations within a single
      document. So placing two different data elements that must stay consistent within an single
      document is good practice. </para>
    <para> You many also want to use a database lock on a document or a sub-document to prevent
      other processes from modifying it. This feature is similar to file locks that are performed on
      a shared file in a file system. Locking a document helps avoiding conflicts when multiple
      people attempt to edit the same document at the same time. You can also calculate hash tags on
      a document as you load it into an editor to verify that it has not been modified by someone
      else while you have been editing it. This strategy, and the use of the etags HTML element,
      helps you avoid the missing updates problem.</para>
    <para>Native XML database collections can be used as a "primary taxonomy" to store documents of
      different types. This is similar to the categorization of a book in a library where the book
      is found according to its primary subject. However, unlike a physical book, a document can
      contain many different category elements and thus does not have to be copied or moved between
      collections. An XML document can contain keywords and category terms that allow search tools
      to find documents that fit multiple subject categories.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Security considerations</title>

    <para>Collections can be used as a way to group documents according to who can access them. You
      may have an internal policy that only allows users with a particular role to modify a
      document. eXist-db provides basic UNIX-style permissions on each collection to allow only some
      groups to have write access to a collection of documents (see <link xlink:href="security">Security</link> for more information).</para>
    <para>An example of using security-based collections to group web application functionality: </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Use the <code>/db/apps</code> folder to hold all your applications</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Use <code>/db/apps/books</code> folder to hold your books application.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Use a <code>/db/apps/books/data</code> to store the actual book data. Only users with
          edit rights can change the data in the collection. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Use a <code>/db/apps/books/views</code> to store read-only transform views of the book
          data.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Use a <code>/db/apps/books/edit</code> for editing tools. Only users with edit rights
          will be able to access this folder.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Use a <code>/db/apps/books/admin</code> for administrative tools. For example changing
          code-tables in selection lists or tools that re-index the collection.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Use a <code>/db/apps/books/unit-tests</code> to store unit tests for the books
          application. Only developers will need this collection loaded on their system.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>


  </sect1>
</article>