<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>Application Server Configuration</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>operations</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>This section deals with the configuration of the eXist-db Application Server in eXist-db's main configuration file
    <code>conf.xml</code>.</para>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="conf.xml">
    <title>Main configuration file</title>

    <para>The main configuration file for <literal>eXist-db</literal> is called <literal>conf.xml</literal>, which is loaded from different
      directories depending on the server set-up (see <link xlink:href="deployment">Server Deployment</link> for more information).
      Specifically:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you installed the standalone eXist-db distribution with the installer, the <literal>conf.xml</literal> file located in the root
          directory of the distribution (as specified by the system property <literal>exist.home</literal>).</para>
        <para/>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If eXist-db is installed as a web application (packaged in a <literal>.war</literal> file) in a servlet engine like tomcat, <literal>
            conf.xml</literal> is read from the <literal>WEB-INF</literal> directory of the web application.</para>
        <para>eXist-db normally has no access to files outside the context in which it is running when it is deployed as part of a web application.
          Therefore, when eXist is deployed in this way, the configuration is read from the <literal>WEB-INF</literal> directory.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The configuration file <literal>conf.xml</literal> is divided into eleven sections:</para>
    <variablelist spacing="compact">
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <tag>db-connection</tag>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Configures the storage back-end.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <tag>repository</tag>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Settings for the package repository.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <tag>binary-manager</tag>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Settings for the Binary Manager.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <tag>indexer</tag>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Controls the indexing process.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <tag>scheduler</tag>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Job scheduler for system or user jobs. </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <tag>parser</tag>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Default settings for parsing structured documents.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <tag>serializer</tag>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Default settings for the serializer (external data representation).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <tag>transformer</tag>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Default settings for the XSLT Transformer.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <tag>validation</tag>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Settings for XML validation.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <tag>xquery</tag>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Define (built-in) modules that contain xQuery functions.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <tag>xupdate</tag>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Configuration options related to XUpdate processing.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>The following sections describe the most commonly modified of the above elements, including how to change the default behavior of eXist-db's
      handling of whitespace characters.</para>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->
    <sect2>
      <title>
                <tag>db-connection</tag> element</title>

      <para>This element contains basic default storage settings for eXist-db, including memory and system limits. Only one <tag>db-connection</tag>
        should be specified. An example configuration for the native back-end is shown below:</para>

      <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-1.xml"/>

      <sect3>
        <title>
                    <tag>db-connection</tag> attributes</title>

        <variablelist spacing="compact">
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>database</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This attribute selects a database system type. Since relational database back-ends are no longer supported by the current release
                of eXist, only <literal>native</literal> is available.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>files</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This attribute specifies the directory where the native back-end will keep its database files, and so it is necessary that this
                directory exists. If a relative path is specified, it will be based on the root directory as defined in the
                  <literal>exist.home</literal> system property. If this data directory does not have write permissions (see <link xlink:href="security">User Authentication and Access Control</link>), eXist will internally switch to <emphasis>read-only
                  mode</emphasis> such that any attempt to change the database will throw an exception.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>cacheSize</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This attribute sets the maximum amount of main memory used by all page buffers (i.e. assuming all page buffers are at full
                capacity). The database uses this parameter to calculate the maximum size of each internal cache. You can increase this value if your
                system allows for greater memory use.</para>
              <para>While indexing documents, eXist will reserve the amount of memory specified in cacheSize - even if not all caches are filled - and
                will not use it for temporary data.</para>
              <para>The cacheSize should not be more than half of the size of the JVM heap size (set by the JVM <code>-Xmx</code> parameter). If the
                JVM heap is less than 512 megabyte, the cacheSize should even be smaller, e.g. 1/3.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>collectionCache</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Determines the size of the collection cache, which is a separate caching space. Usually this setting does not need to be changed
                unless you really have more than a few thousand collections in the db. Increase it carefully, maybe up to 128M.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>pageSize</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This specifies the number of bytes used for internal data and B-tree pages. This should be equal to or a multiple of the page size
                used by the filesystem (usually a multiple of 4096).</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>nodesBuffer</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Size of the temporary buffer used by eXist for caching index data while indexing a document. If set to -1, eXist will use the
                entire free memory to buffer index entries and will flush the cache once the memory is full.</para>
              <para>If set to a value &gt; 0, the buffer will be fixed to the given size. The specified number corresponds to the number of nodes the
                buffer can hold, in thousands. Usually, a good default could be <code>nodesBuffer="1000"</code>.</para>
              <para>The default setting, nodesBuffer="-1", can be problematic if you frequently need to store large documents in a multi-user
                environment. In this case, the index operation may consume most of the memory resources, which means that concurrent threads will be
                slowed down or even come to a halt.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>
                    <tag>db-connection</tag>/<tag>pool</tag> element</title>

        <para>These settings control the internal database connection pool.</para>
        <variablelist spacing="compact">
          <title>
            <tag>pool</tag> Attributes</title>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>min</code> | <code>max</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>These options specify the minimum and maximum size of the connection pool. This pool restricts the number of parallel (basic)
                operations that can be executed by the database. Settings should be somewhere between 1 and 20. </para>
              <para>Please note that this has nothing to do with the HTTP and XMLRPC server settings - these servers have their own connection
                pools.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>sync-period</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This option defines how often the database will flush its internal buffers to disk (in milliseconds). The sync-thread will
                interrupt normal database operation after the specified time and write all dirty pages to disk. It also writes a checkpoint to the
                transaction log. In case of a database crash, only transactions which started after the last checkpoint have to be redone or rolled
                back. The sync-period should thus not be set too long.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>wait-before-shutdown</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This option specifies the maximum amount of time (in milliseconds) that the database will allow for any running processes to
                complete upon database shutdown. After that, eXist will try to kill the remaining processes.</para>
              <para>If wait-before-shutdown is set to a positive number, eXist will stop the db after the specified timeout, even if there were still
                running database operations. In this case, no checkpoint will be written to the transaction log. If there were any open transactions,
                eXist will trigger a recovery run after restart.</para>
              <para>If wait-before-shutdown is set to -1, eXist will not shut down before all active database operations returned. This is a safe
                setting, but it may require a manual intervention to stop the JVM.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>
                    <tag>db-connection</tag>/<tag>query-pool</tag> element</title>

        <para>This element configures the global pool for compiled XQuery expressions. For each XQuery, a maximum number of compiled expressions are
          kept in the pool, and is removed if it hasn't been used for the defined timeout. The XQuery pool is multi-threaded.</para>
        <para>
          <tag>query-pool</tag> Attributes:</para>
        <variablelist spacing="compact">
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>max-stack-size</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The maximum number of queries in the query-pool.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>size</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The number of copies of the same query kept in the query-pool. Value <code>"-1"</code> effectively disables caching. Queries
                cannot be shared by threads, each thread needs a private copy of a query.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>timeout</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The amount of time that a query will be cached in the query-pool in milliseconds.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>timeout-check-interval</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The time between checking for timed out queries. For value <code>"-1"</code> the time out is switched off, resulting cached
                queries to remain in the cache forever.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>
                    <tag>db-connection</tag>/<tag>recovery</tag> element</title>

        <para>This element configures the journalling and recovery of the database. With recovery enabled, the database is able to recover from an
          unclean database shutdown due to, for example, power failures, OS reboots, and hanging processes. For this to work correctly, all database
          operations must be logged to a journal file. The location, size and other parameters for this file can be set using the <tag>recovery</tag>
          element.</para>
        <para>
                    <tag>recovery</tag> Attributes:</para>
        <variablelist spacing="compact">
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>enabled</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>If this attribute is set to <literal>yes</literal>, automatic recovery is enabled.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>size</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This attributes sets the maximum allowed size of the journal file. Once the journal reaches this limit, a checkpoint will be
                triggered and the journal will be cleaned. However, the database waits for running transactions to return before processing this
                checkpoint. In the event one of these transactions writes a lot of data to the journal file, the file will grow until the transaction
                has completed. Hence, the size limit is not enforced in all cases.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>journal-dir</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This attribute sets the directory where journal files are to be written. If no directory is specified, the default path is to the
                  <literal>data</literal> directory.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>sync-on-commit</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This attribute determines whether or not to protect the journal during operating system failures. That is, it determines whether
                the database forces a file-sync on the journal after every commit. If this attribute is set to <literal>yes</literal>, the journal is
                protected against operating system failures. However, this will slow performance - especially on Windows systems. If set to
                  <literal>no</literal>, eXist will rely on the operating system to flush out the journal contents to disk. In the worst case
                scenario, in which there is a complete system failure, some committed transactions might not have yet been written to the journal, and
                so will be rolled back.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>group-commit</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>If set to <code>yes</code>, eXist will not sync the journal file immediately after every transaction commit. Instead, it will wait
                until the current file buffer (32kb) is really full. This can speed up eXist on some systems where a file sync is an expensive
                operation (mainly windows XP; not necessary on Linux).</para>
              <para>However, <literal>group-comit="yes"</literal> will increase the chance that an already committed operation is rolled back after a
                database crash.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>force-restart</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Try to restart the db even if crash recovery failed. This is dangerous because there might be corruptions inside the data files.
                The transaction log will be cleared, all locks removed and the db re-indexed.</para>
              <para>Set this option to <code>yes</code> if you need to make sure that the db is online, even after a fatal crash. Errors encountered
                during recovery are written to the log files. Scan the log files to see if any problems occurred.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>consistency-check</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>If set to <code>yes</code>, a consistency check will be run on the database if an error was detected during crash recovery. This
                option requires force-restart to be set to <code>yes</code>, otherwise it has no effect.</para>
              <para>The consistency check outputs a report to the directory {files}/sanity and if inconsistencies are found in the db, it writes an
                emergency backup to the same directory.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>
                    <tag>db-connection</tag>/<tag>watchdog</tag> element</title>

        <para>This is the global configuration for the <emphasis>query watchdog</emphasis>. The watchdog monitors all query processes, and can
          terminate any long-running queries if they exceed one of the predefined limits. These limits are as follows:</para>

        <para>
                    <tag>watchdog</tag> Attributes:</para>
        <variablelist spacing="compact">
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>query-timeout</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This attribute sets the maximum amount of time (expressed in milliseconds) that the query can take before it is killed. The
                setting can be overwritten in an XQuery by specifying the option <literal>exist:timeout</literal>:</para>
              <programlisting language="xquery">declare option exist:timeout "time-in-ms";</programlisting>
              <para>Please check the documentation on <link xlink:href="xquery">XQuery options</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>output-size-limit</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This attribute limits the size of XML fragments constructed using XQuery, and thus sets the maximum amount of main memory a query
                is allowed to use. This limit is expressed as the maximum number of nodes allowed for an in-memory DOM tree. The purpose of this
                option is to avoid memory shortages on the server in cases where users are allowed to run queries that produce very large output
                fragments. The setting can be overwritten in an XQuery by specifying the option <literal>exist:output-size-limit</literal>:</para>
              <programlisting language="xquery">declare option exist:output-size-limit "size-hint";</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>
                    <tag>db-connection</tag>/<tag>default-permissions</tag> element</title>

        <para>Specifies the default permissions for all resources and collections in eXist (see <link xlink:href="security.xml"> User Authentication
            and Access Control</link>). When this is not configured, the default <literal>mod</literal> (similar to the Unix <code>chmod</code>
          command) is set to <literal>0775</literal> in the <literal>resources</literal> and <literal>collections</literal> attributes. A different
          default value may be set for a database instance. Local overrides are also possible.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>
                <tag>indexer</tag> element </title>

      <para>This element sets parameters on how XML files are to be indexed by eXist. An example configuration is shown below:</para>
      <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-4.xml"/>

      <sect3>
        <title>
          <tag>indexer</tag> attributes</title>

        <variablelist spacing="compact">
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>caseSensitive</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Specifies whether string comparisons are to be case-sensitive. This option applies to XPath equality tests (i.e. the
                  <literal>=</literal> operator), as well as functions such as <literal>contains()</literal>, <literal>starts-with()</literal> and
                  <literal>ends-with()</literal>. </para>
              <para>This setting does not apply to operators or functions of the full-text index (e.g. <literal>&amp;=</literal>,
                  <literal>|=</literal>, <literal>near()</literal>) nor the n-gram index, which are <emphasis>never</emphasis> case-sensitive</para>
              <warning>
                <para>Setting <literal>caseSensitive="no"</literal> violates the XQuery specs! The option should be regarded as a dirty workaround,
                  which will be removed in the future. Please use the n-gram or full-text indexes for case-insensitive queries or - if that is
                  impossible - specify a <link xlink:href="xquery.xml#collations">collation</link>.</para>
              </warning>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>suppress-whitespace</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Specifies how the <tag>indexer</tag> is to treat whitespace at the start or end of a character sequence. This option
                  <emphasis>only</emphasis> applies to newly stored files, and therefore changing it has no effect on previously stored documents.
                Possible values for this attribute are:</para>
              <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <literal>leading</literal> - Suppresses leading whitespace.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <literal>trailing</literal> - Suppresses trailing whitespace.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <literal>both</literal> - Suppresses leading and trailing whitespace.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <literal>none</literal> - Preserves all whitespace.</para>
                </listitem>
              </orderedlist>
              <para>Note that suppressing whitespace at the start or end of character sequences does effectively change the document!</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>preserve-whitespace-mixed-content</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>controls how ignorable whitespace is handled. If set to <literal>no</literal>, ignorable whitespace, e.g. between the end tag of
                an element and the start tag of another, will not be stored into the persistent DOM. This leads to a smaller DOM and usually increases
                the readability of the XML. Ignorable whitespace is not considered as a part of the logical document model, so removing it doesn't
                change the document.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>tokenizer</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This attribute invokes the Java class used to tokenize a string into a sequence of single words or tokens, which are stored to the
                full-text index. Currently only <literal>SimpleTokenizer</literal> is available.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>index-depth</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This attribute specifies the depth of the DOM index, or the tree level up to which elements will be added to the index. For
                example, a value of <literal>2</literal> results in the document root node and all its child elements being indexed; a value of
                  <literal>1</literal> only indexes the root node.</para>
              <para>The DOM index maps unique node identifiers to the nodes' storage locations in the DOM file. Generating this index is time- and
                memory-consuming. It is furthermore primarily needed to access nodes by their unique node identifier, for example, when serializing
                XML data for query results or XUpdate - which are operations not normally considered time-critical. Moreover, most XPath expressions
                can do without this index since they use short-cuts to access the node directly.</para>
              <para>Normally only top-level elements are added to the DOM index, whereas attributes and text nodes are always excluded. This results
                in much smaller index sizes and, consequently, a smaller <literal>dom.dbx</literal> file size. Usually, setting the
                  <literal>index-depth</literal> to a value of <literal>2</literal> offers a reasonable compromise of index size and
                performance.</para>
              <para>However, if your documents are <emphasis>deeply-structured</emphasis>, you might consider increasing this setting to a level of 3,
                4 or 5. For example, if the longest path from the document root to an element node has greater than ten node levels, an
                  <literal>index-depth</literal> setting of <literal>4</literal> or <literal>5</literal> would probably help to increase overall query
                performance for some types of queries.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>validation</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This attribute defines the default setting for the validation of documents by the XML parser. If it is set to
                  <literal>no</literal>, documents will never be validated against an existing DTD or schema. A value of <literal>auto</literal> will
                leave document validation to the SAX parser.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>
                    <tag>indexer</tag>/<tag>modules</tag> element </title>

        <para>This section configures optional indexing modules. Beginning with version 1.2, eXist features a modularized indexing architecture, which
          allows new indexes to be plugged into the indexing pipeline. The <tag>modules</tag> section lists and configures the indexes that will be
          available to the database:</para>
        <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-5.xml"/>
        <para>The only common attributes for each <tag>module</tag> element are <literal>class</literal> and <literal>id</literal>. The other
          attributes, as well as any nested elements, are specific to the index implementation. Detailed information is available in the article on
            <link xlink:href="indexing.xml#moduleconf">Configuring Database Indexes</link>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>
                    <tag>indexer</tag>/<tag>stopwords</tag> element </title>

        <para>The <literal>file</literal> attribute for this element points to a file containing a list of <emphasis>stop-words</emphasis>. Stop-words
          are not added to the full-text index.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>
                    <tag>indexer</tag>/<tag>index</tag> element </title>

        <para>This configuration element specifies the default index settings. These settings are applied if neither the collection nor any of its
          ancestors provide a collection configuration.</para>
        <para>Configuring indexes via the default settings is <emphasis>not</emphasis> recommended. If you need a global collection configuration,
          store one for the root collection <literal>/db</literal>. For more information, see <link xlink:href="indexing.xml">Configuring
            Indexes</link>.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>
                <tag>scheduler</tag> element </title>

      <para>This section is used to configure asynchronous jobs with eXist's internal scheduler. Three types of jobs are supported:</para>
      <variablelist spacing="compact">
        <varlistentry>
          <term>startup jobs</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Startup jobs are executed once during database startup, but before the database becomes available. These jobs are synchronous. The
              database is blocked to outside requests and no other operations will run at the same time.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>system jobs</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>System jobs require the database to be in a consistent state. The scheduler will run them in an exclusive environment. Once the job
              is triggered, the database will block all new requests and wait for running operations to complete. It then executes the job. All other
              database operations will be stopped until the job returns or throws an exception. Any exception will be caught and a warning written to
              the log.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>user jobs</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>User jobs may be scheduled at any time and may be mutually exclusive or non-exclusive</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>Below is an example which configures a <link xlink:href="backup">BackupSystemTask</link>: </para>

      <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-6.xml"/>
      <para>Each job is configured in a <tag>job</tag> element which accepts a number of standard attributes:</para>
      <sect3>
        <title>
          <tag>job</tag> attributes</title>

        <variablelist spacing="compact">
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>type</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The type of the job to schedule. Must be either <code>startup</code>, <code>system</code> or <code>user</code>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>class</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>If the job is written in Java this should be the name of the class that extends either</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                                        <code>org.exist.scheduler.StartupJob</code>
                                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                                        <code>org.exist.storage.SystemTask</code>
                                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                                        <code>org.exist.scheduler.UserJavaJob</code>
                                    </para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>xquery</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>If the job is written in XQuery (not suitable for system jobs) this should be a path to the XQuery stored in the database, e.g.
                  <literal>/db/myCollection/myJob.xql</literal>. XQuery job's will be launched under the <code>guest</code> account initially. The
                running XQuery may switch permissions through calls to <literal>xmldb:login()</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>cron-trigger</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>To define a firing pattern for the Job using <code>cron</code> style syntax. Not applicable to start-up jobs.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>unschedule-on-exception</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Either <code>true</code> (default) or <code>false</code>. If <code>true</code> and an exception is encountered the job is
                unscheduled for further execution until a restart. Otherwise, the exception is ignored.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>period</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Can be used to define an explicit period for firing the job instead of a <code>cron</code> style syntax. Expressed in
                milliseconds. Not applicable to start-up jobs.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>delay</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Can be used for periodic jobs to delay the start of a job. If unspecified jobs will start as soon as the database and scheduler
                are initialised.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>repeat</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Can be used for periodic jobs to define how many periods a job should be executed. If unspecified, jobs will repeat
                indefinitely.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para>Every job can take additional parameters, which are passed as name/value pairs.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>
                <tag>serializer</tag> element </title>

      <para>The serializer is responsible for serializing XML documents or document fragments back into XML. This configuration element defines
        default settings for various parameters, which can also be specified programmatically. All settings can be overwritten by XQuery <link xlink:href="xquery.xml#serialization">serialization options</link>.</para>
      <sect3>
        <title>
                    <tag>serializer</tag> attributes</title>

        <variablelist spacing="compact">
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>enable-xinclude</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This attribute determines whether <tag>xinclude</tag> tags are to be expanded during serialization. Setting the value to
                  <literal>false</literal> will leave <tag>xinclude</tag> tags unexpanded.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>enable-xsl</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Setting this attribute to <literal>true</literal> tells the serializer to pass its output to an XSL stylesheet when it encounters
                an XSL processing-instruction at the start of the document.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>add-exist-id</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This attribute tells the serializer to add additional debug attributes to each element. This information includes the internal
                identifier of the node and source document. Values:</para>
              <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <literal>all</literal> - Adds debug information to every node in the output.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <literal>element</literal> - Adds debug information to top-level elements only.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <literal>none</literal> (default) - Disables debugging feature.</para>
                </listitem>
              </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>indent</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The serializer defaults to pretty-print the resulting XML source code. Setingt this option to <literal>no</literal> disables
                pretty-printing.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>match-tagging-elements</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The database can highlight matches in the text content of a node by tagging the matching text string with <tag>exist:match</tag>.
                This only works for XPath expressions using the full-text index. Set the parameter to <literal>yes</literal> to
                  <emphasis>disable</emphasis> this feature.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>
                <tag>transformer</tag> element </title>

      <para>This section determines which XSLT processor will be used by eXist. By default, eXist relies on Saxon.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>
                <tag>validation</tag> element </title>

      <para>Defines the default validation settings active when parsing XML and links to catalog files. Catalog files are used to locate DTDs, schemas
        and resolve external entities in general.</para>
      <para>Please refer to the corresponding documentation on <link xlink:href="validation.xml">XML Validation</link>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>
                <tag>xupdate</tag> element</title>

      <para>Inserting new nodes into a document can lead to fragmentation in the DOM storage file. eXist will thus trigger a de-fragmentation run if
        the fragmentation exceeds a certain limit. The frequency of such de-fragmentation runs can be configured in the <tag>xupdate</tag> section.
        The main parameter is called <literal>allowed-fragmentation</literal>:</para>

      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xupdate allowed-fragmentation="20" enable-consistency-checks="no" />]]></programlisting>
      <sect3>
        <title>
          <tag>xupdate</tag> attributes</title>

        <variablelist spacing="compact">
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>allowed-fragmentation</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This attribute defines the maximum number of page splits allowed within a document before a de-fragmentation run is
                triggered.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>enable-consistency-checks</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>This attribute is for or debugging purposes only. If the parameter is set to <literal>yes</literal>, a <emphasis>consistency
                  check</emphasis> will be run on modified documents after every XUpdate request. This checks whether the persistent DOM is complete,
                and all pointers in the structural index point to valid storage addresses that contain valid nodes.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>
                <tag>xquery</tag> element</title>

      <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-8.xml"/>
      <para>The <tag>xquery</tag> section is used to enable/disable certain core features of the XQuery engine. It also lists the XQuery modules that
        will be known to the query engine by default.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>
                    <tag>xquery</tag> attributes</title>

        <variablelist spacing="compact">
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>enable-java-binding</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Set to <code>yes</code> to enable the <link xlink:href="xquery">java binding</link>. Giving users full access to all
                Java classes should be considered a security risk and the feature is thus disabled by default.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>disable-deprecated-functions</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Set to <code>yes</code> to enable XQuery functions marked as deprecated.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>enforce-index-use</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>controls if available range indexes should be used if only some collections in the context set define a matching index. Available
                settings are: </para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                                        <code>always</code> to always use an index, even if it does not apply to the entire set of collections being queried.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                                        <code>strict</code> to only use indexes if they are defined for the entire collection set.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>

              <para> </para>
              <para>For example, if you have two collections: <code>/db/one</code> and <code>/db/two</code>, and you define a range index on a certain
                element <tag>node</tag> in <code>/db/one</code>, but not in <code>/db/two</code>, the query engine would not use the index with
                setting <code>strict</code> if you query both collections. At compile time, eXist doesn't know if <tag>node</tag> exists in both
                collections and will not use the index if it determines that an index definition does only apply to a part of the collection set being
                queried. To use the index, you would need to start your XPath expression with a call to <code>collection()</code>, selecting the
                correct collection with the index defined.</para>
              <para>If <code>enforce-index-use</code> is set to <code>always</code>, the query engine only checks if one collection in the collection
                set has a matching index defined on it. This may lead to an incomplete query result if one forgets certain collections.</para>
              <para>In other words, when <code>enforce-index-use</code> is set to "always", it is the query writer's responsibility to make sure
                indexes are defined properly. But experience has shown it is easier for users to understand that a certain result is incomplete
                because an index is missing, whereas they have problems to see that a performance issue is caused by inconsistent indexing. </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>raise-error-on-failed-retrieval</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Set to <literal>yes</literal> if a call to <literal>doc()</literal>, <literal>xmldb:document()</literal>,
                  <literal>collection()</literal> or <literal>xmldb:xcollection()</literal> should raise an error (FODC0002) when an XML resource can
                not be retrieved.</para>
              <para>Set to <literal>no</literal> if a call to <literal>doc()</literal>, <literal>xmldb:document()</literal>,
                  <literal>collection()</literal> or <literal>xmldb:xcollection()</literal> should return an empty sequence when an XML resource can
                not be retrieved.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>enable-query-rewriting</code>o</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>the query engine can often achieve considerable performance improvements by rewriting an XQuery expression into a more efficient
                form (see the documentation about <link xlink:href="indexing">indexing</link>). However, these features are relatively
                new. If you have doubts about the correctness of a query result, you may temporarily set <literal>enable-query-rewriting</literal> to
                  <literal>no</literal> and see if the result changes in any way. If it does, you have hit a bug which should be reported. </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
                            <code>backwardCompatible</code>
                        </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>|Set to <code>yes</code> to enable XPath 1.0 backwards compatibility. The setting mainly effects automatic type conversions, which
                were less strict in XPath 1.0 than in later versions.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>
                    <tag>xquery</tag>/<tag>builtin-modules</tag> element </title>

        <para>This section lists the XQuery modules which will be known to the query engine. The modules in this list can be imported into a query
          without specifying a location. For example:</para>
        <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-9.xml"/>
        <para>This establishes a static mapping between the module URI for the file module and the Java class which implements it. When using that
          module, it is sufficient to provide the correct URI in the import. Specifying a location is not needed, like in:</para>
        <programlisting language="xquery">import module namespace file="http://exist-db.org/xquery/file";</programlisting>
        <para>Instead of providing a Java class, one can also specify a <code>src</code> URI which must point to the XQuery source code of the module,
          for instance:</para>
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<module uri="http://exist-db.org/xquery/kwic" src="resource:org/exist/xquery/lib/kwic.xql"/>]]></programlisting>
        <para>For the <code>src</code> attribute, eXist understands the <link xlink:href="xquery.xml#module-system">same types of URIs</link> as in an
          ordinary XQuery import statement.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

</article>