<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>KWIC (Keywords in Context) Output</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>xquery</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>Keywords In Context (KWIC) helps users to quickly scan through search results by listing hits surrounded by their context. eXist provides a
    KWIC module that is not bound to a specific index or query operation. It but can be applied to query results from all indexes that support match
    highlighting. This includes the Lucene-based index and the ngram index.</para>
  <para>The documentation search function on eXist's home page is a good example. It queries documents written in DocBook format. However, the KWIC
    module has also been successfully used with different schemas (e.g. TEI) and languages (e.g. Chinese).</para>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Using the Module</title>

    <para>The KWIC module is entirely written in XQuery. To use the module, import its namespace into your query (you don't need to specify a
      location):</para>
    <programlisting language="xquery">import module namespace kwic="http://exist-db.org/xquery/kwic";</programlisting>

    <para>The easiest way to get KWIC output is to call the <literal>kwic:summarize</literal> function on an element node returned from a full text or
      ngram query:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-3.txt"/>
    <para>Every call to <literal>kwic:summarize</literal> will return an HTML paragraph containing 3 <code>span</code> elements with the text before
      and after each match, as well as the match text itself:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-4.xml"/>

    <para>The <tag>config</tag> element, passed to <literal>kwic:summarize</literal> (as second parameter) determines the appearance of the generated
      HTML. It recognizes 3 attributes:</para>
    <variablelist spacing="compact">
      <varlistentry>
        <term><code>width</code></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The maximum number of characters to be printed before and after the match</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><code>table</code></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>By default <literal>kwic:summarize</literal> returns an HTML paragraph with spans.</para>
          <para>If <code>table="yes"</code> it will return an HTML <emphasis>table row</emphasis>
            <tag>tr</tag> element. The text chunks will be enclosed in a table column <tag>td</tag> element.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><code>link</code></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If present, each match will be enclosed within a link, using the URI in the link attribute as target.
            <!--This feature should be documented-->
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <sect2>
      <title>Using a callback function for more fine-grained control</title>

      <para>If you look at the output of query above you may notice that a space is missing between words if the previous or following chunk extends
        to a different <tag>LINE</tag> element. And it would also be nicer to display text from <tag>LINE</tag> elements only and to ignore
          <tag>SPEAKER</tag> or <tag>STAGEDIR</tag> elements. This can be achieved with the help of a callback function:</para>
      <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-5.txt"/>
      <para>The third parameter to <literal>kwic:summarize</literal> here is a reference to a function accepting 2 arguments:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A single text node which should be appended or prepended to the current text chunk</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A string indicating the current direction in which text is appended: <code>before</code> or <code>after</code>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>


      <para>The function can return the empty sequence if the current node should be ignored (for instance if it belongs to a footnote which should
        not be displayed). Otherwise it must return a single string.</para>
      <para>The <literal>local:filter</literal> function above first checks if the passed node has a SPEAKER or STAGEDIR parent. If so, it
          <emphasis>ignores</emphasis> that node by returning the empty sequence. If not, the function adds a single whitespace before or after the
        string, so adjacent lines will be properly separated.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Advanced Use</title>

    <para>Using <literal>kwic:summarize</literal>, you will get one KWIC-formatted item for every match, even if the matches are in the same
      paragraph. Also, the context from which the text is taken is always the same: the element you queried. To get more control over the output, you
      can directly call <literal>kwic:get-summary</literal>, which is the module's core function. </para>
    <para><literal>kwic:get-summary</literal> expects 3 or 4 parameters. </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The current context root</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The match object to process</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Parameters 3 and 4 are the same as for <literal>kwic:summarize</literal></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Before passing nodes to <literal>kwic:get-summary</literal> you have to <emphasis>expand</emphasis> them, which basically means to create an
      in-memory copy in which all matches are properly marked up with <tag>exist:match</tag> tags. The main part of the query should look as
      follows:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-6.txt"/>
    <para>In this example, we select the first <tag>exist:match</tag> only, thus ignoring all other matches within
      <literal>$expanded</literal>.</para>

    <para>Sometimes you may also want to change the context to restrict the KWIC display to certain elements within the larger query context, for
      instance paragraphs within sections. The following example still queries <tag>SPEECH</tag> but displays a KWIC entry for each <tag>LINE</tag>
      with a match, grouped by speech:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-7.txt"/>
    <para>You might wonder why we don't query <tag>LINE</tag> directly to get a different context, as in:</para>
    <programlisting language="xquery">//SPEECH[ft:query(LINE, "nature")]</programlisting>
    <para>This is because Lucene computes the relevance of each match with respect to the SPEECH context, not LINE. If we queried LINE, each single
      line would get a match score and the matches would end up in a completely different order.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="highlight">
    <title>Marking up Matches without using KWIC</title>

    <para>Sometimes you don't want to use the KWIC module, but still would like an indication where matches were found in the text. eXist's XML
      serializer can automatically highlight matches when it writes out a piece of XML. All the matches will be surrounded by an
        <tag>exist:match</tag> tag.</para>
    <para>You can achieve the same within an XQuery by calling the extension function <literal>util:expand</literal>:</para>

    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-9.txt"/>
    <para>
      <literal>util:expand</literal> returns a copy of the XML fragment it received in its first parameter, which, unless configured otherwise, has
      all matches wrapped into <tag>exist:match</tag> tags.</para>
  </sect1>
</article>