<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>HTML Templating Module</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>application-development</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>The HTML templating framework makes creating XQuery applications that produce HTML pages
    more easy.</para>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The main goal of the HTML templating framework is a clean separation of concerns.
      Generating entire pages in XQuery is quick and dirty, but makes maintenance and code sharing
      difficult. Ideally people should be able to look at the HTML view of an application and modify
      its look and feel without knowing XQuery. The application logic, written in XQuery, should be
      kept separate. Likewise, the XQuery developer should only have to deal with the minimal amount
      of HTML (generated dynamically).</para>
    <para>The templating module also handles most of the HTTP processing an application requires. It
      does so using sophisticated features like automatic parameter injection and type conversion.
      The goal was to remove repeating code like:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-1.txt"/>
    <para>In fact you should not see many calls to the HTTP request or session module inside a
      templating function. This is all handled by parameter injection. </para>
    <note>
      <para>Working examples for the templating module can be found in the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="{demo}/examples/templating/templates.html">demo application</link>.</para>
    </note>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Writing the HTML</title>

    <para>The templating module is based mainly on conventions. Wherever possible it tries to make a
      best guess instead of requiring additional code or annotations. This works as long as the
      conventions used are sufficiently clear.</para>
    <para>The input for the templating framework is always a plain HTML file. The module scans the
      HTML view for elements with <code>class</code> (or <code>data-template</code>, see below)
      attributes following a simple convention and tries to translate them into XQuery function
      calls. By using class attributes, the HTML remains sufficiently clean and does not get messed
      up with application code. A web designer could take the HTML files and work on it without
      being bothered by the extra class names.</para>
    <para>In the simplest case, a template call inside a class attribute is just the name of a
      function known in the XQuery context. To start with the usual "Hello world" example:</para>
    <programlisting language="xquery">&lt;div class="demo:hello grey-box"&gt;Greet the user&lt;/div&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>When the module encounters demo:hello, it will try to find a function named "demo:hello"
      in all the modules known to the XQuery. If this function's signature follows a certain
      convention (see below), it will be called and the <tag>div</tag> will either be replaced or
      enhanced by whatever the function returns.</para>
    <para>Please note that the additional class "grey-box" does not interfere with the template call
      and is ignored by the templating framework. The templating framework will only take a closer
      look at class names which follow the <code>prefix:local-name</code> pattern.
        <code>grey-box</code> is probably be a class used for CSS styling, so we don't want to
      remove it. </para>
    <para>It is possible to pass static parameters to a template call. These must be encoded as URI
      parameters, for instance: <code>demo:hello?language=de</code>. A static parameter will be
      passed to the XQuery function as a fallback value, if it cannot be determined by looking at
      the HTTP context (see below).</para>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>HTML5 Method</title>

      <para>Instead of "abusing" class attributes to encode template calls or other
        application-specific information, HTML5 provides a standard method for adding data to an
        element, using <literal>data-*</literal> attributes. This approach is supported in the
        templating framework (beginning with version 0.3.0 of the shared-resources package).</para>
      <para>The <literal>data-*</literal> attributes must follow the function naming pattern. The
        templating function to call has to be specified in an <literal>data-template</literal>,
        optional parameters go into one or more attributes <literal>data-template-*</literal>. </para>
      <para>For example the previous example could be rewritten as:</para>
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;div data-template="demo:hello" data-template-language="de"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</programlisting>
      <para>The templating framework supports both alternatives.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Templating Functions</title>

    <para>A templating function is an ordinary XQuery function in a module which takes at least two
      parameters of a specific type. Additional parameters are allowed. If a function does not
      follow this convention it will be ignored by the framework.</para>
    <para> For example, our "Hello world!" function could be defined as follows:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-5.txt"/>
    <para>The two required parameters are <code>$node</code> and <code>$model</code>: </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <code>$node</code> contains the HTML node currently being processed: in this case, the
            <tag>div</tag> element. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>$model</code> is an XQuery map with application data. It will be empty for now,
          but we'll see later why it is important.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Parameter Injection and Type Conversion</title>

    <para>The additional parameters in the example above, <code>$language</code> and
        <code>$user</code>, will be injected automatically. The templating framework tries to make a
      best guess how to fill those parameters with values. It checks the following 3 contexts for
      parameters with the same name (in the order below):</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>if the current <emphasis>HTTP request</emphasis> contains a (non-empty) parameter with
          the same name as the parameter variable, this is used to set the value of the
          variable</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>if the <emphasis>HTTP session</emphasis> contains an attribute with the same name as
          the parameter variable, this is used to set the value of the variable</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>if the <emphasis>static parameters</emphasis> passed to the template call contain a
          parameter matching the variable name, it will be used</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>If neither 1 nor 2 lead to a non-empty value, the function signature will be checked for
      an annotation <code>%templates:default("name", "value1", ..., "valueN")</code>. See
      below.</para>
    <para>If "language" is passed as a parameter in the HTTP request, it will overwrite the static
      parameter we provided because the HTTP request is checked first. </para>
    <para>The templating framework will also attempt automatic type conversion for all parameters.
      If the parameter has a declared type of <code>xs:integer</code>, it will try to cast a
      parameter it finds into an integer. If the type is <code>node()</code>, the parameter value
      will be parsed into XML. These conversions may fail and this results in an error passing a
      parameter with the wrong type.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Additional Annotations</title>

    <para>Our "Hello world" example above does not preserve the div from which it was called, but
      replaces it with a new one which lacks the "grey-box" class. This is the default behavior. To
      preserve the enclosing div, we should add the XQuery annotation <code>%templates:wrap</code>
      to the function signature.</para>
    <para>Another annotation can be used to provide a default value for a parameter:
        <code>%templates:default("parameter", "value1", "value2", ...)</code>. The first parameter
      of the annotation must match the name of the parameter variable. All other parameters in the
      annotation are used as values for the variable. </para>
    <para>For example, set <code>$language</code> to <code>en</code> if the value cannot be
      determined otherwise:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-6.txt"/>
    <para>Because of the <code>%templates:wrap</code> we can now remove the wrapping <tag>div</tag>
      in the function and just return a string now. </para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Using the Model to Keep Application Data</title>

    <para>In a more complex application, a view will have many templating functions which all access
      the same data. For example, take a typical search page: there might be one HTML element to
      display the number of hits, one to show the query, and another one for printing out the
      results. All those components need to access the search result. How to do this in a templating
      framework?</para>
    <para>This is where the <code>$model</code> parameter comes into play. It is passed to all
      template functions and they can add data to it. This is available to nested template calls. </para>
    <para>For example a search page:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-7.xml"/>
    <para> The <code>demo:hit-count</code> and <code>demo:result-list</code> occur inside the
        <tag>div</tag> calling <code>demo:search</code>. They are <emphasis>nested</emphasis>
      template calls. <code>demo:search</code> will perform the actual search operation, based on
      the parameters passed by the user. Instead of directly printing the search result in HTML, it
      delegates this to the nested templates.</para>
    <para>
      <code>demo:search</code> can be implemented as: </para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-8.txt"/>
    <para>
      <code>demo:search</code> differs from the functions we have seen so far in that it returns an
      XQuery map and not HTML or some atomic type. If a templating function returns a map, the
      templating framework will proceed as follows:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add the returned map to the current <code>$model</code> map (adding it to the map
          keeps entries produced by any ancestor templates)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>resume processing the children of the current HTML node</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>The <code>demo:hit-count</code> can now access the query results in
      <code>$model</code>:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-9.txt"/>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Manual Processing Control</title>

      <para>Inside a templating function, you can also call <code>templates:process($nodes as
          node()*, $model as map(*))</code> to have the templating module process the given node
        sequence. </para>
      <warning>
        <para>You need to make sure you are not running into an endless loop by calling
            <code>templates:process</code> on the currently processed node.</para>
      </warning>
      <para> A common pattern is to trigger <code>templates:process</code> on the children of the
        current node:</para>
      <programlisting language="xquery">templates:process($node/node(), $model)</programlisting>
      <para>This is comparable to calling <tag>xsl:apply-templates</tag> in XSLT and will have the
        same effect as returning a map (see the section above), but with your templating function
        having full control.</para>
      <para>For example, it is sometimes necessary to first process all the descendant nodes of the
        current element, then apply some action to the processed tree. The documentation app has a
        function, <code>config:expand-links</code>, which scans the final document tree for links
        and expands them. The function is implemented as follows:</para>
      <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-11.txt"/>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Set-Up</title>

    <para>The templating module is entirely implemented in XQuery. It provides a single public
      function, <code>templates:apply</code>. A complete main module which calls the templating
      framework to process an HTML file passed in the HTTP request body could look as
      follows:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-12.txt"/>
    <para>This module would be called from the URL rewriting controller. For example, we could add a
      rule to <literal>controller.xql</literal> to pass any .html resource to the above main query
      (saved to <literal>modules/view.xql</literal>):</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-13.txt"/>
    <para>The only part of the main module code which might look a bit unusual is the inline lookup
      function: the templating module uses dynamic function calls to execute template functions in
      application modules. But unfortunately, XQuery modules can only "see" functions in their own
      context. There is therefore no way for the templating module to determine what functions are
      defined in application modules which are outside its context. So need to "help" it by
      providing a callback function to resolve function references. The lookup function is defined
      in the main context and can access all the modules imported into the main module.</para>
    <para>Normally you can just copy and paste the main module code as given above. To adopt it to
      your own application, just import your application modules and you're done.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Integration with eXide</title>

    <para>The "New Application" templates in eXide already include the HTML templating module and
      configures the URL rewriting to call this for any path ending in <literal>.html</literal>.
      Using eXide is therefore the easiest way to get started with the templating framework. </para>
    <para>Please consult the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="development-starter.xml">Getting Started with Web Application Development</link>
      guide.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Where to Find the Module?</title>

    <para>If you generate your application with eXide, a copy of the HTML templating module will be
      included, so you can customize it. If you rather want to make sure you have the latest version
      of the templating module: the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/eXist-db/shared-resources">shared-resources</link>
      application also exports the module. This will always be the latest version. You could
      therefore define a dependency on the shared-resources app (see the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="repo.xml">packaging
        documentation</link>). You can now just import the module by its namespace URI, but without
      specifying a location:</para>
    <programlisting language="xquery">import module namespace templates="http://exist-db.org/xquery/templates";</programlisting>
    <para>The documentation and demo applications all read the templating module from
      shared-resources.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Pre-defined Template Commands</title>

    <para>The templating module defines a number of general-purpose templating functions which are
      described below. </para>
    <para><code>templates:surround</code> is probably the most powerful one and used by almost all
      HTML views.</para>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>templates:include</title>

      <programlisting language="xquery">templates:include?path=path-to-xml-resource</programlisting>
      <para>Includes the content of the resource given by <code>path</code> into the current
        element. <code>path</code> is always interpreted relative to the current application
        directory or collection.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>templates:each</title>

      <programlisting language="xquery">templates:each?from=map-key&amp;amp;to=map-key</programlisting>
      <para>Retrieve the sequence identified by the map key <literal>from</literal> in the
          <code>$model</code> map. If it exists, iterate over the items in its value (as a sequence)
        and process any nested content once. During each iteration, the current item is added to the
          <code>$model</code> map using the key <literal>to</literal>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>templates:if-parameter-set</title>

      <programlisting language="xquery">templates:if-parameter-set?param=request-parameter</programlisting>
      <para>Conditionally includes content only if the given request parameter is set and not
        empty.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>templates:if-parameter-unset</title>

      <programlisting language="xquery">templates:if-parameter-unset?param=request-parameter</programlisting>
      <para>Conditionally includes content only if the given request parameter is
          <emphasis>not</emphasis> set or empty.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>templates:surround</title>

      <programlisting language="xquery">templates:surround?with=xml-resource&amp;at=id&amp;using=id</programlisting>
      <para>Surrounds its content with the contents of the XML resource specified in
          <code>with</code>. The <code>at</code> parameter determines where the content is inserted
        into the surrounding XML. It should match an existing HTML <code>id</code> in the
        template.</para>
      <para>The <code>using</code> parameter is optional and specifies the <code>id</code> of an
        element in the <code>with</code> resource. The current content will be surrounded by this
        element. If this parameter is missing, the entire document given in <code>with</code> will
        be used.</para>
      <para>The surround template instruction is used by all pages of the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="{demo}/index.html">Demo</link>
        application. The header, basic page structure and menus are the same for all pages. Each
        page only contains a simple <tag>div</tag> with a template instruction:</para>
      <programlisting language="xquery">templates:surround?with=templates/page.html&amp;at=content</programlisting>
      <para>The instruction takes the content of the current element and injects it into the
        template page.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>templates:form-control</title>

      <programlisting language="xquery">templates:form-control</programlisting>
      <para>Use on <tag>input</tag> and <tag>select</tag> elements: checks the HTTP request for a
        parameter matching the name of the form control and fills it into the value of an input or
        selects the corresponding option of a select.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>templates:load-source</title>

      <programlisting language="xquery">templates:load-source</programlisting>
      <para>Commonly used with an <tag>a</tag> element: opens the document referenced in the
          <code>href</code> attribute in eXide.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>