<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>Writing Java Applications with the XML:DB API</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>java-development</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>This article explains how to work with eXist-db from Java code using the XML:DB API. This API provides a common interface to native or
    XML-enabled databases and supports the development of portable, reusable applications.</para>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The preferred way to work with eXist-db when developing Java applications is to use the XML:DB API. eXist-db's implementation of the XML:DB
      standards follows the XIndice implementation, and conforms to the latest working drafts put forth by the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://xmldb-org.sourceforge.net/xapi/">XML:DB Initiative</link>. For more information,
      refer to the Javadocs for this API.</para>
    <para>The basic components employed by the XML:DB API are <emphasis>drivers</emphasis>, <emphasis>collections</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>resources</emphasis> and <emphasis>services</emphasis>.</para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Drivers</emphasis> are implementations of the database interface that encapsulate the database access logic for specific XML database
      products. They are provided by the product vendor and must be registered with the database manager.</para>
    <para>A <emphasis>collection</emphasis> is a hierarchical container for <emphasis>resources</emphasis> and further sub-collections. Currently two
      different resources are defined by the API: <literal>XMLResource</literal> and <literal>BinaryResource</literal>. An
        <literal>XMLResource</literal> represents an XML document or a document fragment, selected by a previously executed XPath query.</para>
    <para>Finally, <emphasis>services</emphasis> are requested for special tasks such as querying a collection with XPath, or managing a
      collection.</para>
    <para>There are several XML:DB examples provided in eXist's <literal>samples</literal> directory . To start an example, use the
        <literal>start.jar</literal> jar file and pass the name of the example class as the first parameter, for instance:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="listings/listing-1.txt"/>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Using the XML:DB API</title>

    <para>Programming with the XML:DB API is straightforward. You will find some code examples in the
        <literal>samples/org/exist/examples/xmldb</literal> directory.</para>
    <para>In the following simple example, a document is retrieved from the eXist server and printed to standard output.</para>

    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="java" xlink:href="listings/listing-2.txt"/>

    <para>With this example, the database driver class for eXist (<literal>org.exist.xmldb.DatabaseImpl</literal>) is registered first with the
        <literal>DatabaseManager</literal>. </para>
    <para>Next we obtain a <literal>Collection</literal> object from the database manager by calling the static method
        <literal>DatabaseManger.getCollection()</literal>. This method expects a fully qualified URI for its parameter value, which identifies the
      desired collection. The format of this URI must be:</para>
    <programlisting>xmldb:[DATABASE-ID]://[HOST-ADDRESS]/db/collection</programlisting>
    <para>Because more than one database driver can be registered with the database manager, the first part of the URI
      (<literal>xmldb:exist</literal>) is required to determine which driver class to use. The <emphasis>database-id</emphasis> is used by the
      database manager to select the correct driver from its list of available drivers. To use eXist-db, this ID should always be <code>exist</code>
      (unless you have set up multiple database instances; additional instances may have other names).</para>
    <para>The final part of the URI identifies the collection path, and optionally the host address of the database server on the network. Internally,
      eXist uses two different driver implementations: The first talks to a remote database engine using XML-RPC calls, the second has direct access
      to a local instance of eXist-db. The root collection is always identified by <literal>/db</literal>. For example:</para>
    <programlisting>xmldb:exist://localhost:8080/exist/xmlrpc/db/shakespeare/plays</programlisting>
    <para>This references the Shakespeare collection on a remote server running the XML-RPC interface as a servlet at
        <literal>localhost:8080/exist/xmlrpc</literal>. </para>

    <para>If we leave out the host address, the XML:DB driver will try to connect to a locally attached database instance. For instance:</para>
    <programlisting>xmldb:exist:///db/shakespeare/plays</programlisting>
    <para>In this case, we have to tell the XML:DB driver that it should create a new database instance if none has been started. This is done by
      setting the <literal>create-database</literal> property of class <literal>Database</literal> to <code>true</code> (more information on embedded
      use of eXist-db can be found in the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="deployment">deployment guide</link>).</para>
    <para>The <literal>setProperty</literal> calls are used to set database-specific parameters. In this case, pretty-printing of XML output is turned
      on for the collection. eXist uses the property keys defined in the standard Java package <literal>javax.xml.transform</literal>. Thus, in Java
      you can simply use class <literal>OutputKeys</literal> to get the correct keys.</para>
    <para>Calling <literal>col.getResource()</literal> finally retrieves the document, which is returned as an <literal>XMLResource</literal>. All
      resources have a method <literal>getContent()</literal>, which returns the resource's content, depending on it's type. In this case we retrieve
      the content as type <literal>String</literal>.</para>
    <para>To query the repository, we may either use the standard <literal>XPathQueryService</literal> or eXist's <literal>XQueryService</literal>
      class. The XML:DB API defines different kinds of services, which may or may not be provided by the database. The <literal>getService</literal>
      method of class <literal>Collection</literal> calls a service if it is available. The method expects the service name as the first parameter,
      and its version (as a string) as the second.</para>

    <para>The following is an example of using the XML:DB API to execute a database query:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="java" xlink:href="listings/listing-6.txt"/>
    <para>To execute the query, method <literal>service.query(xpath)</literal> is called. This method returns a <literal>ResourceSet</literal>,
      containing the Resources found by the query. <literal>ResourceSet.getIterator()</literal> gives us an iterator over these resources. Every
      Resource contains a single document fragment or value, selected by the XPath expression.</para>
    <para>Internally, eXist does not distinguish between XPath and XQuery expressions. <literal>XQueryService</literal> thus maps to the same
      implementation class as <literal>XPathQueryService</literal>. However, it provides a few additional methods. Most important, when talking to an
      embedded database, <literal>XQueryService</literal> allows for the XQuery expression to be <emphasis>compiled</emphasis> to an internal
      representation, which can then be reused. With compilation, the previous example code would look as follows:</para>

    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="java" xlink:href="listings/listing-7.txt"/>
    <para>The XML-RPC server automatically caches compiled expressions, and so calling <literal>compile</literal> through the remote driver produces
      no effect if the expression is already cached.</para>
    <para>Next, we would like to store a new document into the repository. This is done by creating a new <literal>XMLResource</literal>, assigning it
      the content of the new document, and calling the <literal>storeResource</literal> method of class <literal>Collection</literal>. </para>
    <para>First, a new Resource is created by method <literal>Collection.createResource()</literal>, and expects two parameters: the id and type of
      resource being created. If the id parameter is <code>null</code>, a unique resource-id will be automatically generated .</para>
    <para>In some cases, the collection may not yet exist, and so we must create it. To create a new collection, call the
        <literal>createCollection</literal> method of the <literal>CollectionManagementService</literal> service. In the following example, we simply
      start at the root collection object to get the <literal>CollectionManagementService</literal> service.</para>

    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="java" xlink:href="listings/listing-8.txt"/>

    <note>
      <para>The <literal>XMLResource.setContent()</literal> method takes a Java object as its parameter. The eXist driver checks if the object is a
        File. Otherwise, the object is transformed into a String by calling the object's <literal>toString()</literal> method. Passing a File has one
        big advantage: If the database is running in embedded mode, the file will be directly passed to the indexer. Thus, the file's content does not
        have to be loaded into memory. This is handy if your files are very large.</para>
    </note>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Extensions to XML:DB</title>

    <para>eXist provides extensions on top of the XML:DB specification.</para>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Additional Services</title>

      <para>The <code>UserManagementService</code> service contains methods to manage users and handle permissions. These methods resemble common Unix
        commands such as <literal>chown</literal> or <literal>chmod</literal>. As with other services, <literal>UserManagementService</literal> can be
        retrieved from a collection objectn:</para>
      <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="listings/listing-9.txt"/>
      <para>Another service called <code>DatabaseInstanceManager</code> provides a single method to shut down the database instance accessed by the
        driver. You have to be a member of the <literal>dba</literal> user group to use this method or an exception will be thrown. </para>
      <para>Finally, interface <code>IndexQueryService</code> supports access to the terms and elements contained in eXist's internal index. Method
          <code>getIndexedElements()</code> returns a list of element occurrences for the current collection. For each occurring element, the
        element's name and a frequency count is returned.</para>
      <para>Method <code>scanIndexTerms()</code> allows for a retrieval of the list of occurring words for the current collection. This can be useful
        to provide users a list of searchable terms together with their frequency.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2 xml:id="multidb">
      <title>Multiple Database Instances</title>

      <para>As explained above, passing a local XML:DB URI to the <literal>DatabaseManager</literal> means that the driver will try to start or access
        an embedded database instance. You can configure more than one database instance by setting the location of the central configuration
        file.</para>
      <para> The configuration file is set through the <literal>configuration</literal> property of the <literal>DatabaseImpl</literal> driver class.
        If you would like to use different drivers for different database instances, specify a name for the created instance through the
          <literal>database-id</literal> property. You may later use this name in the URI to refer to a database instance. The following fragment sets
        up two instances:</para>

      <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="java" xlink:href="listings/listing-10.txt"/>
      <para>With this example, the URI<code> xmldb:test:///db</code> selects the test database instance. Both instances should have their own data and
        log directory as specified in the configuration files.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>