<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <info>
    <title>Advanced Installation Methods</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>installation</keyword>
      <keyword>operations</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>The eXist-db <link xlink:href="basic-installation">Basic Installation</link> article describes how to install and start eXist-db for basic
    usage. This article explains more advanced methods of installing and running eXist, for instance for a headless (no GUI) system, running it as a
    service, etc.</para>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="headless">
    <title>Headless Installation</title>

    <para>The <link xlink:href="basic-installation">Basic Installation</link> of eXist-db requires a graphical desktop. You can also install eXist on
      a headless (no GUI) system. For this launch the installer from the command line, using the <code>-console</code> option:</para>
    <programlisting>java -jar eXist-{version}.jar -console</programlisting>
    <para>In console mode, the installer will prompt for several parameters (almost like the GUI version does). A dump of a sample interaction is
      shown below:</para>
    <programlisting xlink:href="listings/listing-2.txt"/>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="service">
    <title>Running eXist-db as a Service</title>

    <para>Instead of manually running the eXist-db server in a shell window, you can run it as a background service which is automatically launched
      during system start-up. This can be convenient, especially for servers. eXist-db continues to run even after users have logged off.</para>
    <para>eXist-db comes with pre-configured scripts that use <link condition="_blank" xlink:href="http://yajsw.sourceforge.net/">YAJSW (Yet Another
        Java Service Wrapper)</link> to handle the setup procedure. The scripts for this are contained in the directory
      <literal>tools/yajsw</literal>. </para>
    <para>Out of the box the following mainstream platforms are supported:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Windows x86 (32bit/64bit)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Linux x86 (32bit/64bit) &amp; IA (64bit) </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>macOS x86 (32bit/64bit) </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Solaris x86 (32bit/64bit) &amp; SPARC (32bit/64bit)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2 xml:id="windows">
      <title>Windows</title>

      <para>On Windows there are three identical options:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose <guimenuitem>Install eXist-db as Service</guimenuitem> from the eXist-db's system tray application.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose <guimenuitem>Install eXist-db as Service</guimenuitem> from eXist-db's entry in the Windows start menu.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run <literal>tools/yajsw/bin/installService.bat</literal> from the command line.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Installing eXist-db as a service on Windows requires full administrator rights.</para>

      <para>After installing eXist-db as a service, you'll find eXist-db in the list of services registered with Windows:</para>
      <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="assets/services.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      <para>Launch it via the service manager (as shown in the screenshot above) or from the command line:</para>
      <programlisting>tools\yaysw\bin\startService.bat</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2 xml:id="linux">
      <title>Unix/Linux</title>

      <para>The scripts for running eXist-db as a service for Unix and Linux based system (among which MacOS)can be found in the
          <literal>tools/yajsw/bin/</literal> sub-directory.</para>
      <para>Run the following command to get eXist-db started during initialization of the system:</para>
      <programlisting>tools/yajsw/bin/installDaemon.sh</programlisting>
      <para> This works for MacOS and many Linux distributions.</para>
      <para>It might be required to set some variables for the specific system. Complete
        documentation of the configuraiton settings YAJSW can be found at the <link
          xlink:href="http://yajsw.sourceforge.net/YAJSW%20Configuration%20Parameters.html">YAJSW
          website</link>. Below are a list of some important settings: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>wrapper.app.account</code> - Allows eXist to be run as a specific
              user</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>wrapper.plist.template</code> - Used on Mac systems to provide a list of
              parameters to <code>launchd</code> daemon</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>wrapper.ping.timeout</code> YAJSW pings the application to determine if it
              has entered and unresponsive state. The ping timeout parameters sets the limit on how
              long YAJSW will wait. If you have long running queries you may find that you need to
              increase the value of this parameter to prevent YAJSW from restarting eXist. The
              parameter value is in seconds and the default value is 30.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      <para> If your system supports <code>systemd</code> you can run the service wrapper as a non-privileged user. You will be notified on choosing
          <code>systemd</code> non-privileged when running the service wrapper installer and uninstaller.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2 xml:id="other">
      <title>Other platforms</title>

      <para>Support for additional platforms can be bootstrapped by looking at templates in the <code>tools/yajsw/templates</code> sub-directory.
        Consult the <link condition="_blank" xlink:href="http://yajsw.sourceforge.net/">YAJSW documentation</link> for more information.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="bin-executables">
    <title>Alternatives for scripts in the bin Directory</title>

    <para>Included in the distribution are a number of useful <literal>.sh</literal> (Unix Shell) and <literal>.bat</literal> (DOS batch) programs
      located in the <literal>bin</literal> sub-directory. Their names speak for themselves.</para>
    <para>However, if you find that programs do not launch, you can try to manually launch them on the command-line without the scripting wrapper.
      This often provides useful debugging information.</para>
    <para>To manually launch these scripts, give the following commands:</para>
    <variablelist spacing="compact">
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>startup.sh</code> (Unix) / <code>startup.bat</code> (Windows)</term>
        <listitem>
          <programlisting>java -jar start.jar jetty</programlisting>
          <para>Starts the included Jetty web server at port 8080. eXist runs as a web application, located at <link xlink:href="http://localhost:8080/exist/">http://localhost:8080/exist/</link>. </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>shutdown.sh</code> (Unix) / <code>shutdown.bat</code> (Windows)</term>
        <listitem>
          <programlisting>java -jar start.jar shutdown -p youradminpassword</programlisting>
          <para>Closes the running instance of eXist. If eXist has been started with <literal>startup.sh</literal>, calling
              <literal>shutdown.sh</literal> will also stop the Jetty web server. Otherwise, only the database is stopped by this call (since eXist
            has no control over the environment in which it is running). You should <emphasis>always</emphasis> call <literal>shutdown</literal>
            before killing the server process.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>server.sh</code> (Unix) / <code>server.bat</code> (Windows)</term>
        <listitem>
          <programlisting>java -jar start.jar standalone</programlisting>
          <para>Launches eXist as a stand-alone server process. In this setup, eXist is only accessible through the XMLRPC and the built-in HTTP
            interface.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>client.sh</code> (Unix) / <code>client.bat</code> (Windows)</term>
        <listitem>
          <programlisting>java -jar start.jar client</programlisting>
          <para>Launches the <link xlink:href="java-admin-client">Java Admin Client</link>. This application is also launched if no application is
            selected on the command-line, like this:</para>
          <programlisting>java -jar start.jar</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>
</article>
