<!-- $Id$ -->
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <productname>eXist-db – Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>Using oXygen</title>
        <date>November 2014</date>
    </bookinfo>
    <chapter>
        <title>Using oXygen</title>
        <section id="overview">
            <title>Overview</title>
            <para><ulink url="http://oxygenxml.com/">oXygen XML Editor</ulink> is a powerful tool
                for working with eXist-db. Its eXist-db-specific capabilities include:<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>browsing eXist-db database contents</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>editing database contents (open, save, rename documents; create,
                            rename collections)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>editing XQuery files and continuously validate them against eXist-db's
                            XQuery engine</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>executing queries and displaying results</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist> This article describes how to configure oXygen to work with
                eXist-db. While the oXygen documentation describes <ulink
                    url="http://oxygenxml.com/xml_editor/eXist_support.html">oXygen's eXist-db
                    support</ulink>, we provide up-to-date information here for the convenience of
                eXist-db users.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="setup">
            <title>How to tell oXygen about your eXist-db installation</title>
            <para>To tap into eXist-db via oXygen, you must tell oXygen a bit about your eXist-db
                installation. The steps to do this are admittedly too tedious, but you only need to
                perform these steps once. First, we need to create an entry for eXist-db in oXygen's
                list of Data Sources; this involves pointing oXygen to 5 key libraries (.jar files)
                in our eXist-db directory so that oXygen knows how to connect to our version of
                eXist-db. Then we need to create an entry in its list of Data Connections; this
                involves providing oXygen with a URL and account information for your eXist-db
                instance.</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>In oXygen, go to Preferences > Data Sources, and you will see a window
                        with two areas: Data Sources (on the top) and Connections (on the bottom).
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>In the Data Sources pane, select the <guibutton>New</guibutton> button to
                        create a new data source.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>A new dialog will appear, with fields for Name, Type, and Driver
                        Files.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>In the Name field enter a unique name for this eXist-db data source, e.g.,
                        "eXist-db Data Source".</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>In the Type dropdown menu select "eXist."</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Finally, select the <guibutton>Add Files</guibutton> button. Browse to the
                        directory where you installed eXist-db, and select each of the following
                        files so that they appear in the Driver files area: <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>exist.jar</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>lib/core/ws-commons-1.0.2.jar</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>lib/core/xmldb.jar</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>lib/core/xmlrpc-client-3.1.3.jar</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>lib/core/xmlrpc-common-3.1.3.jar</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Select OK to complete the creation of the new Data Source and return to
                        the Data Sources screen, where will will create a new Data Connection to
                        your eXist-db installation. In the "Connections" area of the screen, select
                        the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button to creat a new data connection.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>A new dialog will appear, with fields for Name, Type, and Driver
                        Files.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>In the Name field enter a unique name for your eXist-db server, e.g.,
                        "eXist-db on localhost 8080".</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>In the Data Source drop down menu, select the Data Connection name that
                        you created above.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>In the XML DB URI field, enter the URL pointing to your eXist-db's XML-RPC
                        service (e.g., http://localhost:8080/exist/xmlrpc). oXygen v14 and higher
                        allow you to make the connection between oXygen and eXist-db secure and
                        SSL-encrypted; to do so select the checkbox, "Use a Secure HTTPS Connection
                        (SSL)", and use your eXist-db's secure port for the XML DB URI (e.g.,
                        https://localhost:8443/exist/xmlrpc).</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>In the User and Password fields, enter your eXist-db account details
                        (e.g., typically, the "admin" user and associated password that you set up
                        when you installed eXist-db).</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>In the Collection field, enter "/db".</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Select OK to complete the creation of the new Data Connection. Select OK
                        to exit oXygen's Preferences. Congratulations! You have told oXygen
                        everything it needs to know about eXist-db.</para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </section>
        <section id="browsing-db">
            <title>How to browse your database contents</title>
            <para>Now that you have created an oXygen Data Source and Connection for eXist-db, you
                can browse your database contents from within oXygen in two ways: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use the Data Source Explorer, an oXygen pane that lists your
                            Connections including the one you created above. To open the Data Source
                            Explorer, select Window > Show view > Data Source Explorer. Using this,
                            you can browse collections and their contents; you can right click on
                            these items display contextual menus with options to create, rename, or
                            move database contents.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Use the File > Open URL to browse and pick documents or files database
                            to open. The first time you connect to your database, you will need to
                            fill in several fields: your eXist-db account credentials and Server URL
                            (e.g., http://localhost:8080/exist/webdav/db/)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
        </section>
        <section id="validating-queries">
            <title>How to validate XQuery files against eXist-db's XQuery engine</title>
            <para>By default oXygen uses Saxon to validate XQuery files that you open in oXygen.
                Saxon is a fine tool for validating XQuery (among its many capabilities), but it
                lacks knowledge of eXist-db built-in functions and other settings. Thus, if you are
                ultimately creating XQuery to use in eXist-db, you will find numerous advantages in
                configuring oXygen to use eXist-db for validation instead of Saxon. The steps to
                complete this configuration are very easy:</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>In oXygen, go to Preferences > XQuery. On the dropdown menu labeled,
                        "XQuery Validate with", select the name of the Data Connection that you
                        created above.</para>
                    <para>Select OK to confirm your new preference.</para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
            <para>Now when you are editing an XQuery file in oXygen, the validation information you
                receive (i.e., when you click on the <guibutton>Validate</guibutton> toolbar button)
                is supplied from eXist-db.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="executing-queries">
            <title>How to execute queries and display results</title>
            <para>You can execute queries against eXist-db from within oXygen. To do so:</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Open an XQuery file that you would like to execute.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Select the <guibutton>Configure Transformation Scenario</guibutton>
                        toolbar button, select the <guibutton>New</guibutton> button, and select
                        "XQuery Transformation" in the dropdown menu.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>A new dialog will appear with fields to configure your XQuery
                        transformation settings. Enter a Name for the transformation (e.g.,
                        "Transform with eXist-db"). In the "Transformer" dropdown menu, select the
                        name of the Data Connection that you created above.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Select OK to confirm these settings, and then select "Save and Close" to
                        exit the configuration window, or select the <guibutton>Apply
                            Associated</guibutton> button to execute your query.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Henceforth, you can execute any query using this transformation scenario
                        by simply selecting the <guibutton>Apply Transformation Scenario</guibutton>
                        toolbar button</para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
