<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>Basic Installation</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>installation</keyword>
      <keyword>getting-started</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>This article describes eXist-db's basic installation procedure. It will help you install and setup eXist-db in a quick and easy way on, for
    instance, your laptop or a development server. Before you know it you'll be up and running and programming XQuery!</para>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->


  <sect1 xml:id="system-requirements">
    <title>System Requirements</title>

    <para>eXist-db runs on any system Java runs on. So all recent versions of Linux, macOS, and Windows are ok. The following requirements must be
      met:</para>
    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>At least Java version 8 (since eXist-db 3.0)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>About 200Mb of disk space for the installation</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>At least 512Mb memory to run</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Administrative privileges are not required to install or run eXist-db, but certain installation procedures are not possible without
      administrative privileges. </para>


    <note xml:id="about-java">
      <title>eXist-db and Java</title>
      <para>eXist-db is built on Java, a free, cross-platform software development environment. Java comes in a number of versions, so it is important
        that you use the version that eXist-db requires: Java 8 (since eXist-db 3.0). For instructions about running Java on your operating system,
        see Oracle's <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" condition="_blank" xlink:href="http://www.java.com/en/download/help/index_installing.xml">Installing Java</link> page. It is recommended to use the Oracle Java
        VM, but the OpenJDK 7 is a good open source alternative for the Oracle JVM.</para>
      <para>eXist-db runs with both the Java JRE (Java Runtime Environment) and the JDK (Java Development Kit). The JRE usually suffices. You only
        need the JDK to compile eXist-db from its source code.</para>

      <para>Details of the Java installation can be obtained with the <code>java -version</code> command:</para>
      <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="listings/listing-1.txt"/>

      <para>For Linux users: Unfortunately, Oracle's own pages (such as the link above) focus on commercial Linux distributions. Users of other
        distributions are better served by distribution-specific instructions. More information for specific versions of Linux can be found at <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" condition="_blank" xlink:href="http://livingtao.blogspot.com/2012/01/few-easy-steps-to-install-sunoracle-jdk.html">Amazon Linux</link>, <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" condition="_blank" xlink:href="http://www.webupd8.org/2012/01/install-oracle-java-jdk-7-in-ubuntu-via.html">Ubuntu</link> and <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" condition="_blank" xlink:href="http://www.webupd8.org/2012/06/how-to-install-oracle-java-7-in-debian.html">Debian</link>.</para>


      <para>Note for pre eXist-db v2.2 versions: Due to compatibility issues it is NOT recommended to use "OpenJDK6" (IcedTea) and "GNU
        Compiler for Java" (GCJ) which are shipped by several Linux distributions.</para>
    </note>

    <warning>
      <para> If you have installed Saxon as a JRE extension (via the extensions folder), this can cause a critical error during installation. To avoid
        this error either remove the JRE extension, or install a second JRE just for use with eXist-db and set JAVA_HOME accordingly.</para>
    </warning>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="installation">
    <title>Installing eXist-db</title>

    <para>The first steps in installing eXIst-db are downloading the installer and firing it up:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Download the installer by following the download link on the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://exist-db.org/">eXist-db homepage</link> page. We recommend that you download the latest stable release.</para>
        <para>The installer is a single file called <literal>eXist-db-setup-[version].jar</literal> (for instance
            <literal>eXist-db-setup-3.6.1.jar</literal>). </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Launch the eXist-db installer:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>On Mac and Windows, simply double-click the downloaded <code>.jar</code> file.</para>
            <note>
              <para>On Mac OS X 10.7 and higher, a security feature called <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://support.apple.com/kb/HT5290">Gatekeeper</link> may prevent the installer from running since eXist-db is not
                registered with Apple. To circumvent the warning dialog and allow the installer to run, right-click or control-click the file and
                select Open.</para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>On Linux distributions with a graphical desktop interface (e.g., Ubuntu), you can launch the installer by making the
                <code>.jar</code> file executable, right-clicking it, and selecting the "Open With ... Java" option.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>If necessary you can launch the installer from the command line with the following command:</para>
            <programlisting>java -jar eXist-db-setup-[version].jar</programlisting>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>More advanced installation methods (like installing on a headless system) are described in the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="advanced-installation.xml#headless">Advanced Installation</link> article.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>After the installer is launched, follow the prompts described below to complete the installation. We recommend that you accept the default
      options, since these are designed to make using eXist-db easy. The installer's dialog panes are as follows:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Installation Directory:</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>You will be asked where to install eXist-db on your hard disk. The installer will suggest an appropriate directory, but if you want,
            you can install eXist-db anywhere on your system.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Data Directory</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The data directory is where eXist-db keeps its data files. The installer will suggest keeping the data files inside the application
            directory, but you can select a different location if you want.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Admin Password and Memory Settings:</term>
        <listitem>
          <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="assets/installer1.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>
          <para>The Admin Password is a password for the eXist-db administrator account, or more commonly, the "admin" account. This admin account
            belongs to you, and certain key functions in eXist-db can only be performed by the admin. While you can leave the admin password blank, we
            strongly recommend setting the password in order to secure access your installation of eXist-db. Why? Keep in mind that while eXist-db is
            running, it can be accessed by other users on your local network (be it in your home or office, or at a cafe or on a train). So, securing
            your administrator's account on eXist-db is a good way to protect your data and prevent others from abusing the account.</para>
          <para>Configure the maximum amount of memory which will be available to Java (and eXist-db) and the portion of it which will be reserved for
            internal caches.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Package Installation:</term>
        <listitem>
          <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="assets/installer2.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The "core" package is required to run eXist-db.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The "sources" package is optional. Removing "sources" cuts the installation size considerably, but best to install everything
                unless you are starved for disk space.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The "apps" package allows you to select or deselect a number of applications which will be installed into eXist-db when it starts
                the first time. If you are new to eXist-db, we recommend to at least select "dashboard", "demo", "doc", "eXide" and "fundocs". You'll
                need those to make your first steps in XQuery development.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>


        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>After this the installer will go through a number of additional steps and screens installing files and configuring the system. Once finished
      you're ready to run!</para>

    <note>
      <title>MacOS users installing via disk image</title>
      <para>For macOS users installing via disk image the default data directory will be: <code>/Users/$username$/Library/Application
          Support/org.exist</code>
      </para>
      <para>Change the default (empty) password via the <literal>Open dashboard</literal> option from the menubar icon once installation has finished.
          <emphasis>Watch out:</emphasis> during the initial run of eXist-db its Dock icon may remain active even after eXist-db has been shut down.
        Simply right-click on the eXist-db Dock icon and select <literal>Quit</literal>. On subsequent runs the dock icon should behave as expected.
      </para>
    </note>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="launching">
    <title>Launching eXist-db</title>

    <para>To launch eXist-db:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>On the Mac, double-click eXist-db's application icon where you installed eXist-db.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>On Linux or Windows, select the <emphasis>eXist-db Database Start-up</emphasis> desktop shortcut icon or Start Menu entry.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <note>
      <para>eXist-db can also be run as a background service. For more information see the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="advanced-installation.xml#headless">Advanced Installation</link> article.</para>
    </note>


    <para>A splash screen appears showing the eXist-db logo. Upon first start-up, eXist-db will upload the applications you selected in the installer.
      This may take a while and is only done once.</para>
    <figure>
      <title>Splash screen during start-up</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="assets/launch1.png" width="40%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>Once eXist is started, a menu bar icon (Mac) or system tray icon (Linux/Windows) appears. This gives you access to eXist-db's tools and lets
      you shutdown or restart the database. Click on it to see a menu providing direct access to the most important tools.</para>
    <figure>
      <title>Menu bar icon on Mac</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="assets/launch2.png" width="40%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <note>
      <title>Linux Installation</title>
      <para>Installing into the system tray does not work equally well on all operating systems. If the system tray icon cannot be installed, you'll
        see a small toolbar dialog pop up instead.</para>
      <para>Also, the desktop integration does not work properly on all versions of Linux. However, you may always use the provided shell scripts
          (<literal>bin/startup.sh</literal>) to launch eXist-db without desktop integration.</para>
    </note>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Launching from the command line</title>

      <para>You can also start eXist-db from the command line:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Open your terminal or command prompt.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Change (<code>cd</code>) to the directory where you installed eXist-db (for instance, <literal>/usr/local/lib/exist/</literal> for
            Linux, <literal>/Applications/eXist/</literal> for Mac, or <literal>C:\Program Files\eXist</literal> for Windows).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Simply calling <literal>start.jar</literal> will start eXist-db via the desktop launcher:</para>
          <programlisting>java -jar start.jar</programlisting>

        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>If you want to launch eXist-db without a GUI, use the shell scripts in the <literal>bin/</literal> sub-directory. On Linux or Mac, enter
          <code>bin/startup.sh</code>, on Windows <code>bin\startup.bat</code>. More information about these start-up scripts in the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="advanced-installation.xml#headless">Advanced Installation</link> article.</para>

      <note>
        <title>Having trouble?</title>
        <para>If you're having trouble launching eXist-db, see our articles on <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="troubleshooting">Troubleshooting</link> and <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="advanced-installation.xml#headless">Advanced Installation</link>.</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="diving-in">
    <title>Diving In</title>

    <para>After a successful installation and launch, access eXist-db's <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="{dashboard}/">Dashboard</link>, the central administration and application hub of eXist-db. If the system tray icon works on your system, select <guimenuitem>Open
      Dashboard</guimenuitem> from the pop-up menu. Or just open a web browser and enter the following URL: <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://localhost:8080/exist/">http://localhost:8080/exist/</link>
    </para>
    <para>The following page appears:</para>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="assets/index1.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>Seeing it? Congratulations! (Not seeing it? See our article on <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="troubleshooting.xml">Troubleshooting</link>).</para>

    <para>All right, ready to dive in! Your local installation includes everything you need. Access is easy, through the applications on the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="{dashboard}/">Dashboard</link> (see also the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="dashboard">article on the Dashboard</link>).</para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="shutting-down">
    <title>Shutting Down the Database</title>

    <para>Improperly shutting down the database can corrupt your data files. Follow one of the following procedures to properly shut down
      eXist-db:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The system tray pop-up menu has an option <guimenuitem>Stop server</guimenuitem>. You may also choose <guimenuitem>Quit (and stop
            server)</guimenuitem> to shut down eXist-db and the system tray launcher at the same time.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>From the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="{dashboard}">Dashboard</link>: select the Shutdown button</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>From the command line, run the <literal>bin/shutdown.sh</literal> (Linux/Mac) or <literal>shutdown.bat</literal> (DOS/Windows) shutdown
          scripts, using your admin account's credentials:</para>
        <programlisting>bin/shutdown.sh -u admin -p youradminpassword</programlisting>
        <programlisting>bin/shutdown.bat -u admin -p youradminpassword</programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>From the command line, run the following Java command, using your admin account's credentials:</para>
        <programlisting>java -jar start.jar shutdown -u admin -p youradminpassword</programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>From the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="java-admin-client">Java Admin Client</link>: select
            <guimenuitem>Connection</guimenuitem>, <guimenuitem>Shutdown</guimenuitem> from the menu.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
</article>
