<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">

  <info>
    <title>Database Backup and Restore</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>operations</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <para>This article discusses eXist-db's database backup/restore procedures and related details</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>During backup, eXist-db exports the contents of its database (both XML and binary files) to a hierarchy of directories on the hard drive.
      This hierarchy is organized according to the organization of collections in the database.</para>

    <para>There are two main methods for creating a backup:</para>
    <variablelist spacing="compact">
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Server-side</term>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="server-side-backup"/> are run through eXist-db's job scheduler or
            triggered via the web interface. This type of backup extracts the data directly from the
            low-level database files. It is therefore much faster then a client-side backup and also
            provides support for incremental backups.</para>
          <para>A server-side backup guarantees that the database is in a consistent state during
            backup. Possible corruptions in the database will be detected and the backup process
            will try to work around them. In many cases, damaged resources can at least be partially
            recovered. However it should be noted, that database operations will be suspended whilst
            the backup is in-progress.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Client-side</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>You can use the <link xlink:href="java-admin-client">Java Admin Client</link> or a command line utility to create a <xref linkend="client-side-backup"/> of the data on the server.</para>
          <para>When the client controls the backup process, unlike the server-side backups, the
            server is not blocked and continues to accept requests from other clients. Other users
            can modify the db while the backup is running, so logical dependencies between different
            resources may not be preserved correctly. The client uses the XML:DB API to access the
            database. This means that it cannot backup documents or collections if they are damaged
            in any way.</para>
          <para>Consider client-side backups a lightweight form of backup. During backup the
            database is not locked so people can keep working. However, the result may therefore be
            inconsistent. Client-side backups are <emphasis>not safe</emphasis> in terms of getting
            a complete and consistent copy of your data.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>The format of the generated backup archives will be the same for both backup methods:
      Resource and collection <emphasis>metadata</emphasis> is exported to a special XML descriptor
      file, named <literal>__contents__.xml</literal>, with information including resource type,
      owner, modification date and/or permissions assigned to a resource. You will find one
        <literal>__contents__.xml</literal> file in each directory created by the backup. This
      descriptor file is required to restore the backup. A full backup includes index configuration
      files and user settings.</para>

    <para>The location of the backup files depends on how the backup was initiated:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para> Backups via the dashboard or XQuery, are server-side backups, and write backups into
          the <code>export</code> directory inside the data directory of the eXist instance.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The Emergency Backup Tool writes into <code>$EXIST_HOME/export</code>, unless configured otherwise.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Client Side backups done via the Java Admin Client are configurable with regards the
          location that the backup files should be written to.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Likewise, other methods (e.g. <link xlink:href="ant-tasks"><code>Ant
            tasks</code></link>) are also fully configurable.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Users can manually modify files in the backup directories without requiring special software. Any changes made to these files are reflected
      in the database after a restore (or when the data is imported into another database system).</para>

    <warning>
      <para> When migrating to a new eXist-db version, take care to use a version of the client corresponding to your server version. Usually, the
        backup process is backwards compatible. However, using a newer client version to create the backup from a server running an older version may
        lead to unexpected problems.</para>
      <para>The backup process also generates a report. Normally this contains the list of
        collections which were backed up. If you notice any warnings or errors, it is especially
        important that you perform a “full restore” of your backed-up data onto the new installation
        of eXist, as described in the <link xlink:href="#restore">following steps.</link>
      </para>
    </warning>
    <important>
      <para>Due to limitations of the ZIP format, please make sure the size of your zipped backup does not exceed 4 gigabytes. All backup methods
        support backups to the file system as an alternative.</para>
    </important>



  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="server-side-backup">
    <title>Server-side Backups</title>

    <para>Server-side backups are executed as system tasks, which means that when performing a server-side backup, eXist-db will do the
      following:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Wait for all pending transactions to complete.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Enter protected mode. No new transactions will be allowed. Concurrent requests by other clients will be blocked and added to the
          internal queue.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The system runs an <link xlink:href="#automatic-consistency-check">automatic consistency check</link> on the database.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Run the backup process.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Once the backup is complete, the database will switch back to normal service and all locks will be released.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sect2>
      <title>Triggering backups using the Dashboard</title>
      <para>You can trigger the backup using the <link xlink:href="dashboard">Dashboard</link>:</para>
      <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="assets/Backup.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      <para>Clicking the <guimenuitem>Trigger Backup</guimenuitem> button will schedule a single server-side backup task.</para>
      <para>You can click on <literal>Refresh</literal> to update the view, which lists all backup archives currently available within the standard
        backup directory. Click on the name of an archive to download it.</para>
      <para>eXist-db can also create <emphasis>incremental backups</emphasis>, meaning only resources which were modified since the last backup are
        backed up.</para>
      <para>All backups will be stored in ZIP format. The default storage directory is
          <literal>webapp/WEB-INF/data/export/</literal>. You can configure a different directory in
        the configuration file <literal>conf.xml</literal>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Scheduling Backups</title>

      <para>You can use eXist-db's <link xlink:href="configuration">scheduler</link> to schedule
        server-side backup and consistency check tasks. To do this, add the following definition to
        the scheduler section in the configuration file <literal>conf.xml</literal></para>


      <example>
        <title>Job Definition in conf.xml</title>
        <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-1.xml"/>
      </example>
      <para>The time/frequency of the backup is specified in the <literal>cron-trigger</literal> attribute. The syntax is borrowed from the Unix
          <literal>cron</literal> utility, though there are small differences. Please consult the Quartz documentation about <link xlink:href="http://www.quartz-scheduler.org/documentation/quartz-2.x/tutorials/tutorial-lesson-06.html">CronTrigger</link> configuration.
        The definition in the example means every 12 hours, starting at midnight. </para>
      <para>The task accepts the following parameters:</para>
      <variablelist spacing="compact">
        <varlistentry>
          <term>output</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The directory to which the backup is written. Relative paths are interpreted relative to eXist-db's main data directory.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>backup</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Setting this to <code>yes</code> will create a full database backup (in addition to running the system checks).</para>
            <para>Setting this to "no" will not create a backup unless errors were detected during the consistency check. In that case the task will
                <emphasis>always</emphasis> try to generate an emergency backup.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>zip</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>If set to <code>yes</code>, the backup will be written into a zip archive. Due to limitations of the zip format, archives larger
              than 4 gigabytes may not be readable.</para>
            <para>Setting this to <code>no</code> will create a backup on the file system which has no such limitations.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>incremental</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Setting this to <code>yes</code> will trigger an incremental backup. The first backup will always be a full backup. Subsequent
              backups will be incremental: only resources which were modified since the last backup will be saved.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>incremental-check</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>By default, for incremental backups no consistency check is done because this may take too long. Setting
                <literal>incremental-check</literal> to <code>yes</code> will enable consistency checking for incremental backups.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>max</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>On incremental backup, create a full backup every <literal>max</literal> backup runs. For eaxmple, if you set the parameter to
                <code>2</code>, a full backup will be performed after every two incremental backups.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <note>
        <para>You can schedule more than one backup job. For example, an incremental backup could be done multiple times a day while a full backup is
          created once during the night </para>
      </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Triggering Backups from XQuery</title>

      <para>System jobs can also be triggered from within an XQuery script using the <literal>system:trigger-system-task</literal> function:</para>
      <example>
        <title>Triggering a Backup From XQuery</title>
        <programlisting language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-2.txt"/>
      </example>
      <para>This will schedule a backup to be executed as soon as possible.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="automatic-consistency-check">
      <title>Automatic Consistency Checks</title>

      <para>The system task runs a consistency and sanity check on the database before a server-side backup. Reports of this check are written into
        the same directory as the backup archive. The last report can also be viewed using JMX (see <xref linkend="using-jmx"/>).</para>
      <para>The consistency check will first check the collection hierarchy, then scan through the stored node tree of every document in the db,
        testing node properties like the node's id, child count, attribute count and node relationships. Contrary to normal database operations, the
        different <code>.dbx</code> files are checked independently. This means that even if a collection is no longer readable, the tool will still
        be able to scan the documents in the damaged collection.</para>
      <para>The backup task uses the information provided by the consistency check to work around damages in the db. It tries to export as much data
        as possible, even if parts of the collection hierarchy are corrupted or documents are damaged:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Descendant collections will be exported properly even if their ancestor collection is corrupted</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Documents which are intact but belong to a destroyed collection will be stored into a special collection
              <literal>/db/lost_and_found</literal>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Damaged documents removed from the backup</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <sect3 xml:id="using-jmx">
        <title>Using JMX to View Check Reports</title>

        <para>If Java Management Extensions (JMX) are enabled in the Java VM that is running eXist, you can use a JMX client to see the latest
          consistency check reports. The screen shot below shows <code>jconsole</code>,(included with the Java JDKs):</para>
        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="assets/jconsole.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <para>eXist also includes a command-line JMX client. Call it with parameter <literal>-s</literal> to see the latest consistency report:</para>
        <programlisting>java -jar start.jar org.exist.management.client.JMXClient -s</programlisting>
        <para>This may produce output as shown below:</para>
        <programlisting xlink:href="listings/listing-6.txt"/>
        <para>You can also subscribe to the notifications made available by the SanityReport MBean to be informed of sanity check results. Please
          consult eXist-db's <link xlink:href="jmx.xml">JMX documentation</link> on how to configure this.</para>
      </sect3>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="client-side-backup">
    <title>Client-side Backup</title>

    <para>For client-side backups you can either use the <link xlink:href="java-admin-client">Java Admin Client</link> or the backup command line
      utility.</para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Using the Java Admin Client</title>


      <para>If you are using the <link xlink:href="java-admin-client">Java Admin Client</link>, do the following:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select either the Backup Icon (arrow pointed upward) in the toolbar or <guimenuitem>Tools, Backup</guimenuitem> from the menu.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>From the <literal>Collection</literal> drop-down menu, select the collection to backup. To backup the entire database, select
              <literal>/db</literal>.</para>
          <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="assets/backup1.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>In the <literal>Backup-Directory</literal> field enter where the backup must be stored. Use one of the following:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>A full directory path. The backup will be written on the file system</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The name of a zip file (with a <code>.zip</code> extension). The backup will stored as a zip.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click <guimenuitem>OK</guimenuitem>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="command-line-utility">
      <title>Using the command-line utility</title>

      <para>If you are using the command-line utility for the client-side backup/restore, do the following:</para>
      <para>To launch the utility, do one of the following:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run either the <literal>bin/backup.sh</literal> (Linux/Unix) or
              <literal>bin\backup.bat</literal> (Windows) script</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enter on the command-line (to view the all the available options use the <literal>-h</literal> parameter):</para>
          <programlisting xlink:href="listings/listing-7.txt"/>
          <para>To view the all the available options use the <literal>-h</literal> parameter.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>For example, to backup the entire database on a Unix system to the target directory <literal>/var/backup/hd060501</literal>, enter the
        following:</para>
      <programlisting>bin/backup.sh -u admin -p admin-pass -b /db -d /var/backup/hd060501</programlisting>

      <para>By default, the utility connects to the database at the URI: <literal>xmldb:exist://localhost:8080/exist/xmlrpc</literal>. If you want to
        backup a database at a different location, specify its <literal>XML:DB URI</literal> (excluding any collection path) using the
          <literal>-ouri</literal> parameter. For example:</para>

      <programlisting xlink:href="listings/listing-9.txt"/>
      <para>Default settings for the user, password or server URIs can also be set in the
          <literal>backup.properties</literal> file.</para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="restore">
    <title>Restoring the Database</title>

    <note>
      <para>Restoring from a backup (or parts of it) does not mean that the existing data in the current database instance will be deleted entirely.
        The restore process will upload the collections and documents contained in the backup. Collections and documents which exist in the database
        but are not part of the backup will not be modified.</para>
      <para>This is a feature, not a bug. It allows us to restore selected parts of the database without touching the rest.</para>
      <para>If you really need to restore into a completely clean database, proceed as follows:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Stop the running eXist database instance</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Change into directory <literal>EXIST_HOME/webapp/WEB-INF/data</literal> or another directory you specified as data directory in the
            configuration (<code>conf.xml</code>).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Remove all <literal>.dbx</literal>, <literal>.lck</literal> and
              <literal>.log</literal> files. <emphasis role="bold">This means removing all your old
              data!</emphasis> eXist will recreate those files upon the next restart.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Start eXist again and launch a restore.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </note>

    <para>To restore the database files from a backup, you can use either the <link xlink:href="java-admin-client">Java Admin Client</link> or the
      backup command line utility.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Restore using the Java Admin Client</title>

      <para>For restoring a backup using the <link xlink:href="java-admin-client">Java Admin Client</link>, do the following:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select either the Restore Icon (arrow pointed downward) in the toolbar or <guimenuitem>Tools, Restore</guimenuitem> from the
            menu.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The dialog box will prompt you to select the backup file to restore. Select one of the following: </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The descriptor <literal>__contents__.xml</literal> file from the topmost
                directory (Collection) you want to restore.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>A zip file containing the backup to restore.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>


        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A second dialog box will prompt you for an admin password to use for the restore process.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the restore was accepted, a progress dialog box will display the restored files:</para>
          <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="assets/backup3.png"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </informalfigure>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Using the Command Line</title>

      <para>To restore from a backup using the command-line utility, please refer to <xref linkend="command-line-utility"/>. </para>
      <para>Add the <literal>-r</literal> parameter and the full path to the <literal>__contents__.xml</literal> file to restore. For example:</para>

      <programlisting xlink:href="listings/listing-10.txt"/>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Repairing the Package Repository After Restore</title>

      <para>After a complete restore, your package repository will probably be out of sync. The dashboard will not show all the packages you had
        previously installed, even though their data collections have been restored (into <literal>/db/apps</literal> by default). This happens
        because the package registry, which is stored on the file system, is not part of a backup.</para>

      <para>A manual repair step is required to get the package repository in sync again. This is
        implemented as an XQuery module, which you can run (via for instance eXide).</para>
      <para>The repair module provides the following interface:</para>
      <variablelist spacing="compact">
        <varlistentry>
          <term>repair:clean-all()</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Unlinks all currently installed packages from the package manager without removing deployed data from the db.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>repair:repair()</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Scan the app root collection in the db for deployed packages and register each of them with the package repository. This
              reconstructs the metadata for the package. The data stored in the db will not be modified in any way.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>repair:repair($collection)</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Only try to repair the application whose deployed data is stored in the given collection.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>After a complete restore into a clean database, the clean-all and repair functions would typically be combined in the following
        XQuery:</para>
      <programlisting language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-11.txt"/>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="emergency-export-tool">
    <title>Emergency Export Tool</title>

    <para>eXist-db provides an emergency consistency check and backup utility. This tool is
      typically used if the database becomes corrupt and does not start up anymore.</para>
    <para>This tool needs direct access to the database files, so you must stop the running database
      instance first if it is active.</para>
    <para>Use the following command line to start the utility as a GUI:</para>
    <programlisting>java -jar start.jar org.exist.backup.ExportGUI</programlisting>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="assets/exportgui.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>Click <guimenuitem>Check</guimenuitem> to run a consistency check only. An error report will be written into the directory specified in
        <guimenuitem>Output Directory</guimenuitem>. Click <guimenuitem>Check &amp; Export</guimenuitem> to run a consistency check
        <emphasis>and</emphasis> a full backup.</para>
    <para>On a headless system use the command-line version instead (The <literal>-h</literal> parameter will get you a list of possible
      options):</para>
    <programlisting>java -jar start.jar org.exist.backup.ExportMain</programlisting>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="standalone">

    <title>Standalone Backup/Restore on Server Platforms</title>

    <para>The instructions above assume you have a standard eXist installation in place, either from
      a release package or a full build environment. That is not always the case on remotely
      deployed server instances.</para>
    <para>To support such deployment scenarios, there is a tool called <literal>backrest</literal>, that makes it easier to do
      restores local to the deployed server. The tool can be found in the sub-folder <literal>tools/backrest</literal>. You can compile the tool by running <literal>ant</literal> in that folder.</para>

    <para>Building the backrest tool will create a fully self-contained zip file in the <code>tools/backrest/dist/eXist-db-backrest-4.0.0/lib</code> directory that can be copied to a
      remote server and used to do both restores and backups local to that server.</para>
    <para>Just unzip the <code>backrest</code> zip file (preserving subdirectories) and execute either the <code>backup.bat</code> or
        <code>backup.sh</code> scripts per the prior instructions and parameter usage. </para>

  </sect1>
</article>
