<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>Versioning Extensions</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>application-development</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->


  <para>eXist-db provides a basic document versioning extension. This extension tracks all changes
    to a document by storing the differences between the revisions. Older versions can be restored
    on the fly and even queried in memory. There's also basic support to detect and intercept
    conflicting writes.</para>
  <para>The versioning extension was created with human editors in mind. These will typically change
    documents through an editor or some form-based front-end. It should work well with documents up
    to several megabytes in size. </para>
  <note>
    <para>eXist-db has no control over the client. It does not know where a document update comes
      from and cannot directly communicate with the user. The versioning extension should therefore
      be seen more like a toolbox than a complete solution. Advanced functionality (merging,
      conflict resolution, etc.) will require support from the end-user applications.</para>
  </note>
  <warning>
    <para>The versioning will not track machine-generated node-level edits using XUpdate or XQuery
      update extensions.</para>
  </warning>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Components</title>

    <para>The versioning extensions has the following components:</para>
    <variablelist spacing="compact">
      <varlistentry>
        <term><code>VersioningTrigger</code></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A trigger (to be registered with a collection) that implements the core versioning
            functionality</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><code>VersioningFilter</code></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A serialization filter which adds special version attributes to every document.
            These attributes are used to detect conflicting writes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <literal>versioning.xqm</literal>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>An XQuery module which provides a function library for end-user applications,
            including functions like <code>v:doc</code> (restore a given revision on the
            fly).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Setup</title>

    <para>Versioning can be enabled for separate collections in the collection hierarchy. To enable
      versioning, a trigger must be registered with the top-level collection. This is done through
      the same collection configuration files, <code>collection.xconf</code>, that are used for
      defining indexes.</para>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Register the versioning trigger</title>

      <para>To enable versioning for a collection, you have to edit the collection's
          <literal>collection.xconf</literal> configuration file. This file must be stored below the
          <literal>/db/system/config</literal> collection. As described in the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="indexing.xml">Configuring
          Indexes</link> document, the <literal>/db/system/config</literal> collection mirrors the
        hierarchical structure of the main collection tree.</para>
      <para>Within <literal>collection.xconf</literal>, you must register the trigger class
          <literal>org.exist.versioning.VersioningTrigger</literal> for the <code>create</code>,
          <code>update</code>, <code>delete</code>, <code>copy</code> and <code>move</code>
        events:</para>
      <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-1.xml"/>

      <para>If you store above document into
          <literal>/db/system/config/db/collection.xconf</literal>, it will enable versioning for
        the entire database.</para>
      <warning>
        <para>A <literal>collection.xconf</literal> at a lower level in the hierarchy will
            <emphasis>overwrite</emphasis> any configuration on higher levels, including these
          trigger definitions. Triggers are not inherited from ancestor configurations. If the new
          configuration doesn't define a trigger, the trigger map will be empty.</para>
        <para>When working with nested collection configurations, you need to make sure that the
          trigger definitions are present in all <literal>collection.xconf</literal> files.</para>
      </warning>
      <para><code>VersioningTrigger</code> accepts one parameter, <literal>overwrite</literal>: if
        this is set to <code>no</code>, the trigger will check for potential write conflicts. For
        example, if two users opened the same document and are editing it, it may happen that the
        first user saves his changes without the second user recognizing it. The second user also
        made changes and if eXist did allow him to store his version, he would just overwrite the
        modifications already committed by the first user.</para>
      <para>The <literal>overwrite="no"</literal> setting prevents this. However, eXist has no
        control over the client. It does not know where the conflicting document came from. All it
        can do is reject the write attempt and raise an error. The error should then be handled by
        the client. Right now there are no clients to support this. More work will be required in
        this area. However, clients can already use the supplied XQuery functions to check for write
        conflicts (see below).</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Enabling the serialization filter</title>

      <para>In order to detect conflicting writes, the versioning extension needs to keep track of
        the base revision to which changes were applied. It does this by inserting special metadata
        attributes into a document when it is retrieved from the database. For this purpose, a
          <emphasis>custom filter</emphasis> has to be registered with eXist's serializer. </para>
      <para>This is done in the <tag>serializer</tag> section in the main configuration file,
          <literal>conf.xml</literal>. Add a <tag>custom-filter</tag> child tag to the
          <tag>serializer</tag> element and set its <literal>class</literal> attribute to
          <literal>org.exist.versioning.VersioningFilter</literal>:</para>
      <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-2.xml"/>
      <para>eXist must be restarted for the versioning filter to become active.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>


  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Accessing the versioning information</title>

    <para>The versioning extension uses the collection <literal>/db/system/versions</literal> to
      store base revisions and differences. The collection hierarchy below
        <literal>/db/system/versions</literal> mirrors the main collection tree. For each versioned
      resource, you'll find a document with suffix <literal>.base</literal>, which contains the base
      revision (the first version of the document). Each revision is stored in a document which
      starts with the original document name and ends with the revision number, for instance
        <literal>hamlet.xml.35</literal>.</para>

    <para>eXist provides an XQuery module to access the revision history or restore a given
      revision. For example, to view the history of a resource:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-3.txt"/>
    <para>This returns an XML fragment like this:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-4.txt"/>
    <para>The most important function is <literal>v:doc</literal>, which is used to restore an
      arbitrary revision of a document on the fly. You can use this function similar to the standard
        <literal>fn:doc</literal> to query the revision. For example:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-5.txt"/>
    <para>This will restore revision 35 of <literal>hamlet.xml</literal> and then find all
        <tag>SPEECH</tag> elements with a <tag>SPEAKER</tag> called "HAMLET". No indexes are
      available to the query engine when processing a restore document.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Detecting write conflicts</title>

    <para>To avoid a user overwriting the changes made by another user, eXist needs to know upon
      which revision the user's changes are based. To make this possible, the versioning filter adds
      a number of metadata attributes to the root element of a document when it is serialized (for
      instance when opening it in an editor). The inserted metadata attributes are all in a separate
      versioning namespace and will never be stored in the database. The following fragment shows
      the added attributes:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-6.xml"/>
    <para>When eXist detects a potential write conflict, it cannot do more than reject the update
      and raise an error. However, there's an XQuery function to check if newer revisions exist. You
      pass it the revision number and the unique key as given in the versioning attributes of the
      document root element. If the function returns the empty sequence, no newer revisions exist in
      the database. Otherwise, the function returns the version documents for each newer revision. </para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-7.txt"/>
    <para>Once you made sure that you really want to store the document and overwrite any revisions,
      simply remove the version attributes from the root element.</para>

  </sect1>
</article>