<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>Code Review Guide</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>exist</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>This article provides guidelines on how to do a proper code review when developing for eXist-db's own code base.</para>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The following areas are important when conducting code review:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Does the solution provide custom class libraries for reusable classes &amp; methods?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>What classes have been extended or implemented and whether they are supported?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Look for deprecated classes &amp; methods. Look for alternate methods if deprecated methods used. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Have the proper classes been extended to provide functionality based on functional requirements? Check whether objects have been
          extended too heavily where a lighter extension would suffice. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Are proper abstract classes &amp; interfaces used to provide a flexible, yet cohesive design model? </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Has code been properly documented, for instance using JavaDoc?</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>And in general, we will look for the 7 Deadly Sins of Software Design and make recommendation accordingly:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Rigidity: Make it hard to change, especially if changes result in ripple effects or when you don't know what will happen when you make
          changes. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Fragility: Make it easy to break. Whenever you change something, something breaks. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Immobility: Make it hard to reuse. When something is coupled to everything. When you try to take a piece of code (class etc.) it takes
          all of its dependencies with it. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Viscosity: Make it hard to do the right thing. There are usually several ways to work with a design. Viscosity happens when it is hard
          to work with the design the way the designer intended to. The results are tricks and workarounds that, many times, have unexpected outcomes
          (especially if the design is also fragile). </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Needless Complexity (Over design): When you overdo it (the "Swiss-Army knife" anti-pattern). A class that tries to anticipate every
          possible need. Another example is applying too many patterns to a simple problem. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Needless Repetition: The same code is scattered around which makes it error prone.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="italic">The 7th Deadly Sin of Software Design is (the obvious) "Not doing any". </emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Clean Unnecessary Code</title>

    <para>As our business needs and techniques evolve, there are more and more changes to our implementation, therefore a lot of code gets deprecated.
      Some of this may need to remain, due to legacy data. However, some of it can be cleaned to make maintenance easy and improve performance.</para>
    <para>Different cases that might be found in the review:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Whole classes are deprecated</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Code segments are unnecessary due to changes.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Redundant registration of listener services.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>A good planning at the beginning will help to avoid messy code. And whenever there is a change to be implemented, plan it first with a
      thorough review to its impact and identify the code that needs to be changed. Only then implementation can start.</para>
    <para>We recommend to review code that has a lot changes remove unnecessary code and merge similar code using team discussion. This may be
      scheduled after migrated system go-live. It will improve code quality, make it easy for debugging, and reduce unnecessary maintenance
      work.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Optimize and reduce database query to improve performance</title>

    <para>Sometimes, we need to balance between Disk/Network and RAM access. We may improve performance at cost of memory, as long as memory
      consumption is not the bottleneck. As a rule of the thumb, a database query is more expensive then in memory processing in terms of performance,
      so we need to optimize and combine some of the queries to reduce database queries as much as possible. </para>
    <para>Another balance is between the optimization and readability. We need to manage optimization in a controllable way.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Use local cache to improve performance</title>

    <para>It is recommended to use local caches to store frequently accessed data to avoid database queries. Such a cache mechanism is simple and easy
      to implement.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Avoid the use of expensive operations</title>

    <para>Avoid using any expensive operations such as String concatenations. String concatenations are expensive because Strings are constant; their
      values cannot be changed after they are created. So each concatenation will create a new String object.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Proper rollback of database transactions</title>

    <para>For database transaction take care of rollback properly. Here is an example how <emphasis>not</emphasis> to do this:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="java" xlink:href="listings/listing-1.txt"/>
    <para>The consequence of this code is that if there is an error when executing the transaction, the transaction will not be rolled back correctly.
      This will have an impact on data integrity. </para>

    <para>We recommend using the following structure for all database transactions to ensure data integrity. </para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="java" xlink:href="listings/listing-2.txt"/>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Hard Coding</title>

    <para>Hard code is hard to maintain and may cause potential problems.Here is an example: </para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="java" xlink:href="listings/listing-3.txt"/>
    <para>This code will remove the host name from the URL. However, it is hard coded and will break if there is a rehosting. </para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Resources not released</title>

    <para>Resource should be released when it is not needed. Here is an example:</para>
    <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="java" xlink:href="listings/listing-4.txt"/>
    <para>The FileInputStream is not closed before returning from the method.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Comply to Java Coding Standards</title>

    <para>Code conventions are important to programmers for a number of reasons:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>80% of the costs, over the lifetime of a piece of software, goes to maintenance.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Hardly any software is maintained for its whole life by the original author.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Code conventions improve the readability of the software, allowing engineers to understand new code more quickly and thoroughly.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you ship your source code as a product, you need to make sure it is well packaged and clean, as any other product you create.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>eXist follows the Sun coding standards. In addition to that:</para>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Comments</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Further details on JavaDoc comments over and above the Sun standard, can be found in the Sun Doc Comments how to guide. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Have JavaDoc comment for all classes </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Each class should have a comment. This comment should describe the function, intent and role of the class. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Have JavaDoc comment for all methods </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Each method should have a comment describing how the method is called and what it does. Discussion of implementation specifics should
            be avoided since this is not for the user of a method to know in most cases. That information belongs in implementation comments. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Within the method JavaDoc comment, info should be added on the parameters. Each method JavaDoc comment should contain an
              <code>@param</code> comment for each parameter, an <code>@return</code> comment if not a void or constructor method, and an
              <code>@throws</code> comment for each exception (cf. Documenting Exceptions with <code>@throws</code> Tag). </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The method pre and post conditions should be documented here. Pre-conditions comprise parameter ranges and the overall state of the
            object and system expected when calling the method. Post-conditions should document the expected return value sets and the state of the
            object and system that will apply when the method exits. These should map to assertions. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The JavaDoc should also document traceability of this method to the design and the requirements. Have JavaDoc comment for all fields
            Each non-trivial field should have a comment describing the role and purpose of the field, as well as any other appropriate information
            such as the range. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Exceptions</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>All exceptions should be handled, it is never acceptable to simply print the exception message and stack trace. Exceptions should be
            dealt and corrective or informative action taken to highlight the issue.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>For debugging purposes the stack trace should be logged at the final destination of the exception or at whenever the exception is
            modified, for example throwing a XXException instead of a <code>java.io.IOException</code>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Logging</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If no logging system is in use in the package already or the logging is unconditional, then log4j should be used for all logging.
            Please see the <emphasis>Log4J Logging Guide</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If a class has unconditional logging, then it should be updated to use log4j. A case of unconditional logging is where there are
              <code>System.out.println()</code> in the code with no conditions surrounding the call. This unnecessarily clutters the log and places a
            burden on performance.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Logging should always be performed at method exit and entry as follows:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Log entry</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Log arguments</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Log exit</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Log return values</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The occurrence of exceptions and the stack trace should also be logged as info level items.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Logging calls should be wrapped in enablement checks so that arguments do not get unnecessarily evaluated for example:</para>
          <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="java" xlink:href="listings/listing-5.txt"/>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Assertions</title>


      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Assertions should be used in the code to verify that the expected results have occurred. Assertions should be used as liberally as
            possible. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Standard Assertions should be performed at method entry and exit; these methods should validate the pre and post-conditions for the
            method. All arguments should be checked for validity as should the return values. Similarly the state of the object and broader system
            should be checked as appropriate on both method entry and exit, for example if a file is open. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

</article>