<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>Java Admin Client</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>operations</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>eXist-db ships with the so-called "Java Admin Client". This application enables users to perform administrative tasks, such as user
    management, security settings, batch import of whole directories, and backup/restore of the database. It can be used either as a GUI or on the
    command line.</para>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="launching">
    <title>Launching the Client</title>

    <para>You can launch the Java Admin Client using one of the following methods:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Windows and Linux users: Click the eXist-db icon in the taskbar and choose the <guimenuitem>Open Java Admin Client</guimenuitem> menu
          entry.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>You can download its Java WebStart file <code>exist.jnlp</code> via your web browser. Once the download has completed, double-click it
          to launch the client: </para>
        <para>
          <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="/webstart/exist.jnlp">
            <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="assets/webstart.small.jpg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>
          </link>
        </para>
        <para>You can also find a link to download the Java WebStart file on the dashboard.</para>
        <note>
          <para>If you built eXist-db from source rather than using the downloadable installer, the Java WebStart function will not work unless you
            sign the jars. To do so, enter the following on your command line from the eXist directory: </para>
          <programlisting>build.bat -f build/scripts/jarsigner.xml (DOS/Windows)</programlisting>
          <programlisting>build.sh -f build/scripts/jarsigner.xml  (Unix)</programlisting>
        </note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Enter the following on your command line from the eXist installation directory (with the <code>JAVA_HOME</code> environment variable set
          correctly):</para>
        <programlisting>bin\client.bat (DOS/Windows)</programlisting>
        <programlisting>bin/client.sh (Unix)</programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Or enter the following on the command line (again from the eXist installation directory):</para>
        <programlisting>java -jar start.jar client</programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="gui">
    <title>Using the Graphical Client</title>

    <para>Once the Graphical Client is launched, you will see the "eXist Database Login" window.</para>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="assets/client1.png" width="75%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>

    <para>The Java Admin Client can connect to a database in two ways:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Most common is to connect to a "remote" server. The client talks with the server using the XML RPC protocol.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>It can also launch an "enbedded database", that is, a database embedded in an application which runs in the same process as the client.
          This embedded option is useful for backup/restore or mass uploads of data; writing to an embedded instance avoids the network
          overhead.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>



    <para>To connect to a remote server, enter your eXist-db username and password, select <guimenuitem>Remote</guimenuitem> from the
        <guimenuitem>Type</guimenuitem> dropdown menu, and in the URL field enter the database's URI. This by default set to
        <code>xmldb:exist://localhost:8080/exist/xmlrpc</code> (the URI for a database installed with all the default settings).</para>
    <para>After clicking <guimenuitem>OK</guimenuitem>, the main client window will open.</para>
    <informalfigure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="assets/client2.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <para>This window is split into two panels. The top panel lists the database collections. The bottom panel acts like a shell and has a command
      prompt. This shell allows you to manually enter database commands.</para>
    <para>Using the Java Admin Client as a GUI is like using any other GUI application. That is why we do not explain it further.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>If eXist-db is online, you expose it to exploitation if you use an empty admin password. If you did not specify an admin password during
        installation, you are strongly advised to set an admin password as soon as possible. You can do this in the Java Admin Client:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Open the <guimenuitem>Edit Users</guimenuitem> window by selecting the <guimenuitem>Manage Users</guimenuitem> icon (image of a pair
            of keys) in the toolbar</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>At the top, select the <guimenuitem>admin</guimenuitem> user in the table of users</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Type in the new password into the password fields</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Click the <guimenuitem>Modify User</guimenuitem> button to apply the changes</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="assets/client3.png" width="50%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
    </warning>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="command-line">
    <title>Using the Command-line Client</title>

    <para>It is sometimes faster or more convenient to use the Java Admin Client on the command line. The following sections provide a quick
      introduction to the most common command line parameters and their use. The client offers three modes of operation:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If an action is specified on the command-line (when starting the client), it will be processed in non-interactive mode and the client
          will terminate after completion.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If option <literal>-s</literal> or <literal>--no-gui</literal> is specified without an action, the client switches to interactive
          shell-mode and prompts for user input. No graphical interface is displayed.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Otherwise the client switches to interactive mode and displays the graphical user interface.</para>
      </listitem>

    </orderedlist>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Interactive Shell Mode</title>

      <para>While this tutorial will not describe the interactive shell mode in detail, most commands work like their counterparts specified on the
        command line. On the shell, just type <literal>help</literal> to get a list of supported commands.</para>
      <para>The shell mode may support full command line history and command completion, depending on the OS</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para> On Unix systems, the client will try to load the GNU <code>readline</code> library, which is part of most Unix installations. This
            gives you access to all the nice things you probably know from Linux shells. For example, pressing the tab-key will try to complete
            collection and document names. However, for this to work, the native library <literal>lib/core/libJavaReadline.so</literal> has to be
            found by the system's loader. On Linux, just add <literal>lib/core</literal> to your <literal>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</literal> (the client.sh
            script does this automatically).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>On Windows OS, you should at least be able to use the cursor-up/cursor-down keys to browse through the command history.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>




      <para>To explain the shell-mode we provide a short example, showing how to store the sample files into the database.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Typing <literal>mkcol shakespeare</literal> and pressing enter will create a Shakespeare collection into which we will put some of the
            sample documents provided with eXist-db.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>To check if the new collection is present, enter <literal>ls</literal> to get a listing of the current collection contents. The
            listing below shows an example session of how to add the sample documents:</para>
          <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="listings/listing-6.txt"/>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Adding files to the database is done using <code>put</code>. This expects either a single file, a file-pattern or a directory name as
            argument. If a directory is specified, all XML and XSL files in that directory will be put into the database. </para>
          <para>To add the files in directory <code>samples/shakespeare</code> simply enter <code>put samples/shakespeare</code>. </para>
          <para>
            <literal>put</literal> also accepts file-patterns, i.e. a path with wildcards <code>?</code> or <code>*</code>. <code>**</code> means: any
            sub-directory. So the command <literal>put samples/**/*.xml</literal> will parse any XML files found in the <literal>samples</literal>
            directory and any of its sub-directories.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>To see if the files have actually been stored use <code>ls</code> again.</para>
          <para/>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>To view a document, use the get command, for instance <code>get hamlet.xml</code>
                    </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>If you ever run into problems while experimenting with eXist-db and your database files get corrupt: just remove the data files created
          by eXist-db and everything should work again. The data files all end with <literal>.dbx</literal>. You will either find them in directory
            <literal>webapp/WEB-INF/data</literal> or <literal>WEB-INF/data</literal>, depending on your installation. It is ok to backup those
          data-files to be able to restore them in case of a database corruption.</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Specifying Parameters</title>

      <para>The client uses the CLI library from Apache's Excalibur project to parse command-line parameters. This means that the same conventions
        apply as for most GNU tools. Most parameters have a short and a long form. </para>
      <para>For example, the user can be specified in short with <literal>-u user</literal> or in long with <literal>--user=user</literal>. You can
        combine argument-less parameters: for example, <literal>-ls</literal> is short for <literal>-l -s</literal>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>General Configuration</title>

      <para>The client reads its default options from the properties file <literal>client.properties</literal>. Most of the properties can be
        overwritten by command-line parameters or by the <literal>set</literal> command in shell-mode.</para>
      <para>The client relies on the XML:DB API to communicate with the database. It will therefore work with remote as well as embedded database
        instances. The correct database instance is determined through the XML:DB base URI as specified in the properties file or through command-line
        options. The <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="deployment.xml">deployment</link> article describes how different
        servers are addressed using the XML:DB URI.</para>
      <para>The XML:DB base URI used by the client for connections is defined by the <literal>uri=</literal> property. By default, this is set to
          <literal>uri=xmldb:exist://localhost:8080/exist/xmlrpc</literal>. With this, the client will try to connect to a database instance running
        inside the webserver at port 8080 of the local host. </para>
      <para>There are several ways to specify an alternate XML:DB base URI: </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Change the <literal>uri=</literal> property in <literal>client.properties</literal>
                    </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use the <literal>-ouri</literal> parameter on the command-line</para>
          <para>For instance, to access a server running inside the Jetty webserver at port <code>8080</code> on a remote host, use</para>
          <programlisting>bin/client.sh -ouri=xmldb:exist://host:8080/exist/xmlrpc</programlisting>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>To start the client in <emphasis>local</emphasis> mode, use:</para>
          <programlisting>bin/client.sh -ouri=xmldb:exist://</programlisting>
          <para> Local mode means that an embedded database instance will be initialized and started by the client. It will have direct access to the
            database instance. Use this option if you want to batch-load a large document or a huge collection of documents.</para>
          <para>Since switching to local mode is required quite often, there's also a shortcut: </para>
          <programlisting>bin/client.sh -l</programlisting>
          <para>This is equivalent to the <literal>-ouri=xmldb:exist://</literal> option shown above.</para>
          <para>When launching the client with option <literal>-l</literal> or <literal>-ouri=xmldb:exist://</literal> the configuration for the
            database instance is read from <literal>conf.xml</literal> located in <code>EXIST_HOME</code>.</para>
          <para>Use the <code>-C</code> parameter to specify an alternate database location. For instance:</para>
          <programlisting>bin/client.sh -C /home/exist/test/conf.xml</programlisting>
          <para>This will temporarily launch a new database instance whose configuration is read from the provided file. Option <literal>-C</literal>
            implies option <literal>-l</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If you have set a password for the admin user you must to authenticate yourself to the database:</para>
      <programlisting>bin/client.sh -l -u username -P password</programlisting>
      <para>If the <literal>-P</literal> password option is missing, the client will prompt for the password.</para>
      <para>The graphical user interface will always prompt for username and password unless you specify both on the command-line.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Storing documents</title>

      <para>To store a set of documents, use the <literal>-m</literal> and <literal>-p</literal> parameters. For instance:</para>
      <programlisting>bin/client.sh -m /db/shakespeare/plays -p /home/exist/xml/shakespeare</programlisting>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <literal>-m</literal> tells the client to implicitly create any missing collection.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <literal>-p</literal> parameter means that all of the following arguments should be interpreted as a list of paths to XML
            documents (you may specify more than one document or directory).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the passed path denotes a directory, the client will try to store all documents in that directory into the database. However, it
            will <emphasis>not</emphasis> recurse into subdirectories. For this, you have to pass the <literal>-d</literal> option. For
            example:</para>
          <programlisting>bin/client.sh -d -m /db/movies -p /home/exist/xml/movies</programlisting>
          <para>This will recurse into all directories below <literal>/home/exist/xml/movies</literal>. For each subdirectory, a collection will be
            created below the <literal>/db/movies</literal> collection. Use this to recursively import an entire collection tree.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para> eXist-db can also store binary resources in addition to XML files. The client tries to determine if the current file is XML or not. The
          <literal>mime-types.xml</literal> lookup table (in the eXist root installation directory) is used for this. It associates: </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>a MIME type</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>an eXist-db type ("xml" or "binary")</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>a file extension</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para> This mechanism is also used by the eXist-db servers . For example to specify that <code>.xmap</code> extension is used for XML files: </para>
      <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-14.xml"/>

    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Removing Collections/Documents</title>

      <para>The <literal>-r</literal> and <literal>-R</literal> parameters are used to remove a document or collection. </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
                        <literal>-r</literal> removes a single document from the collection specified in the <literal>-c</literal> parameter. For
            example:</para>
          <programlisting>bin/client.sh -c /db/shakespeare/plays -r hamlet.xml</programlisting>
          <para>This removes the document <literal>hamlet.xml</literal> from the <literal>/db/shakespeare/plays</literal> collection.</para>

        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>To remove the entire <literal>plays</literal> collection use the <code>-R</code> parameter:</para>
          <programlisting>bin/client.sh -c /db/shakespeare -R plays</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Executing Queries</title>
      <para>Executing queries can be done as follows:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use the <literal>-x</literal> parameter. This parameter accepts an optional argument, which specifies the query to execute. However,
            passing XQuery on the command-line is a problem on many operating systems, because the command shell usually interprets whitespace
            characters as command separators. Therefore if no argument is passed to <literal>-x</literal>, the client will try to read the query from
            standard input.</para>
          <para>For example, on Unix you may do the follwong:</para>
          <programlisting>echo "//SPEECH[contains(LINE, 'love')]" | bin/client.sh -x</programlisting>
          <para>Remember to type Ctrl-d when working without pipe:</para>
          <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="listings/listing-18.txt"/>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Queries can also be read from a file using the <code>-F</code> parameter. For example,</para>
          <programlisting>bin/client.sh -F samples/xquery/fibo.xq</programlisting>
          <para>This executes the XQuery contained in <literal>fibo.xq</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>As an addition use <literal>-n</literal> to specify the number of hits that should be printed to the standard output.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>XUpdate</title>

      <para>You can update a stored document or multiple documents by passing an XUpdate file on the command-line. For example: </para>
      <programlisting>bin/client.sh -c /db/test -f address.xml -X samples/xupdate/xupdate.xml</programlisting>
      <para>This will apply the modifications described in <literal>samples/xupdate/xupdate.xml</literal> to the document
          <literal>address.xml</literal> in collection <literal>/db/test</literal>.</para>
      <para>If you don't specify the <literal>-f</literal> option, the modifications will be applied to all documents in the collection.</para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>
</article>