<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>operations</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>This document contains hints and tips about troubleshooting problems. It also tells you
    where to find information (version numbers, log information, etc.). See also <link xlink:href="getting-help.xml">Getting
    Help</link>.</para>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="normal-start-up">
    <title>Normal Start Up</title>

    <para>When eXist-db starts up it writes log output to the console.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para> If you started eXist-db via the system tray launcher, the console output is captured.
          It can be viewed by selecting the <guimenuitem>Show Tool Window</guimenuitem> menu entry
          in the system tray pop-up. Then select <literal>Show console messages</literal>. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you launched eXist-db via one of the shell scripts, the output directly
          appears.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Output for a properly launched eXIst-db should be similar to the following (Linux)
      example:</para>

    <programlisting xlink:href="listings/listing-1.txt"/>
    <para>When you see the "Server has started" message and no further errors appear, your eXist-db
      installation is working normally.</para>
    <para>When you do not (even) see this message,try the following troubleshooting steps.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="db-locked">
    <title>Database Refuses to Start</title>

    <para>If eXist-db was not shutdown properly, it will start a recovery process to redo committed
      transactions and roll back uncommitted ones. If an inconsistency is found during this process,
      eXist-db will automatically abort the start-up and print out a warning. This emergency stop is
      done to avoid potential damage and give an administrator a chance to check the database and
      create a backup. It does not necessarily indicate a real problem. In most cases, the database
      should be ok and restarting it will be save.</para>
    <para>We recommend to run a <link xlink:href="backup">consistency check</link> in when this happens. If
      inconsistencies are found, make sure you have a backup before continuing.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="clearing-db">
    <title>Going Back to an Empty Database</title>

    <para>During development and testing you may sometimes wish to go back to a completely empty,
      fresh, database. Here's how to really <emphasis>remove everything</emphasis> and reset the
      database to its initial state:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Make sure eXist-db is not running</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you installed the source code (and therefore the development tools), call
            <code>ant</code> as follows:</para>
        <programlisting>build.sh clean-default-data-dir</programlisting>
        <para>If you do not have <code>build.sh</code> (or <code>build.bat</code>), you may can
          manually remove the contents of your data directory. </para>
        <para>The default data directory is <literal>$EXIST_HOME/webapp/WEB-INF/data</literal>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="environmental-variables">
    <title><code>JAVA_HOME</code> and <code>EXIST_HOME</code> Environmental Variables</title>

    <para>When using one of the shell or batch scripts, eXist-db can fail to start up properly if
      either of the two key environmental variables <literal>JAVA_HOME</literal> and/or
        <literal>EXIST_HOME</literal> are not set properly. Both variables are used in the
        <literal>startup.bat</literal> and <literal>startup.sh</literal> scripts and have to be set
      correctly before the scripts are run (you can of course also insert the lines required in the
      beginning of the scripts themselves).</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><literal>JAVA_HOME</literal></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This should point to the directory where Java (JRE or JDK) is installed. </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Windows</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><link xlink:href="http://confluence.atlassian.com/display/DOC/Setting+the+JAVA_HOME+Variable+in+Windows" condition="_blank">Setting <code>JAVA_HOME</code> on Windows</link></para>
                <para/>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Linux</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><link xlink:href="http://www.cyberciti.biz/faq/linux-unix-set-java_home-path-variable/" condition="_blank">Setting <code>JAVA_HOME</code> on Linux</link></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>macOS</term>
              <listitem>
                <para><link xlink:href="http://osxdaily.com/2015/07/28/set-enviornment-variables-mac-os-x/">Setting <code>JAVA_HOME</code> on macOS</link></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><literal>EXIST_HOME</literal></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This must point to the directory that contains eXist-db's configuration file
              <literal>conf.xml</literal>. For example, if the <literal>EXIST_HOME</literal> path is
              <literal>C:\Program Files\eXist</literal>, the server will look for
              <literal>C:\Program Files\eXist\conf.xml</literal>. </para>
          <para>You can set <code>EXIST_HOME</code> in the same way that you set
              <code>JAVA_HOME</code>.</para>
          <para>On macOS, depending on how you installed eXist, you would open a terminal and enter
            either: </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>for JAR based installs</term>
              <listitem>
                <programlisting>export EXIST_HOME=/Applications/eXist</programlisting>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>for DMG and homebrew installs</term>
              <listitem>
                <programlisting>export EXIST_HOME=/Applications/eXist-db.app/Contents/Resources/eXist-db</programlisting>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
          <para>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>Ensure that you have "write" permissions for the <literal>data</literal> directory
      (located by default in <literal>webapp/WEB-INF/</literal>).</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="port-conflicts">
    <title>Port Conflicts</title>

    <para>eXist-db can fail to start up if another service on your system is using the ports that
      eXist's embedded web server is using (port 8080 or 8443 by default). If another service
      occupies these ports, you cannot start up eXist-db unless you shut down the service in
      question or make eXist-db use another port.</para>
    <para>To see whether this is the case, enter <link xlink:href="http://localhost:8080/" condition="_blank">http://localhost:8080/</link> in your
      browser. To make eXist-db use another port, open
        <literal>/tools/jetty/etc/jetty-http.xml</literal> and change the value <code>8080</code> to
      a port number that is not used (for instance <code>8899</code>):</para>
    <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-6.xml"/>

    <para>eXist-db uses port 8443 for confidential communication. Another service may be using this
      port. To make eXist-db use another port, open the file
        <literal>/tools/jetty/etc/jetty-ssl.xml</literal> and change the value <code>8443</code> in
      to a port number that is not used (for instance <code>8444</code>):</para>
    <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-8.xml"/>
    <para>If these changes do not launch eXist-db try the following: Change to the directory where
      you installed eXist-db and enter the following command:</para>
    <programlisting>java -Xmx1024M -Djava.endorsed.dirs=lib/endorsed -jar start.jar jetty</programlisting>
    <para>If you have problems running the shell/batch scripts, read the section about <link xlink:href="advanced-installation.xml#bin-executables">alternative scripts</link>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="logs">
    <title>Using the Logs</title>

    <para>If you experience any problems while using eXist-db, your first step should be to check
      the log files to get additional information about the source of the problem. eXist-db uses the
        <emphasis>log4j-package</emphasis> to write output logs to files. </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para> By default, this output is written to the directory
            <literal>webapp/WEB-INF/logs</literal></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you are running eXist as a service, check the directory
            <literal>tools/yajsw/logs</literal></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The main log files for eXist are <literal>exist.log</literal> and
        <literal>xmldb.log</literal>. </para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="memory">
    <title>Out of Memory</title>

    <para>Running out of memory typically throws Java into an inconsistent state. Some threads may
      still be alive and continue to run while others have died. It is therefore important to avoid
      memory errors up-front by checking the memory consumption of your queries
        <emphasis>before</emphasis> they go into production. Should you encounter an out of memory
      error, please make sure to restart eXist and follow the emergency procedure.</para>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Streaming Large Files</title>

      <para>If you have to generate large binaries (for instance ZIP or PDF) from within XQuery, it
        is best not to do this in memory. There are various XQuery functions which directly stream
        to the HTTP response.</para>
      <para>There's also a known issue with the betterform XForms filter caching every HTTP
        response. To work around this, your XQuery should be run via an URL which is not processed
        by the XForms filter: either disable the filter or use <code>/rest</code> or
          <code>/restxq</code>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="emergency">
    <title>Killing the Database</title>

    <para>If you ever feel you have to kill the database (because it does not respond for whatever
      reason), the recommended procedure is as follows:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Check if a query is running wild and try to kill it. This can be done either through
          the "Scheduler" plug-in in the dashboard, or the "Running Jobs" section in the <link xlink:href="java-admin-client">Java Admin Client</link>. Try to kill the query there and
          wait for a minute if the system returns to normal operations:</para>
        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="assets/schedulerplugin.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Attempt to trigger a proper shutdown, either via the system tray icon or the
          dashboard. Wait for at least 3 minutes. Even if eXist-db does not stop completely, it may
          still be able to complete the shutdown procedure for the core database.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>It may now be safe to kill the eXist-db process. Check the logs to see if the database
          has properly shut down. The last message in the logs will indicate this.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the logs indicate a proper shutdown: before restarting, remove any
            <literal>.log</literal> and <literal>.lck</literal> files from the data directory. This
          will prevent a recovery run, which would certainly take a lot of time.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Otherwise:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>You are sure you have no valuable changes in this db instance, usually because
              it's a development system: follow the step above and remove the
                <literal>.log</literal> files before restart to reduce startup time.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Before restart, archive the contents of the data directory: you may need them if
              anything goes wrong. Restart the database but be prepared for a recovery run, which
              may take considerable time (depending on the size of your db).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>If inconsistencies are detected during the recovery, eXist will switch to
              read-only mode. In this case, stop it again and run a <link xlink:href="backup">consistency check</link>, which can also create a low-level backup.</para>
            <para>If the consistency check reports errors, eXist may still be able to run, but there
              might be inconsistencies in its data structures. Prepare for a complete restore into a
              clean data directory as soon as you can take the database offline for
              maintenance.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <warning>
      <para>Do not repeatedly kill the database. Killing eXist during recovery will most likely
        result in additional damages. Always check the logs and console output to see what eXist is
        doing before you kill it.</para>
    </warning>
  </sect1>
</article>