<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
   <info>
      <title>The xmldb module</title>
      <date>October 2012</date>
      <keywordset>
         <keyword>TBD</keyword>
      </keywordset>
   </info>

   <!-- ================================================================== -->

   <sect1>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>The xmldb module (in the <literal>http://exist-db.org/xquery/xmldb</literal> function
                namespace) contains functions for manipulating database contents. The full list of
                functions and their documentation is in the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="/exist/apps/fundocs/view.html?uri=http://exist-db.org/xquery/xmldb&amp;location=java:org.exist.xquery.functions.xmldb.XMLDBModule">Function Documentation Library</link>. This article discusses some of the
                highlights and main uses for this module.</para>
   </sect1>

   <!-- ================================================================== -->

   <sect1 xml:id="manipulating-database-contents">
      <title>Manipulating Database Contents</title>

      <para>The xmldb functions can be used to create new database collections, or to store
                query output into the database. To illustrate, suppose we have a large file
                containing several RDF metadata records, but we do not want to store the metadata
                records in a single file, since our application expects each record to have its own
                document. In this case, we must divide the document into smaller units. Using an
                XSLT stylesheet would be one way to accomplish this; however, this is quite
                memory-intensive, and the preferable option is to use XQuery to do the
                job.</para>
      <para>The XQuery script below shows how to split a large RDF file into a series of
                smaller documents:</para>
      <example>
         <title>Splitting a Document</title>
         <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-1.txt"/>
      </example>
      <para>Let's look at this script in some detail. First, since we are using functions
                xmldb:create-collection() and xmldb:store(), which require the user to be logged in
                as a member of the dba group, we must log in using xmldb:login(). Once logged in, we
                can create a new sub-collection, called "output" using
                    <literal>xmldb:create-collection</literal>, for which we need to be logged in
                appropriately using <literal>xmldb:login</literal>.</para>
      <para>Next, the <literal>for</literal>-loop iterates through all child elements of the
                top RDF element. In each iteration, we use <literal>xmldb:store</literal> to write out
                the current child node to a new document. Since a unique document name is required
                for each new document, we need a way to generate unique names. In this case, the URI
                contained in the <literal>rdf:about</literal> attribute is unique, so we simply
                compute an MD5 key from it, append the ".xml" extension, and use it as the
                document's name.</para>
   </sect1>

   <!-- ================================================================== -->

   <sect1 xml:id="specifying-document-sets">
      <title>Specifying the Input Document Set</title>

      <para>A database can contain a virtually unlimited set of collections and documents.
                Four functions are available to restrict the input document set to a user-defined set of
                documents or collections: <literal>doc()</literal>, <literal>xmldb:document()</literal>, <literal>collection()</literal> and
                    <literal>xmldb:xcollection()</literal>. The <literal>collection()</literal> and
                    <literal>doc()</literal> functions are standard XQuery/XPath functions, whereas
                    <literal>xmldb:xcollection()</literal> and <literal>xmldb:document()</literal>
                are eXist-db-specific extensions.</para>
      <para>Without an URI scheme, eXist-db interprets the arguments to
                    <literal>collection()</literal> and <literal>doc()</literal> as absolute or
                relative paths, leading to some collection or document within the database. For
                example:</para>
      <programlisting>doc("/db/collection1/collection2/resource.xml")</programlisting>
      <para>refers to a resource stored in
                <literal>/db/collection1/collection2</literal>.</para>
      <programlisting>doc("resource.xml")</programlisting>
      <para>references a resource relative to the base URI property defined in the static
                XQuery context. The base URI contains an XML:DB URI pointing to the base collection
                for the current query context, e.g. <literal>xmldb:exist:///db</literal>.</para>
      <para>The base collection depends on how the query context was initialized. If you call
                a query via the XML:DB API, the base collection is the collection from which the
                query service was obtained. All relative URLs will be resolved relative to that
                collection. If a stored query is executed via REST, the base collection is the
                collection in which the XQuery source resides. In most other cases, the base
                collection will point to the database root /db. </para>
      <note>
         <para>As it might not always be clear what the base collection is, we recommend to
                    use an explicit path to access a document. This makes it easier to use a query
                    via different interfaces.</para>
      </note>
      <para>You can also pass a full URI to the <literal>doc()</literal> function:</para>
      <programlisting>doc("http://localhost:8080/exist/servlet/db/test.xml")</programlisting>
      <para>in this case, the URI will be retrieved and the data stored into a temporary
                document in the database.</para>
      <variablelist spacing="compact">
         <varlistentry>
            <term>doc() / xmldb:document()</term>
            <listitem>
               <para>While <literal>doc()</literal> is restricted to a single document-URI
                            argument, <literal>xmldb:document()</literal> accepts multiple document
                            paths to be included into the input node set. Second, calling
                                <literal>xmldb:document()</literal> without an argument includes
                                <emphasis>EVERY</emphasis> document node in the current database
                            instance. Some examples:</para>
               <programlisting>doc("/db/apps/demo/data/hamlet.xml")//SPEAKER</programlisting>
               <programlisting>xmldb:document('/db/test/abc.xml', '/db/test/def.xml')//title</programlisting>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
         <varlistentry>
            <term>collection() / xmldb:xcollection()</term>
            <listitem>
               <para>The <literal>collection()</literal> function specifies
                            the collection of documents to be included in the query evaluation. By
                            default, documents found in sub-collections of the specified collection
                            are also included. For example, suppose we have a collection <literal>/db/test</literal> that includes two sub-collections
                                <literal>/db/test/abc</literal> and <literal>/db/test/def</literal>. In this case, the function
                            call <literal>collection('/db/test')</literal> will
                            include all of the resources found in <literal>/db/test</literal>, <literal>/db/test/abc</literal> and <literal>/db/test/def</literal>.</para>
               <para>The function <literal>xmldb:xcollection()</literal>
                            can be used to change the behavior of <literal>collection()</literal>. For instance, the function call </para>
               <programlisting>xmldb:xcollection('/db/test')//title</programlisting>
               <para>will ONLY include resources found in <literal>/db/test</literal>, but NOT in <literal>/db/test/abc</literal> or <literal>/db/test/def</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
   </sect1>
</article>