<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
   <info>
      <title>xqDoc</title>
      <date>August 2012</date>
      <keywordset>
         <keyword>TBD</keyword>
      </keywordset>
   </info>

   <!-- ================================================================== -->

   <sect1>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para> xqDoc comments are used to document XQuery library and main modules in a manner
                similar to how Javadoc comments are used to document Java classes and packages. With
                the documentation close to the source, it increases the chances that the
                documentation will be kept current and with tools provided by xqDoc, useful
                documentation can be quickly and easily generated. It should be noted that a XQuery
                module does not need to contain xqDoc style comments in order for the xqDoc tools to
                produce useful output. Without any xqDoc documentation style comments, a very useful
                cross reference (for modules, functions, and variables) and XQuery code browser (for
                modules and functions) will be created by the xqDoc tools. </para>
      <para>xqDoc comments are extracted when eXist parses an XQuery and keeps them with the
                FunctionSignature. To not slow down the parsing, comments are stored as plain
                strings. The comments can be parsed and merged into the function signature later, if
                they are needed.  This would allow tools like eXide to display up to date
                documentation while you are working on a module.</para>
   </sect1>

   <!-- ================================================================== -->

   <sect1>
      <title>Comment Style</title>

      <para> xqDoc style comments begin with a  '(:~'  and end with a  ':)' . Of course,
                 '(::'  would have been preferable to indicate the beginning of an xqDoc style
                comment (since it mimics the JavaDoc style of  '/**' ) but we didn't want to cause
                confusion with an XQuery pragma (since this decision was made, the definition for
                XQuery pragma has been changed). The choice for the begin pattern is really quite
                arbitrary. In any case, one xqDoc style comment can
                be specified before each of the following rules (based on the W3C XQuery 1.0 BNF)
                for library modules and main modules. </para>
      <para>Library Modules</para>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>Module Declaration</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Module Import</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Variable Definition</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Function Definition</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Main Modules</para>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>Main Module</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Module Import</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Variable Definition</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Function Definition</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Like Javadoc, the following tags have special meaning within an xqDoc comment. In
                addition, the values provided for each of the tags can contain embedded XHTML markup
                to enhance or emphasize the xqDoc XHTML presentation. However, make sure the content
                is well formed and that entities are used (i.e. &amp;amp; instead of &amp;). The
                beginning text (up to the first tag) is assumed to be description text for the
                component being documented.</para>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

      <sect2>
         <title>@author</title>

         <para>The @author tag identifies the author for the documented component. Zero or
                    more @author tags can be specified (one per author) </para>
         <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-1.txt"/>
      </sect2>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

      <sect2>
         <title>@version</title>

         <para>The @version tag identifies the version of the documented component. Zero or
                    more @version tags can be specified (one per version) but in reality only a
                    single @version tag would normally make sense. The value for the @version tag
                    can be an arbitrary string.</para>
         <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-2.txt"/>
      </sect2>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

      <sect2>
         <title>@since</title>

         <para>The @since tag identifies the version when a documented component was
                    supported. Zero or many @since tags can be specified, but in reality only a
                    single @since tag would normally make sense. The value for the @since tag can be
                    an arbitrary string but should likely match an appropriate version value.</para>
         <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-3.txt"/>
      </sect2>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

      <sect2>
         <title>@see</title>

         <para>The @see tag provides the ability to hypertext link to an external web site, a
                    library or main module contained in xqDoc, a specific function (or variable)
                    defined in a library or main module contained in xqDoc, or arbitrary text. To
                    link to an external site, use a complete URL such as http://www.xquery.com. To
                    link to a library or main module contained in xqDoc, simply provide the URI for
                    the library or main module. To link to a specific function (or variable) defined
                    in an xqDoc library or main module, simply provide the URI for the library or
                    main module followed by a ';' and finally the function or variable name. To
                    provide a <emphasis role="italic">name</emphasis> for a link, simply include a
                    second ';' followed by the name. To provide text, simply include the 'text'.
                    Multiple @see tags can be specified (one per link or string of text).</para>
         <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-4.txt"/>
      </sect2>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

      <sect2>
         <title>@param</title>

         <para>The @param tag identifies the parameters associated with a function. For each
                    parameter in a function, there should be a @param tag. The @param tag should be
                    followed by the parameter name (as indicated in the function signature) and then
                    the parameter description.</para>
         <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-5.txt"/>
      </sect2>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

      <sect2>
         <title>@return</title>

         <para>The @return tag describes what is returned from a function. Zero or one
                    @return tags can be specified.</para>
         <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-6.txt"/>
      </sect2>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

      <sect2>
         <title>@deprecated</title>

         <para>The @deprecated tag identifies the identifies the documented component as
                    being deprecated. The string of text associated with the @deprecated tag should
                    indicate when the item was deprecated and what to use as a replacement.</para>
         <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-7.txt"/>
      </sect2>

      <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

      <sect2>
         <title>@error</title>

         <para>The @error tag identifies the types of errors that can be generated by the
                    function. Zero or more @error tags can be specified. An arbitrary string of text
                    can be provided for a value.</para>
         <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-8.txt"/>
      </sect2>
   </sect1>

   <!-- ================================================================== -->

   <sect1>
      <title>A representative library module comment</title>

      <para>This comment would precede the module declaration statement for the library
                module.</para>
      <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-9.txt"/>
   </sect1>

   <!-- ================================================================== -->

   <sect1>
      <title>A representative library module function comment</title>

      <para>This comment would precede the function declaration statement in the library
                module.</para>
      <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-10.txt"/>
   </sect1>
</article>