<!-- $Id$ -->
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <productname>eXist-db – Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>Dashboard</title>
        <date>September 2012</date>
    </bookinfo>
    <chapter>
        <title>Dashboard</title>
        <section>
            <title>About the Dashboard</title>
            <para>The eXist-db Dashboard is the central application launchpad and administration
                facility for eXist-db. Much like a tablet or smartphone home screen, the Dashboard
                displays a list of applications, or "apps".</para>
            <para>The Dashboard supports both "apps" and "plugins". Apps are self-contained
                applications providing their own web GUI, while "plugins" run inside the Dashboard
                as simple, single-screen dialogs. Examples for apps are the eXist-db documentation,
                eXide, or the demo app. Examples for plugins are the package manager or the
                collection browser. Plugins are most suitable for administrative functions.</para>
            <para>In addition to applications and plugins, the package repository does also provide
                library and resource packages. They do usually not provide a web GUI and are thus
                not visible on the Dashboard home screen. However, they will appear in the list of
                installed packages within the package manager. You can read more about the different
                types of packages in the <ulink url="repo.xml">package repository
                    documentation</ulink>.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Login</title>
            <figure floatstyle="left">
                <title>Login as User admin</title>
                <graphic fileref="resources/dashboardLogin.png"/>
            </figure>
            <para>To fully use the administration plugins, you need to be logged in as a dba user.
                You may access plugins as a non-dba user, but as soon as you want to apply changes,
                you will get a permission error.</para>
            <para>You can log in by clicking on the link in the left corner of the Dashboard frame. 
                If you are logged in as another user, click on the user
                name to log out.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Using the Package Manager</title>
            <figure floatstyle="left">
                <title>The Package Manager Icon</title>
                <graphic fileref="resources/dashboardPMIcon.png"/>
            </figure>
            <para>The Package Manager lists all installed and available packages. If updates to
                installed packages are available, this is marked in red.</para>
            <para>To filter the package list, select the corresponding radio buttons to see either
                    <guibutton>installed</guibutton> or <guibutton>available</guibutton> packages. Detailed information about each package can
                be viewed by selecting the <guibutton>show details</guibutton> checkbox in the
                upper-right corner.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Installing/Removing a Package</title>
                <figure floatstyle="left">
                    <title>Installing an App</title>
                    <graphic fileref="resources/dashboardInstallApp.png"/>
                </figure>
                <para>To install an app from the public repository, move your mouse over the app. You
                    should see an install button if the app is not currently installed, or a remove
                    button if it is.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Updating a Package</title>
                <figure floatstyle="left">
                    <title>Available Updates to Installed Packages</title>
                    <graphic fileref="resources/dashboardUp2dateApps.png"/>
                </figure>
                <para>Updates to already installed packages appear with the currently installed and the available version number in red.
                    Another note is displayed if a package requires a certain version of eXist-db.
                    If this is the case, please make sure you are on the correct version before you attempt
                    to install it.</para>
                <para>Clicking on the install button will update the package, removing the old
                    one.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Browser Caching</title>
                <figure floatstyle="left">
                    <title>Clear your Cache Information </title>
                    <graphic fileref="resources/dashboardUp2dateInfo.png"/>
                </figure>
                <para>Some apps like eXide or the Dashboard rely on JavaScript libraries. After an
                    update, your browser may still use the old libraries,  which may affect the
                    functionality of the app. You should at least reload any open page belonging to
                    those apps. A corresponding warning will be shown during the update. </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Installing an Older Version</title>
                <figure floatstyle="left">
                    <title>Older Versions in Detailed View</title>
                    <graphic fileref="resources/dashboardSelectVersion.png"/>
                </figure>
                <para>Sometimes you may want to go back to an older version of a package. To see all
                    available versions, switch to the detail view, using the
                        <guibutton>show details</guibutton> button. However, older versions will
                    only be displayed for packages which are not installed, so you have to
                    remove the corresponding package first.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Uploading Your Own Packages</title>
                <figure floatstyle="left">
                    <title>Upload Your Own Application to eXist-db</title>
                    <graphic fileref="resources/dashboardLoadOwnApps.png"/>
                </figure>
                <para>Instead of installing from the public repository, you can also upload a
                    package to the server from your local disk. The package has to be in
                        <filename>.xar</filename> format.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Further Information for Developers</title>
            <para>[To be completed...]</para>
            <para>Plugins are loaded and unloaded on demand via dojo's AMD loader. They are modular,
                self-contained units. To add a new plugin, you need to provide an HTML and a
                    <filename>.js</filename> file, which defines a subclass of the base plugin
                class. The source code for the dashboard is available on <ulink url="http://github.com/eXist-db/dashboard">GitHub</ulink>.</para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>