<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
        <productname>eXist-db – Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>Dashboard</title>
        <date>September 2012</date>
    </bookinfo>
    <chapter>
        <title>Dashboard</title>
        <section>
            <title>About the Dashboard</title>
            <para>The eXist-db Dashboard is the central application launchpad and administration
                facility for eXist-db. Much like a tablet or smartphone home screen, the Dashboard
                displays a list of applications, or "apps". In the Dashboard</para>
            <para>The default apps installed in eXist-db relate to administration and assist with
                application development. The database administration apps include: Admin Web
                Application, Collections, Shutdown, Backup, Package Manager, and User Manager. The
                application development applications include: eXide XQuery IDE.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Using the Dashboard</title>
            <para>To enter an app, select its icon.</para>
            <para>To find new apps to install, select the Package Manager app and browse the list of
                applications and code library packages available from eXist-db's public repository.
                This repository is eXist-db's equivalent of an "app store". Detailed information
                about each package can be viewed by selecting the <guibutton>Show
                    Details</guibutton> checkbox in the upper-right corner. If you want to connect
                to a different repository, select the <guibutton>gear</guibutton> button and enter
                the repository's URL.</para>
            <para>To install an app from the repository, select the app; this will reveal a
                gear-shaped <guibutton>install</guibutton> button. You can also install packages
                stored on your filesystem; just select the <guibutton>gear</guibutton> icon in the
                top-left corner of the main Package Manage pane to bring up the Upload dialog, then
                click on the "Click to select .xar package" to browse your filesystem to find the
                .xar package, then select "Submit" to upload the package to eXist-db for
                installation. Once installed, a new app will appear in the Dashboard landing
                page.</para>
            <para>Deleting an unwanted application is as simple as hovering the mouse over an app's
                icon, which reveals a trashcan icon; click on the trashcan icon to delete the app.
                Alternatively, from the Package Manager app, select an installed app and click on
                the orange-tinted <guibutton>gear</guibutton> button.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>On Apps vs. Plugins</title>
            <para>The Dashboard supports both "apps", which are self-contained applications
                providing their own web GUI, as well as "plugins": simple, single-screen dialogs
                which run inside the dashboard. The eXist-db Documentation App, eXide, and eXist-db
                Demo App are apps, while the Collection Browser, Shutdown, Backup, Package Manager,
                and User Manager are plugins. Plugins are most suitable for administrative
                functions.</para>
            <para>Plugins are loaded and unloaded on demand via dojo's AMD loader. They are modular,
                self-contained units. To add a new plugin, you need to provide an HTML and a
                plugin.js file, which defines a subclass of the base plugin class.</para>
            <para>Future plans for plugins include the addition of a template plugin to help others
                understand how to set up a plugin, and XForms support, which would make plugin
                authoring a lot easier but requires an update to betterform.</para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
