<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ --><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="file:/Applications/oxygen/frameworks/docbook/css/docbook.css"?>
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <productname>eXist-db – Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>Configuring Database Indexes</title>
        <date>November 2009</date>
        <orgname>The eXist-db Project</orgname>
    </bookinfo>
    <chapter>
        <title>Configuring Database Indexes</title>
        <section>
            <title>Overview</title>
            <para>In this section, we discuss the types of database indexes used by eXist-db, as well
                as how they are created, configured and maintained. It assumes readers have a basic
                understanding of XML and XQuery.</para>
            <para>Database indexes are used extensively by eXist-db to facilitate efficient querying of
                the database. This is accomplished both by system-generated and user-configured
                database indexes. The current (3.0) version of eXist-db by default includes the following
                types of indexes:</para>
            <note>
                <para>Properly configured indexes have a huge impact on database performance! Some
                    expressions might run a hundred times faster with an index. This is particular
                    applies to the range index: without a range index, eXist has to do a full scan
                    over the context nodes to look up an element value, which severly limits 
                    performance and scalability.</para>
            </note>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>
                            <ulink url="newrangeindex.xml">New Range Indexes</ulink>
                        </emphasis>: A rewritten range index which provides superior performance on
                        large data sets.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>
                            <ulink url="lucene.xml">Full Text Indexes</ulink>
                        </emphasis>: This full text indexing module features faster and
                        customizable full text indexing by transparently integrating Lucene into the
                        XQuery engine. Prefer this index over the Legacy Full Text Index.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>
                            <ulink url="oldrangeindex.xml">Legacy Range Indexes</ulink>
                        </emphasis>: These map specific text nodes and attributes of the documents
                        in a collection to typed values.</para>
                </listitem>
                <!--<listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>
                            <ulink url="ftlegacy.xml">Legacy Full Text Indexes</ulink>
                        </emphasis>: These map specific text nodes and attributes of the documents in
                        a collection to text tokens.</para>
                </listitem>-->
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>
                            <ulink url="ngram.xml">NGram Indexes</ulink>
                        </emphasis>: These map specific text nodes and attributes of the documents
                        in a collection to splitted tokens of n-characters (where n = 3 by default).
			This is very efficient for exact substring searches and for queries on scripts
                        (mostly non-European ones) which can not be easily split into whitespace
                  separated tokens and are thus a bad match for the Lucene full text index. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>
                            <ulink url="devguide_indexes.xml#spatial">Spatial Indexes</ulink>
                            (Experimental)</emphasis>: A working proof-of-concept index, which listens for spatial geometries
                        described through the Geography Markup Language (GML). A detailed description of
                        the implementation can be found in the <ulink url="devguide_indexes.xml#spatial">Developer's Guide to Modularized Indexes</ulink>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>
                            xml:id Index
                        </emphasis>: An index of all xml:id attribute values is automatically created. 
                    These values can be queried by fn:id(). </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>
                            <ulink url="#structuralidx">Structural Indexes</ulink>
                        </emphasis>: This index keeps track of the elements, attributes, and the nodal structure
                        of all XML documents in a collection. It is created and maintained automatically. No configuration required.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
      <!--<note>
                <para>Currently, comments and processing instruction nodes are not indexed. Whether
                    they should be or not, and how some processing instructions could "hint" the
                    indexing process is still being considered.</para>
      </note>-->
            <para>eXist-db features a modularized indexing architecture. Most
                types of indexes have been moved out of the database core and are now maintained as
                pluggable extensions. The full text, the ngram, the spatial and the new range indexes 
                fall under this category. </para>
        </section>
        <section id="idxconf">
            <title>Configuring Indexes</title>
            <para>eXist-db has no "create index" command. Instead, indexes are configured in
                collection-specific configuration files. These files are stored as standard XML
                documents in the system collection: <filename>/db/system/config</filename>, which
                can be accessed like any other document (e.g. using the Admin interface or Java
                Client). In addition to defining settings for indexing collections, the
                configuration document specifies other collection-specific settings such as triggers
                or default permissions.</para>
            <para>The contents of the system collection (<filename>/db/system/config</filename>)
                should mirror the hierarchical structure of the main collection. Configurations are shared
                by descendants in the hierarchy unless they have their own configuration (i.e. the
                configuration settings for the child collection override those set for the parent).
                If no collection-specific configuration file is created for any document, the global
                settings in the main configuration file, <filename>conf.xml</filename>, will apply
                by default. That being said, the <filename>conf.xml</filename> file should only
                define the default global <emphasis>index creation policy</emphasis>.</para>
            <para> To configure a given collection - e.g. <filename>/db/foo</filename> - create a
                file <filename>collection.xconf</filename> and store it as <filename>/db/system/config/db/foo/collection.xconf</filename>. Note the replication of
                the <filename>/db/foo</filename> hierarchy inside <filename>/db/system/config/</filename>. Sub-collections which do not have a <filename>collection.xconf</filename> file of their own will be governed by the
                configuration policy specified for the closest ancestor collection which does have
                such a file, so you are not required to specify a configuration for every
                collection. Note, however, that configuration settings do not cascade, that is to say that a sub-collection
                with a <filename>collection.xconf</filename>, will not inherit any settings from any ancestor collection
                that has a <filename>collection.xconf</filename>; If you choose
                to deploy a <filename>collection.xconf</filename> file in a sub-collection, you must
                specify in that file <emphasis>all</emphasis> the configuration options you wish to
                have applied to that sub-collection (and any lower-level sub-collections without
                    <filename>collection.xconf</filename> files of their own). </para>
            <section>
                <title>Maintaining Indexes and Re-indexing</title>
                <table>
                    <title/>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td>
                                    <para>The eXist-db index system automatically maintains and updates
                                        indexes defined by the user. You therefore do not need to
                                        update an index when you update a database document or
                                        collection. eXist-db will even update indexes following partial
                                        document updates via <emphasis>XUpdate</emphasis> or
                                            <emphasis>XQuery Update</emphasis> expressions.</para>
                                    <para>The only exception to eXist-db's automatic update occurs when
                                        you <emphasis>add a new index definition to an existing
                                            database collection</emphasis>. In this case, the new
                                        index settings will <emphasis>only</emphasis> apply to new
                                        data added to this collection, or any of its
                                        sub-collections, and <emphasis>not</emphasis> to previously
                                        existing data. To apply the new settings to the entire
                                        collection, you need to trigger a "manual reindex" of the
                                        collection being updated. You can re-index collections using
                                        the Java Admin Client (shown on the right). From the Admin
                                        menu, select File»Reindex Collection.
                                    </para>
                                    <para>You can also index by passing an XQuery to eXist-db:</para>
                                    <synopsis language="xquery">xmldb:reindex('/db/foo')</synopsis>
                                </td>
                                <td>
                                    <screenshot>
                                        <graphic fileref="resources/client4.png"/>
                                    </screenshot>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>General Configuration Structure and Syntax</title>
                <para>Index configuration files are standard XML documents that have their elements
                    and attributes defined by the eXist-db namespace:</para>
                <synopsis>http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0</synopsis>
                <para>The following example shows a configuration example:</para>
                <example>
                    <title>Configuration Document</title>
                    <programlisting>
                        <markup>
&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
    &lt;index&gt;
        &lt;!-- Full text index based on Lucene --&gt;
        &lt;lucene&gt;
            &lt;text qname="SPEECH"&gt;
                &lt;ignore qname="SPEAKER"/&gt;
            &lt;/text&gt;
            &lt;text qname="TITLE"/&gt;
        &lt;/lucene&gt;
        
        &lt;!-- Range indexes --&gt;
        &lt;range&gt;
            &lt;create qname="title" type="xs:string"/&gt;
            &lt;create qname="author" type="xs:string"/&gt;
            &lt;create qname="year" type="xs:integer"/&gt;
        &lt;/range&gt;

        &lt;!-- N-gram indexes --&gt;
        &lt;ngram qname="author"/&gt;
        &lt;ngram qname="title"/&gt;
    &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;
</markup>
                    </programlisting>
                </example>
                <para>All configuration documents documents have an <sgmltag>index</sgmltag>
                    element directly below the root element, which encloses the index configuration.
                    Only <emphasis>one</emphasis>
                    <sgmltag>index</sgmltag> element is permitted in a document. Apart from the
                    index configuration, the document may also contain settings not related to indexing,
                    e.g. for triggers; these will not be covered here. </para>
                <para>In the <sgmltag>index</sgmltag> element are elements that define the various
                    index types. Each index type can add its own configuration elements, which are
                    directly forwarded to the corresponding index implementation. The example above
                    configures three different types of indexes: full text, range and ngram.</para>
                <section>
                    <title>Namespaces</title>
                    <para>If the document to be indexed uses namespaces, you should add a
                            <option>xmlns</option> declaration for each of the required namespaces to
                        the <sgmltag>index</sgmltag> element:</para>
                    <example>
                        <title>Using Namespaces</title>
                        <programlisting>
                            <markup>
&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
    &lt;index xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"&gt;
        &lt;fulltext default="none" attributes="no"&gt;
            &lt;create qname="atom:title"/&gt;
        &lt;/fulltext&gt;
        &lt;range&gt;
            &lt;create qname="atom:id" type="xs:string"/&gt;
        &lt;/range&gt;
    &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;
</markup>
                        </programlisting>
                    </example>
                    <para>The example configuration above creates two indexes on a collection of
                        atom documents. The two elements which should be indexed are both in the
                            <literal>atom</literal> namespace and we thus need to declare a mapping
                        for this namespace. Please note that the <option>xmlns</option> namespace
                        declarations have to be specified on the <sgmltag>index</sgmltag> element, not
                        the <sgmltag>create</sgmltag> or <sgmltag>fulltext</sgmltag>
                        elements.</para>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Check Index Usage</title>
            <para>The quickest way to see if an index was used or not is to go to the 
                <guimenuitem>Profiling</guimenuitem> menu item in the <ulink url="{monex}">Monex Monitoring and Profiling application</ulink>.</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Click on <guimenuitem>Enable Tracing</guimenuitem> to enable usage statistics.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Run the query you would like to profile. The profiler will collect statistics about
                    any query running on the database instance, no matter how the query is called.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Click <guimenuitem>Refresh</guimenuitem> and switch to the <guimenuitem>Indexes</guimenuitem>
                    tab.</para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
            <figure>
                <title>Query Profiling</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="resources/IndexProfiling.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>The table provides the following information:</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Source</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The query containing the expression. The line/column of the expression is
                        given in brackets. For queries stored in the database, the file name will be shown.
                        Dynamically executed queries are displayed with the name "String".</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Index</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Type of the index used: "range" for the old range index, "new-range" for the new
                        range index, "lucene" for the full text index.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Optimization</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Either "Full", "Basic", or "No index". The meaning of those labels is as follows:</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>"Full": the expression was rewritten by the optimizer to make full use of the index.
                                This is the best you can achieve.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>"Basic": the index was used, but the expression was not rewritten by the optimizer. This is
                                better than "No index" but still several times slower than "Full". Most probably the context of 
                                the expression was too complex to rewrite it.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>"No index": no index defined. Expression is evaluated in "brute force" mode.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Calls</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The number of calls to the expression.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Elapsed time</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The time elapsed for all calls together. The time is measured for the index lookup only.
                        The absolute numbers are not reliable (due to measurement errors), but they show a tendency: if a lookup takes 
                        relatively longer than other expressions, it might be worth to optimize it with an index.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
        <section id="moduleconf">
            <title>Enabling Index Modules</title>
            <para>While some indexes (n-gram, full text) are already pre-build in the standard
                eXist-db distribution, other modules may need to be enabled first. For example, the
                spatial index depends on a bunch of external libraries, which do not ship with
                eXist-db. However, enabling the spatial index is a simple process:</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Copy the properties file <filename>extensions/indexes/build.properties</filename> and store it as
                        <filename>local.build.properties</filename> in the same directory if it does not already exist.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Edit <filename>extensions/indexes/local.build.properties</filename>:</para>
                    <example>
                        <title>local.build.properties</title>
                        <programlisting>
# N-gram module
include.index.ngram = true

# Spatial module
include.index.spatial = false
                        </programlisting>
                    </example>
                    <para>To include an index, change the corresponding property to "true".</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Call the Ant build system once to regenerate the eXist-db libraries:</para>
                    <synopsis>build.sh</synopsis>
                    <para>or</para>
                    <synopsis>build.bat</synopsis>
                </step>
            </procedure>
            <para>The build process should create a jar file for every index implementation in
                directory <filename>lib/extensions</filename>. For example, the spatial index is
                packaged into the jar <filename>exist-spatial-module.jar</filename>.</para>
            <para>Once the index module has been built, it can be announced to eXist-db. To activate an
                index plugin, it needs to be added to the <sgmltag>modules</sgmltag> section within
                the global configuration file <filename>conf.xml</filename>:</para>
            <example>
                <title>Index Plugin Configuration in conf.xml</title>
                <programlisting>
                    <markup>&lt;modules&gt;
    &lt;module id="ngram-index" class="org.exist.indexing.ngram.NGramIndex"
        file="ngram.dbx" n="3"/&gt;
    &lt;!-- The full text index is always required and should
         not be disabled. We still have some dependencies on
         this index in the database core. These will be removed
         once the redesign has been completed. --&gt;
    &lt;module id="ft-legacy-index" class="org.exist.fulltext.FTIndex"/&gt;
&lt;/modules&gt;</markup>
                </programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>Every <sgmltag>module</sgmltag> element needs at least an <option>id</option> and
                <option>class</option> attribute. The class attribute contains the name of the
                plugin class, which has to be an implementation of
                <classname>org.exist.indexing.Index</classname>.</para>
            <para>All other attributes or nested configuration elements below the
                <sgmltag>module</sgmltag> element are specific to the implementation and will
                differ between indexes. They should be documented by the index implementor.</para>
            <para>If an index implementation cannot be loaded from the specified class, the entry
                will simply be ignored. A warning will be written to the logs which should provide
                more information on the issue which caused the configuration to fail.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Automatic Indexes</title>
            <section id="structuralidx">
                <title>Structural index</title>
                <para>This index keeps track of the elements (tags), attributes, and nodal structure
                    for all XML documents in a collection. It is created and maintained
                    automatically in eXist-db, and can neither be reconfigured nor disabled by the
                    user. The structural index is required for nearly all XPath and XQuery
                    expressions in eXist-db (with the exception of wildcard-only expressions such as
                    "<command>//*</command>"). This index is stored in the database file
                    <filename>structure.dbx</filename>. </para>
                <para>Technically, the structural index maps every element and attribute
                    <emphasis>qname</emphasis> (or <emphasis>qualified name</emphasis>) in a
                    document collection to a list of <sgmltag>documentId, nodeId</sgmltag> pairs.
                    This mapping is used by the query engine to resolve queries for a given XPath
                    expression.</para>
                <para>For example, given the following query:</para>
                <synopsis>//book/section</synopsis>
                <para>eXist-db uses two index lookups: the first for the <sgmltag>book</sgmltag> node,
                    and the second for the <sgmltag>section</sgmltag> node. It then computes the
                    <emphasis>structural join</emphasis> between these node sets to determine
                    which <sgmltag>section</sgmltag> elements are in fact children of
                    <sgmltag>book</sgmltag> elements.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
