<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: getting-help.xml 17201 2012-09-28 23:05:30Z joewiz $ -->
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
        <productname>eXist-db – Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>Learning XQuery and eXist-db</title>
        <date>September 2012</date>
    </bookinfo>
    <chapter>
        <title>Learning XQuery and eXist-db</title>
        <para>This article provides tips and resources for newcomers to XQuery and eXist-db.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Key Points to Learning XQuery</title>
            <para>This is a guide to help you learn XQuery.  It contains some brief background on XQuery and
                then list resources you can learn to use XQuery.</para>
            <para>XQuery is unique in the development stack in that it replaces both SQL and the traditional software layers that convert SQL into 
                presentation formats such as HTML, PDF and ePub.  Learning how to select basic data from
                a native XML can be learned in just a few hours if you are already familiar with SQL and other
                functional programming lanaguges.  However learning how to create custom XQuery functions, how to design XQuery modules
                and how to execute unit tests on XQuery takes considerablly longer.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Learning by Example</title>
                <para>Many people learn a new language by reading small examples of code.
                    One of the ideal locations for this is the 
                    <ulink url="http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/XQuery#Beginning_Examples">XQuery Wikibook Beginning Examples</ulink>
                </para>
                <para>These examples are all designed and tested to work with eXist.  Please let us know if
                    there are specific examples you would like to see.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Learning Functional Programming</title>
                <para>XQuery is a functional programming language so many things that you do in procedural programs are not
                    recomended or not possible.  In XQuery all variables should be imuutable, meaning they should be set once
                    but never changed.  This aspect of XQuery allows it to be stateless and side-effect free.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Learning FLOWR statements</title>
                <para>Interation in XQuery uses parallel progamming statements called FLOWR statements.  Each loop of a FLOWR
                    statement is performed in a seperate thread of execution.  As a result you can not use the output of any computation
                    in a FLOWR loop as an input to the next loop.  This concept can be difficult to learn if you have never used parallel progamming
                    systems.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Learning XPath</title>
                <para>XQuery also includes the use of XPath to select various nodes from an XML document.  Note
                    that with native XML databases the shortest XPath expression is often the fastest since
                    short expressions use element indexes.  You may want to use a tool such as an XPath "builder" tool
                    within an IDE such as oXygen to learn how to build XPath expressions.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Using eXide or the XQuery sandbox</title>
                <para>eXist comes with a web-based tool for doing XQuery development.  Although this tool is not as advanced
                    as a full IDE such as oXygen, it is ideal for small queries where and IDE is not accessible.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Learning how to update XML documents</title>
                <para>eXist comes with a set of operations for updating on-disk XML documents.
                    <ulink url="http://exist-db.org/update_ext.xml">eXist XQuery Update Operations</ulink>
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Learning how to debug XQuery</title>
                <para>eXist has some early support for step-by-step debugging of XQuery.  But the interface
                    is not mature yet.  Many people choose to debug complex recursive functions directly within XML IDEs such as oXygen
                    that support step-by-step debugging using the internal Saxon XQuery library.  The oXygen IDE allows you to set
                    breakpoints and watch the output document get created one element at a time.  This process is strongly recomended
                    if you are just learning topics like recursion.
                    <ulink url="http://exist-db.org/exist/debugger.xml">eXist XQuery Debugger</ulink>
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Learning recursion in XQuery</title>
                <para>XML is an inherently recursive data structure: trees contain sub-trees.  So many XQuery
                    functions are best designed using recursion.  Transforming many documents are best done
                    using recursive functions.  One good place to start learning recursion is the identity
                    node filter functions in the XQuery wikibook.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Effective use of your IDE</title>
                <para>Most developers that do XQuery more than a few hours a day eventually end up using a full commercial
                    XQuery IDE with oXygen being the best integrated with eXist.  Setting up oXygen is a bit tricky the first time
                    since you need to load five jar files into a "driver" for oXygen.  Yet once this is done and the default
                    XQuery engine is set up to use oXygen there are many high-productivity features that are enabled.  Central
                    to this is the XQuery auto-complete feature.  As you type within XQuery all eXist functions and their parameters are
                    shown in the IDE.  For example if you type "xmldb:" all the functions of the XMLDB module will automatically appear
                    in a drop-down list.  As you continue to type or select a function the parameters and types are also shown.
                    This becomes a large time saver as you use more XQuery functions.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Learning XQuery Resources</title>
            <para>The following is an annotated list of resources that may help you learn XQuery.</para>
            <bibliography>
                <biblioentry>
                    <title>XQuery 1.0 W3C Specification</title>
                    <biblioid>
                        <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery/" condition="_blank">http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery/</ulink>
                    </biblioid>
                    <bibliomisc>The official 1.0 specification.  You should use XQuery
                        to keep your XQuery programs portable.</bibliomisc>
                </biblioentry>
                <biblioentry>
                    <title>XQuery Wikibook</title>
                    <biblioid>
                        <ulink url="http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/XQuery" condition="_blank">http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/XQuery</ulink>
                    </biblioid>
                    <bibliomisc>A collection of sample progams in XQuery using the eXist system.
                        Note that some examples are not complete and some may not be updated to use
                        the latest release of eXist.</bibliomisc>
                </biblioentry>
                <biblioentry>
                    <title>XQuery Wikibook - Beginning Examples</title>
                    <biblioid>
                        <ulink url="http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/XQuery#Beginning_Examples" condition="_blank">http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/XQuery#Beginning_Examples</ulink>
                    </biblioid>
                    <bibliomisc>A collection of sample progams in XQuery using the eXist system.
                        Note that some examples are not complete and some may not be updated to use
                        the latest release of eXist.</bibliomisc>
                </biblioentry>
                <biblioentry>
                    <title>XQuery Wikipedia Article</title>
                    <biblioid>
                        <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XQuery" condition="_blank">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XQuery</ulink>
                    </biblioid>
                    <bibliomisc>An excellent brief overview of what XQuery is and it main features.
                    </bibliomisc>
                </biblioentry>
                <biblioentry>
                    <title>XQuery Book by Priscilla Walmsley</title>
                    <biblioid>
                        <ulink url="http://www.datypic.com/books/xquery/" condition="_blank">http://www.datypic.com/books/xquery/</ulink>
                    </biblioid>
                    <bibliomisc>A precise and thurough coverage of all the features of the XQuery
                        language. An excellent and well written reference book for all XQuery
                        developers. This book is frequently cited in other XQuery
                        tutorials.</bibliomisc>
                </biblioentry>
                <biblioentry>
                    <title>XQuery Tutorial at the commercial W3C schools site</title>
                    <biblioid>
                        <ulink url="http://www.w3schools.com/xquery" condition="_blank">http://www.w3schools.com/xquery</ulink>
                    </biblioid>
                    <bibliomisc>Basic XQuery tutorial but not recommended for eXist specific items.
                        Disucssion of XLink and XPointer should not be used.</bibliomisc>
                </biblioentry>
            </bibliography>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>