<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
        <productname>eXist-db – Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>Older Versions</title>
        <date>September 2012</date>
    </bookinfo>
    <chapter>
        <title>Older Versions</title>
        <section id="v1.4-installation">
            <title>eXist-1.4.x: Installation Notes</title>
            <para>eXist 1.4.x requires the Java 1.6 JDK from Oracle for installation; the Java JRE
                does not suffice, nor do versions earlier than 1.6. See Oracle's <ulink
                    url="http://www.java.com/en/download/help/index_installing.xml">Installing
                    java</ulink> page for instructions on installing the Java 1.6 JDK.</para>
            <para>The Mac and Linux versions of eXist 1.4.x lack the menubar/toolbar icons for
                starting, shutting down, and restarting eXist.</para>
            <!-- TODO poll the devs for other differences -->
        </section>
        <section id="v1.4-repository">
            <title>eXist 1.4.x: Installing Sample Applications using the Admin Webpage</title>
            <para>eXist version 2.0.x comes with an application repository, which allows users to
                download and deploy eXist-db based applications with a single mouse click. Most of
                the examples can be installed from the application repository. If you are using
                eXist 2.0, continue with the section describing <ulink url="app-repository.xml"
                    >installation via the repository</ulink>.</para>
            <para>On eXist 1.4.x, the repository was not yet available, so you have to use the admin
                web application to download and install data.</para>
            <para>To begin using the database system, you must first create document collections and
                import files into eXist. To help you in learning these and other basic database
                operations, a number of simple XQuery web applications have been included with the
                eXist distribution. These applications are designed to allow users to experiment and
                query sample XML documents using the eXist database system. </para>
            <informaltable>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <para>To start using these sample applications, you must log in to
                                    the eXist database administration page. To log in, go to the
                                        <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/exist/admin/admin.xql"
                                        >Administration » Admin</ulink> link located on the sidebar
                                    menu on the <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/exist/">local
                                        eXist homepage</ulink>.</para>
                                <para>You should now see the login screen as shown on the
                                    right.</para>
                                <para>Enter the username "admin" and the password you set during
                                    installation (or which you have set by other means). </para>
                            </td>
                            <td>
                                <screenshot>
                                    <graphic fileref="resources/admin1.png"/>
                                </screenshot>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <para>Once you have logged in, select Examples Setup from the menu
                                    on the left. Most of the example data is shipped with eXist, but
                                    some files need to be downloaded. Check the "The XML Acronym
                                    Demystifier" and "The Mondial Database (Europe)" in order to
                                    download these files. Click on the "Import Files" button to
                                    import the example data into eXist.</para>
                                <para>After you have imported the files, you can access the
                                    collections they are imported into by clicking on "Browse
                                    Collections". Here you can upload and delete individual files,
                                    as well as view the contents of them.</para>
                            </td>
                            <td>
                                <screenshot>
                                    <graphic fileref="resources/admin2.png"/>
                                </screenshot>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <para>After the example data has been imported, you can go back to
                                    the <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/exist/">Home</ulink> page
                                    and you will now be able to query the imported files through a
                                    number of small web applications listed in <ulink
                                        url="http://localhost:8080/exist/examples.xml">All
                                        Examples</ulink> in the "Examples" tab.</para>
                                <!--"All Examples" should be moved up to the top in the Examples tab. "Bibliographic" should read "Bibliography". Jens Petersen-->
                                <para>The simplest of these applications is the <ulink
                                        url="http://localhost:8080/exist/sandbox/">XQuery
                                        Sandbox</ulink> shown on the right which allows users to
                                    submit queries to the XML files imported into the database. The
                                    XQuery Sandbox provides the easiest way to start experimenting
                                    with eXist and XQuery.</para>
                                <para>A number of sample queries are furnished through the dropdown
                                    menu. After modifying the queries, you can store them in the
                                    slots on the left. Click on an empty slot to store the query in
                                    the main query field. If you click on a slot with a stored
                                    query, the contents of the stored query and the main query field
                                    will be swapped.
                                    <!-- Users have complained that they do not understand this mechanism. Perhaps it would be an idea to have separate store and display buttons. Jens Petersen -->
                                </para>
                            </td>
                            <td>
                                <screenshot>
                                    <graphic fileref="resources/sandbox.png"/>
                                </screenshot>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
