<!-- $Id$ -->
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
        <productname>eXist-db – Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>Quick Start</title>
        <date>September 2012</date>
    </bookinfo>
    <chapter>
        <title>Quick Start</title>
        <section id="overview">
            <title>Overview</title>
            <para>Installing eXist-db on your computer is quick and easy. Once you confirm that your
                system meets the requirements, download the installer, follow the installation
                instructions, and before long you'll be up and running with eXist-db.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="system-requirements">
            <title>System Requirements</title>
            <para>eXist-db is compatible with all recent versions of Linux, Mac OS X, and Windows.
                Out of the box, eXist-db uses 512 MB of RAM and about 200 MB of disk space.
                Administrative privileges are not required to install or run eXist-db, but certain
                installation procedures are not possible without administrative privileges. The
                critical requirement is that Java be installed.</para>
            <note id="about-java">
                <title>eXist-db and Java</title>
                <para>eXist-db is built on Java, a free, cross-platform software development
                    environment. Java comes in a number of versions, so it is important that you
                    install the version that eXist-db requires: Java 6, released by Oracle. Other
                    versions, including Java 7 and OpenJDK have not been tested, so they are not yet
                    supported. eXist-db can run with both the Java "JRE" (Java Runtime Environment)
                    and the "JDK" (Java Development Kit)—as long as you use version 6. The JRE is
                    adequate for running eXist-db; you do not need the JDK unless you intend to
                    compile eXist-db from its source code. For instructions about running Java on
                    your operating system, see Oracle's <ulink
                        url="http://www.java.com/en/download/help/index_installing.xml">Installing
                        Java</ulink> page.</para>
                <para>Linux users: Installing the Oracle JDK is probably the most difficult part of
                    installing eXist on Linux. Unfortunately, Oracle's own pages (such as the link
                    above) focus on commercial Linux distributions. Users of other distributions are
                    better served by distribution-specific instructions. Instructions that
                    eXist-db users have found useful include: <ulink
                        url="http://livingtao.blogspot.com/2012/01/few-easy-steps-to-install-sunoracle-jdk.html"
                        >Amazon Linux</ulink> and <ulink
                        url="http://www.gaggl.com/2012/04/installing-java6-jdk-on-ubuntu-12-04/"
                        >Ubuntu 12.04</ulink>.</para>
            </note>
        </section>
        <section id="installation">
            <title>Installing eXist-db</title>
            <para>Download the installer for the latest stable release of eXist-db from the <ulink
                url="download.xml">Downloads</ulink> page. The installer is a single file called
                <filename>eXist-setup-[version]-revXXXXX.jar</filename>. Here, [version] and
                XXXXX reflect the version and revision numbers of eXist-db, and .jar is a Java
                Archive file. We recommend that you download the <emphasis>latest stable
                    release</emphasis>.</para>
            <note id="versions">
                <title>Versions of eXist-db</title>
                <para>eXist-db has advanced rapidly in recent years, so for the best experience and
                    performance we recommend you use the most recent stable version. These
                    instructions assume you are doing so, so if you are using an older version of
                    eXist-db, see our article on <ulink url="older-versions.xml">Older
                        Versions</ulink>; if you need to run the latest, "bleeding-edge" development
                    version of eXist-db, see <ulink url="running-trunk.xml">Running
                        Trunk</ulink>.</para>
            </note>
            <para>Once the download has completed, launch the eXist-db installer. To launch the
                installer on Mac or Windows, simply double-click the .jar you downloaded file. (On
                Mac OS X 10.7 and higher, a security feature called <ulink
                    url="http://support.apple.com/kb/HT5290">Gatekeeper</ulink> may prevent the
                installer from running since eXist-db is not registered with Apple; to circumvent
                the warning dialog and allow the installer to run, right-click or control-click the
                file and select Open.) On Linux distributions with a graphical desktop interface
                (e.g., Ubuntu), you can launch the installer by making the .jar file executable,
                right-clicking on the .jar file, and selecting "Open With Sun Java 6 Runtime". Or,
                to launch the installer from the command line, enter the following command:
                <synopsis format="linespecific">java -jar eXist-setup-[version]-revXXXXX.jar</synopsis>
                (Windows and Mac users can also use the command line procedure, but most users
                prefer the graphical installer.)</para>
            <para>After the installer is launched, follow the prompts described below to complete
                the installation. We recommend that you accept the default options, since these are
                designed to make using eXist-db easy. The installer's dialog panes are as follows: <procedure>
                    <step>
                        <para>(Windows only) <emphasis>Select the Path to Java</emphasis>: You will
                            be asked to select where Java is located on your computer. Browse to
                            C:\Program Files\Java, and then select your most up to date version of
                            Java (typically, "jre6" or "jdk1.6.0_xx"). Click Next.</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>
                            <emphasis>Choose the Installation Directory</emphasis>: You will be
                            asked where to install eXist-db on your hard disk. The installer will
                            suggest an appropriate directory, but if you want, you can install
                            eXist-db anywhere on your system.</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>
                            <emphasis>Choose the Data Directory</emphasis>: The data directory is
                            where eXist-db keeps its data files. The installer will suggest keeping
                            the data files inside the application directory, but you can select a
                            different location if you want.</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>
                            <emphasis>Choose the Admin Password</emphasis>: The Admin Password is a
                            password for the eXist-db administrator account, or more commonly, the
                            "admin" account. This admin account belongs to you, and certain key
                            functions in eXist-db can only be performed by the admin. While you can
                            leave the admin password blank, we strongly recommend setting the
                            password in order to secure access your installation of eXist-db. Why?
                            Keep in mind that while eXist-db is running, it can be accessed by other
                            users on your local network (be it in your home or office, or at a cafe
                            or on a train). So, securing your administrator's account on eXist-db is
                            a good way to protect your data and prevent others from abusing the
                            account. Best to choose a unique password.</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>
                            <emphasis>Select the Packs To Install</emphasis>: The "core" package is
                            required to run eXist-db, and the "sources" and "javadoc" packages are
                            optional. Removing "sources" and "javadoc" cuts the installation size in
                            half, but best to install everything unless you are starved for disk
                            space.</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>(Windows and Linux only) <emphasis>Start Menu and/or Desktop Shortcut
                            Options</emphasis>: The installer can create convenient desktop
                            shortcuts and Start Menu entries for starting and accessing
                            eXist-db.</para>
                    </step>
                </procedure>
            </para>
            <para>When the installer is finished installing eXist-db, click Quit to close it.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="launching">
            <title>Launching eXist-db</title>
            <para>On the Mac, double-click eXist-db's application icon where you installed eXist-db.
                On Linux or Windows, select the <emphasis>eXist-db Database Startup</emphasis>
                desktop shortcut icon or Start Menu entry you created at the end of the
                installation.</para>
            <para>Once eXist is started, you will see a new menu bar icon (Mac) or task bar icon
                (Linux/Windows) for eXist-db. This icon gives you access eXist-db's tools and lets
                you shutdown or restart the database.</para>
            <para>You can also start eXist-db manually if you feel comfortable with the command
                line:</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>Open your terminal or command prompt.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Change (cd) to the directory where you installed eXist-db (e.g.,
                        "<filename>/usr/local/lib/exist/</filename>" for Linux,
                        "<filename>/Applications/eXist/</filename>" for Mac, or
                        "<filename>C:\Program Files\eXist</filename>" for Windows).</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>On Linux or Mac, enter the following:</para>
                    <synopsis format="linespecific">bin/startup.sh</synopsis>
                    <para>If you are a Windows user, enter the following:</para>
                    <synopsis format="linespecific">bin\startup.bat</synopsis>
                </step>
            </procedure>
            <note>
                <title>Having trouble?</title>
                <para>If you suspect you have had a problem launching eXist-db, see our article on
                    <ulink url="troubleshooting.xml">Troubleshooting</ulink>.</para>
            </note>
        </section>
        <section id="diving-in">
            <title>Diving In</title>
            <para>Let's test to see the server is running, enter the following URL in a web browser:
                <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/exist/">http://localhost:8080/exist/</ulink>
            </para>
            <para>You should now see the following web page:</para>
            <screenshot>
                <graphic fileref="resources/index1.png"/>
            </screenshot>
            <para>See it? Congratulations! (Not seeing it? See our article on <ulink
                url="troubleshooting.xml">Troubleshooting</ulink>.)</para>
            <para>Do you notice the similarity between the page and the homepage of exist-db.org?
                You are actually now running a complete, local copy of the eXist-db.org website on
                your computer.</para>
            <para>Now that you have successfully installed eXist-db, you are ready to dive in. Your
                local copy includes everything you need to do so: the eXist-db <ulink
                    url="/exist/apps/dashboard">Dashboard</ulink> app, which lets you add
                application packages from eXist-db.org's public repository (including all of
                eXist-db's documentation), upload your own data to the database, and perform
                administrative tasks (like creating user accounts). It also includes the <ulink
                    url="/exist/apps/eXide">eXide</ulink> web application for querying the database
                and creating your own applications.</para>
            <para>To learn more about the Dashboard app and installing applications from the
                eXist-db public application repository, see the article on the <ulink
                    url="dashboard.xml">Dashboard</ulink>. To learn more about the eXide app, see
                the article on <ulink url="exide.xml">eXide</ulink>.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="shutting-down">
            <title>Shutting Down the Database</title>
            <para>Improperly shutting down the database can corrupt your data files, so follow one
                of these procedures to properly shut down eXist-db.</para>
            <procedure>
                <step>
                    <para>From the <ulink url="/exist/apps/dashboard">Dashboard App</ulink>: select
                        the Shutdown button</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>From the command line, run the <filename>bin/shutdown.sh</filename>
                        (Linux/Mac) or <filename>shutdown.bat</filename> (DOS/Windows) shutdown
                        scripts, using your admin account's username and password.</para>
                    <synopsis>bin/shutdown.sh -u admin -p youradminpassword</synopsis>
                    <synopsis>bin/shutdown.bat -u admin -p youradminpassword</synopsis>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>From the command line, run the java command, using your admin account's
                        password:</para>
                    <synopsis>java -jar start.jar shutdown -u admin -p youradminpassword</synopsis>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>From the <ulink url="client.xml">Java Admin Client</ulink>: select
                        Connection » Shutdown from the menu.</para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
