<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <productname>eXist-db – Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>HTML Templating Module</title>
        <date>June 2012</date>
        <author>
            <firstname>Wolfgang</firstname>
            <surname>Meier</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address format="linespecific">
                    <email>wolfgang at exist-db.org</email>
                </address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </bookinfo>
    <chapter>
        <title>HTML Templating Module</title>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para>The HTML templating module is used by many of the apps which currently ship with
                eXist-db. It has been designed with one goal in mind: separation of concerns. Following
                the Model-View-Controller (MVC) concept, the view should be cleanly separated from
                the application logic which operates on the model (the data being processed). The
                templating module implements this in a strict sense: the view is plain, valid HTML5
                and does not include any application code. All the application logic should go into
                separate XQuery modules and will be called automagically by the templating
                framework.</para>
            <para>The templating module scans the HTML view for elements with class attributes
                following a simple convention and tries to translate them into XQuery function
                calls. We'll see below how the templating framework tries to map template names into
                functions. In the simplest case, a class attribute which triggers a function call
                just contains the name of a function in an XQuery library known to the system. The templating
                module splits the class attribute contents into whitespace-separated components, then
                checks if any of them matches the namespace prefix and local name of a function in
                a known module. For
                example, in the <filename>.html</filename> file, there might be a div:</para>
            <synopsis language="html">&lt;div class="demo:hello"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</synopsis>
            <para>
                <code>demo:hello</code> matches a function in module <filename>demo.xql</filename>
                which is known to the system:</para>
            <synopsis language="xquery"><![CDATA[
declare function demo:hello($node as node()*, $model as map(*)) as element(span) {
    <span>Hello World!</span>
};]]></synopsis>
            <para>Very often, you will also need to pass some (static) parameters to the template.
                This is done by appending a query string to the template call:</para>
            <synopsis language="html">&lt;div class="demo:multiply?n1=5&amp;n2=8"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</synopsis>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Pre-defined Template Commands</title>
            <para>The templating module already defines a number of general-purpose template
                commands.</para>
            <section>
                <title>templates:include</title>
                <synopsis>templates:include?path=path-to-xml-resource</synopsis>
                <para>Includes the content of the resource given by path into the current element.
                    The path is always interpreted relative to the current application directory or
                    collection.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>templates:if-parameter-set</title>
                <synopsis>templates:if-parameter-set?param=request-parameter</synopsis>
                <para>Conditionally includes its content only if the given request parameter is set
                    and is not empty.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>templates:if-parameter-unset</title>
                <synopsis>templates:if-parameter-unset?param=request-parameter</synopsis>
                <para>Conditionally includes its content only if the given request parameter is not
                    set or is empty.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>templates:surround</title>
                <synopsis>templates:surround?with=xml-resource&amp;at=id&amp;using=id</synopsis>
                <para>Surrounds its content with the contents of the XML resource specified in
                    "with". The "at" parameter determines where the content is inserted into the
                    surrounding XML. It should match an existing HTML id in the template.</para>
                <para>The "using" parameter is optional and specifies the id of an element in the
                    "with" resource. The current content will be surrounded by this element. If the
                    parameter is missing, the entire document given in "with" will be used.</para>
                <para>The surround template instruction is used by all pages of this demo
                    application. The header, basic page structure and menus are the same for all
                    pages. Each page thus only contains a simple div with a template
                    instruction:</para>
                <synopsis>templates:surround?with=templates/page.html&amp;at=content</synopsis>
                <para>The instruction takes the content of the current element and injects it into
                    the template page.</para>
                <section>
                    <title>templates:form-control</title>
                    <synopsis>templates:form-control</synopsis>
                    <para>Use on &lt;input&gt; and &lt;select&gt; elements: checks the HTTP request
                        for a parameter matching the name of the form control and fills it into the
                        value of an input or selects the corresponding option of a select.</para>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>templates:display-source</title>
                    <synopsis>templates:display-source?lang=language</synopsis>
                    <para>Display the contents of the element as a code block with syntax
                        highlighting. This also adds a button which copies the code into eXide if
                        clicked.</para>
                </section>
                <section>
                    <title>templates:load-source</title>
                    <synopsis>templates:load-source</synopsis>
                    <para>Normally used with an &lt;a&gt; element: opens the document referenced in
                        the href attribute in eXide.</para>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Writing Template Functions</title>
            <para>The templating system is based on conventions: an XQuery function which should be
                called via the templating system needs to accept at least two default
                parameters:</para>
            <synopsis language="xquery">demo:hello($node as node(), $model as map(*))</synopsis>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>$node</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>the node which contained the class attribute which triggered the
                            templating call.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>$model</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>is used to pass arbitrary information between template functions. See
                            the section on "nesting templates" below. The model also contains
                            general configuration for the templating contained in a map item called
                            "configuration".</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <section>
                <title id="inject">Parameter Injection </title>
                <para>In addition to the default parameters, a templating function may take up to
                    (currently) 8 additional parameters. The templating system tries to determine a
                    value for each of the additional parameters as follows:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>if the current HTTP request contains a (non-empty) parameter with the
                            same name as the parameter variable, it is used to set the value of the
                            variable</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>if the static parameters passed to the template call contain a
                            parameter matching the variable name, it will be used</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>if neither 1) nor 2) lead to a non-empty value, the function signature
                            will be checked for an annotation <code>%templates:default("name",
                                "value1", ..., "valueN")</code>. The first parameter of the
                            annotation should match the name of the parameter variable. All other
                            parameters of the annotation are taken as values for the
                            variable.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Type conversion</title>
                <para>When injecting parameters, the templating module tries to convert all values
                    to the type specified for the parameter in the function signature. For example,
                    the function:</para>
                <synopsis language="xquery">declare function demo:multiply($node as node()*, $model as map(*), $n1 as xs:int, $n2 as xs:int)</synopsis>
                <para>defines two optional parameters, $n1 and $n2 with type <code>xs:int</code>.
                    Request and static parameters will always be strings, so the templating module
                    needs to transform them into the desired target type. This works for all atomic
                    types as well as XML elements and text nodes.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Return type</title>
            <para>The return type of the templating function may either be a map or any other
                type:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If it is a map, it will be merged into the current $model. The templating
                        framework then continues processing any descendants of the current node,
                        passing the new model to nested template calls.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Any other result will be inserted into the output document and replaces
                        the current node. Nested templates will not be processed
                        automatically.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Nesting Templates</title>
            <para>Template calls can be nested, but the outer template function needs to make sure
                all descendant XML nodes are passed through the templating system. To do this, just
                call</para>
            <synopsis language="xquery">templates:process($children, $model)</synopsis>
            <para>from within the template function. $children would contain the descendant nodes
                you want to include, $model is a map containing data you want to pass along to
                nested template calls. The model is an important concept here: in a well designed
                application, all the information which is processed by nested templates in a page
                should be contained in the model. It should always extend the map you received as
                parameter into the current function. Since maps are immutable, new items added to
                the map will only be visible to nested templates.</para>
            <para>Instead of calling <code>templates:process</code> directly, the templating
                function may also just return a map (see previous section). This map will
                automatically be merged into the map received in $model. In most cases, it will thus
                be sufficient to just return a new map containing one item. For example, in the
                Shakespeare example (see demo app), there's an outer template call to
                    <code>shakespeare:query</code>, which runs a query on the data. The template
                does not return the query result, but instead just puts it into the model.
                Displaying the results to the user is done by the two nested templates:
                    <code>shakespeare:hit-count</code> and
                <code>shakespeare:show-hits</code>. </para>
            <para>
                Here's the code of <code>shakespeare:query</code>:</para>
            <synopsis language="xquery"><![CDATA[
declare 
    %templates:wrap
function shakes:query($node as node()*, $model as map(*), $query as xs:string?, $mode as xs:string) {
    session:create(),
    let $hits := shakes:do-query($query, $mode)
    let $store := session:set-attribute($shakes:SESSION, $hits)
    return
        map:entry("hits", $hits)
};
    ]]></synopsis>
            <para>As you can see, the function simply a new map with a single item, "hits", containing
            the query results. The templating framework will pass this to any nested templates.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Annotations</title>
            <para>By default, whatever is returned by the current templating function - or any nested
            template call - will replace the currently processed HTML element. In many cases you want
            to preserve the current element and its attributes and just replace its content. This
            can be achieved by specifying the annotation <code>%templates:wrap</code>.</para>
            <para>The annotation does not take any parameters.</para>
            <section>
                <title>%templates:wrap</title>
                <para>By default, whatever is returned by the current templating function - or any nested
                    template call - will replace the currently processed HTML element. In many cases you want
                    to preserve the current element and its attributes and just replace its content. This
                    can be achieved by specifying the annotation <code>%templates:wrap</code>.</para>
                <para>The annotation does not take any parameters.</para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>%templates:default(name, value1, ..., valueN)</title>
                <para>As already discussed in the section on parameter
                        injection, this annotation is used to provide static defaults for any
                    optional parameter whose value cannot be determined by looking at the HTTP
                    request or static parameters.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Calling the Templating Module</title>
            <para>To trigger the templating, just call templates:apply from your main XQuery.
                templates:apply takes 3 parameters:</para>
            <synopsis>templates:apply($content as node()+, $resolver as function(xs:string) as item()?, $model as map(*))</synopsis>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>$content</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The HTML content to be processed</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>$resolver</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A lookup function which will be called to find template
                            functions.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>$model</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The initial model: will be passed on to all called template
                            functions.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>The $resolver function has to be provided by the calling code because the
                templating module cannot access the context of the calling module and thus cannot
                see any of the function modules imported by the main module. The function takes two
                arguments: the name of a function to look up and its arity, i.e.: the number of
                arguments it takes. Normally $resolver will just call function-lookup to resolve the
                function name to a function item and return it (if found), but it is important that
                it catches any errors, e.g. caused by an invalid xs:QName.</para>
            <para>The main XQuery could thus look as simple as this:</para>
            <synopsis language="xquery">
xquery version "3.0";

import module namespace templates="http://exist-db.org/xquery/templates" at "templates.xql";

(: The following modules provide functions which will be called by the templating :)
import module namespace shakespeare="http://exist-db.org/apps/demo/shakespeare" at "../examples/web/shakespeare.xql";
import module namespace config="http://exist-db.org/xquery/apps/config" at "config.xqm";

declare option exist:serialize "method=html5 media-type=text/html";

let $lookup := function($functionName as xs:string, $arity as xs:int) {
    try {
        function-lookup(xs:QName($functionName), $arity)
    } catch * {
        ()
    }
}
let $content := request:get-data()
return
    templates:apply($content, $lookup, ())
</synopsis>
            <para>This main XQuery will usually be called through the <code>controller.xql</code>.
                All that is needed is one controller rule which redirects all requests for HTML
                pages to our main query:</para>
            <synopsis language="xquery"><![CDATA[
else if (ends-with($exist:resource, ".html")) then
    <dispatch xmlns="http://exist.sourceforge.net/NS/exist">
        <view>
            <forward url="{$exist:controller}/modules/view.xql">
                <set-attribute name="$exist:prefix" value="{$exist:prefix}"/>
                <set-attribute name="$exist:controller" value="{$exist:controller}"/>
            </forward>
        </view>
        <error-handler>
            <forward url="{$exist:controller}/error-page.html" method="get"/>
            <forward url="{$exist:controller}/modules/view.xql"/>
        </error-handler>
    </dispatch>
        ]]></synopsis>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Integration with eXide</title>
            <para>eXide automatically integrates the templating framework into a new application if
                "HTML Templates" is selected in the "Application Properties":</para>
            <screenshot>
                <graphic fileref="resources/eXide-screenshot.png"/>
            </screenshot>
            <para>eXide generates a corresponding main XQuery and a controller. The templating will
                work out of the box for all HTML views.</para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
