<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <graphic fileref="logo.jpg"/>
        <productname>eXist-db – Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>XML-Prague 2012 eXist PreMeeting</title>
        <date>October 2012</date>
        <orgname>The eXist-db Project</orgname>
    </bookinfo>
    <chapter>
        <title>XML Prague 2012</title>
        <subtitle>eXist-db pre-conference</subtitle>
        <section>
            <title>Erik Siegel - Software Management</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <videoobject>
                    <videodata fileref="http://www.youtube.com/embed/m-VVM8JM_A0" width="560" depth="315"/>
                </videoobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <para>Real world application software management can be a nightmare: Keep track of your
                versions, deploy applications to other platforms (like the production servers)
                without forgetting anything, administration... Tools like SVN, GIT, ANT and the like
                alleviate some of the problems bit it still isn't easy.</para>
            <para>Now eXist introduced a new challenge: Your software is no longer "files on disk"
                but resides (at least partially) in the database where you can no longer use the
                file based tools like SVN. But you probably still want to do version management...
                Also: Moving your code to another platform means inserting it into the database at
                the other end.</para>
            <para>Now all these tasks are IMHO quite boring. You don't want to do all the necessary
                simple but time consuming steps over and over again. Especially because you can't
                effort any errors in this area (have you ever forgot to include that crucial little
                file on a production release? I did...).</para>
            <para>The solution is: Automate the procedures around version management and
                deployments. But how do you do that in an eXist environment? After fiddling around
                quite a bit I came up with a simple and elegant solution for all this that I would
                like to share with you.</para>
            <para>Biography:</para>
            <para>Erik Siegel works as a self-employed XML specialist. His career has involved many
                jobs—researcher, programmer, systems analyst, project manager, systems architect,
                consultant. During the past five years, XML crept in and it's here to stay! His main
                customers are in publishing, and his XML activities include consulting, training,
                schema development, and programming. You can find more information about Erik and
                his company at http://www.xatapult.com.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>David Fichtmueller - Using eXist To Rescue Research </title>
            <mediaobject>
                <videoobject>
                    <videodata fileref="http://www.youtube.com/embed/pQMyNPvTjzU" width="560" depth="315"/>
                </videoobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <para>David Fichtmueller presents the architecture of the reBiND project (<ulink url="">http://rebind.bgbm.org/</ulink>), which aims to rescue threatened research
                data.</para>
            <para>The original video of the stop motion movie can be found at <ulink url="">http://rebind.bgbm.org/rebind_movie</ulink> or <mediaobject>
                    <videoobject>
                        <videodata fileref="http://www.youtube.com/embed/rh7bM1kfRsE" width="560" depth="315"/>
                    </videoobject>
                </mediaobject>
                .</para>
            <para>The slides of this talk are available at <ulink url="">http://rebind.bgbm.org/files/rebind/2012xmlprague/rebind.html</ulink>
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>