<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <productname>Open Source Native XML Database</productname>
        <title>XQSuite</title>
        <orgname>The eXist Project</orgname>
        <date>October 2012</date>
    </bookinfo>
    <chapter>
        <title>XQSuite - Annotation-based Test Framework for XQuery</title>
        <para>XQSuite is a new test framework for XQuery modules based on
        XQuery function annotations. It has a number of advantages over previous
        approaches:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>tests can be defined within the actual application code (if you like), so a
                    function can be tested right where it is implemented. Because annotations are
                    ignored during normal execution, they do not interfere with the
                    application.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>more complex integration tests can be combined into separate modules using the
                    full power of XQuery. Tests are written as ordinary XQuery functions with all
                    the support provided by XQuery editors like eXide.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>properly written tests are easy to read and understand.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>XQSuite is itself implemented in 100% XQuery and can be extended. To
                    run a suite of tests, all you need is a small, main XQuery which imports the
                    modules to be tested.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para>eXist-db previously used a descriptive XML format to define XQuery tests. XQSuite
            replaces this, though the old format and test runner is still supported and is used by
            many of the tests in <filename>tests/src/xquery</filename>.</para>
            <para>XQSuite has two components:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A number of XQuery function annotations to be used within the code module to be tested</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A test runner which takes a sequence of function items and interprets the test
                    annotations</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>To use test annotations in a given XQuery module, the corresponding namespace has to
            be declared:</para>
            <synopsis language="xquery">declare namespace test="http://exist-db.org/xquery/xqsuite";</synopsis>
            <para>A function in the module will be considered by the test runner if it has at least one
                    <code>test:assertXXX</code> annotation, where "XXX" stands for the annotation
                type ("assertEquals", "assertEmpty" ...). Other functions - including private ones -
                will be simply ignored. A minimal example may thus look as follows:</para>
            <programlisting language="xquery">declare function %test:assertEquals("Hello world") local:hello() {
    "Hello world"
};</programlisting>
            <para>When the test runner encounters this function, it will evaluate it once and compare
            its return value to the assertion.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Parameterized Tests</title>
            <para>The simple example above does not expect any parameters. To test
            a function which does take parameters, use the <code>%test:arg</code> annotation in
            combination with one or more assertions:</para>
            <programlisting language="xquery">declare
    %test:arg("n", 1) %test:assertEquals(1)
    %test:arg("n", 5) %test:assertEquals(120)
function m:factorial($n as xs:int) as xs:int {
    if ($n = 1) then
        1
    else
        $n * m:factorial($n - 1)
};</programlisting>
            <para>This example shows multiple tests on the same function using different parameter
            values. The <code>%test:arg</code> annotation is used to set the parameters for the next
            test run, which is triggered by the assertion. This means the tested function will be
            called once for every sequence of <code>%test:arg</code> annotations followed by one or
            more <code>%test:assertXXX</code>. The order of the annotations is thus
            important!</para>
            <para>The first annotation argument to <code>%test:arg</code> denotes the name of the
            function parameter variable to set, the remaining arguments are used to create the
            sequence of values passed. There have to be as many %test:arg annotations for every test
            run as the function takes parameters.</para>
            <para>The result returned by the function call is passed to each assertion in turn, which
            may either pass or fail.&#160;In the example above, we assert that the function should return
            1 if the input parameter is 1, and 120 if the input is 5.</para>
            <para>To test a function which takes a sequence with more than one item for a parameter,
            just append additional values to <code>%test:arg</code>. The test runner will convert
            the values into a sequence.</para>
            <para>If all function parameters expect exactly one value, you can also use a shorter form
            of <code>%test:arg</code>: instead of specifying one <code>%test:arg</code> annotation
            for every parameter, use a single <code>%test:args</code> annotation to define all
            parameter values at once. <code>%test:args</code> simply takes a list of values. Each
            value is mapped to exactly one function parameter. Example:</para>
            <programlisting language="xquery">declare
    %test:args("Hello", "world")
    %test:assertEquals("Hello world")
function local:hello($greet as xs:string, $user as xs:string) {
    $greet || " " || $user
};</programlisting>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Automatic Type Conversion</title>
            <para>XQuery annotation parameters need to be literal values, so only strings and
                numbers are allowed. XQSuite thus applies type conversion to every argument as well
                as to values used in assertions. For example, the following function expects a
                parameter of type <code>xs:date</code>:</para>
            <programlisting language="xquery">declare
    %test:args("2012-06-26")
    %test:assertEquals("26.6.2012")
    %test:args("2012-06-01")
    %test:assertEquals("1.6.2012")
function fd:simple-date($date as xs:date) as xs:string {
    format-date($date, "[D].[M].[Y]")
};</programlisting>
            <para>The string value passed to the <code>%test:args</code> annotation is automatically
                converted to the sequence type declared for the function parameter:
                    <code>xs:date</code>.  The same applies to the assertion values.</para>
            <para>Type conversion works for all primitive types as well as XML nodes.</para>
            <para>If automatic type conversion fails for some reason, the test case will fail as
                well.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Supported Annotations</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>%test:arg($varName, $value1, $value2, ...)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Set the function parameter with variable name $varName to the sequence
                            constructed by converting the remaining annotation parameters to the
                            sequenceType declared by the function parameter.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>%test:args($arg1, $arg2, ...)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Run the function using the supplied literal arguments. There has to be
                            one annotation argument for each parameter the function takes.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>%test:assertEmpty, %test:assertExists</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Expects the function to return an empty sequence (assertEmpty) or a
                            non-empty sequence (assertExists). </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>%test:assertTrue, %test:assertFalse</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Checks if the effective boolean value of the returned result is true
                            or false. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>%test:assertEquals($value1, $value2, ...)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Tests if the return value equals the specified argument. If the
                            function returns more than one item, each item is compared to the given
                            annotation values in turn. The number of returned items has to
                            correspond to the number of annotation values.&#160; If the function returns
                            an atomic type, the assertion argument is cast into the same type and
                            the two are compared using the eq operator.&#160; If the sequence returned by
                            the function contains one or more XML elements, they will be normalized
                            (i.e. ignorable whitespace is stripped). The assertion argument is then
                            parsed into XML and the two node trees are compared using the
                            deep-equals function. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>%test:assertError($errString)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Evaluating the tested function should result in a dynamic error. If
                            value is given, it should either be a string contained in the error
                            description or correspond to the error code of the dynamic error.</para>
                        <para>The annotation value is executed as an XPath expression. The assert
                            passes if the XPath expression returns a non-empty sequence or a single
                            atomic item whose effective boolean value is true. Within the XPath
                            expression, the variable&#160;<emphasis role="bold">$result</emphasis>contains a reference to the result sequence returned
                            by the tested function.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>%test:setUp, %test:tearDown</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Special functions which will be called once before (or after) any
                            other tests contained in the same XQuery module are run. Use those
                            functions to upload data, create indexes, users or prepare anything else
                            needed for tests to run. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Running a Test Suite</title>
            <para>To run a suite of tests, you need to create a main XQuery which</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>imports the <filename>xqsuite.xql</filename> test framework</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>calls <code>test:suite</code> with the sequence of function items to
                        test</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>For a complete example, store the following XQuery module into the database
            as <filename>math.xql</filename>:</para>
            <programlisting language="xquery">xquery version "3.0";

module namespace m="http://foo.org/xquery/math";

declare namespace test="http://exist-db.org/xquery/xqsuite";

declare
    %test:arg("n", 1) %test:assertEquals(1)
    %test:arg("n", 5) %test:assertEquals(120)
function m:factorial($n as xs:int) as xs:int {
    if ($n = 1) then
        1
    else
        $n * m:factorial($n - 1)
};</programlisting>
            <para>To run the tests in this module, create a main XQuery called <filename>suite.xql</filename>
            and store it into the same collection:</para>
            <programlisting language="xquery">xquery version "3.0";

import module namespace test="http://exist-db.org/xquery/xqsuite" 
at "resource:org/exist/xquery/lib/xqsuite/xqsuite.xql";

test:suite(
    inspect:module-functions(xs:anyURI("math.xql"))
)</programlisting>
            <para>Executing the main XQuery within eXide will return the test results as an XML
                fragment (see below).</para>
            <para>In the main XQuery, the function: <code>inspect:module-functions</code> returns a function item for
                every public function defined in the module loaded from the location URI given as
                argument. The location URI is resolved in the same way as in a normal module import,
                so a relative path will be interpreted relative to the location of the main
                XQuery.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Test Suite Output</title>
            <para>
                <code>test:suite</code> returns the results of the tests as an XML fragment using
                the schema defined by the xUnit test tool. The xUnit format is supported by many
                systems, e.g. Jenkins, and is thus a good choice, even though it was designed for
                Java and not XQuery. For every XQuery module tested, <code>test:suite</code> creates
                one <sgmltag>testsuite</sgmltag> element. The result of each test run is output as a
                    <sgmltag>testcase</sgmltag> element. It will be empty if the test has passed. If
                the test failed, there will be a <sgmltag>failure</sgmltag> element containing the
                expected result of the function, and an <sgmltag>output</sgmltag> element with the
                actual result. An example is given below:</para>
            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;testsuites&gt;
    &lt;testsuite package="http://exist-db.org/xquery/test/bang" timestamp="2012-10-16T10:30:12.966+02:00" failures="1" tests="19" time="PT0.046S"&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="constructor" class="bang:constructor"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="functions1" class="bang:functions1"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="functions2" class="bang:functions2"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="functions3" class="bang:functions3"&gt;
            &lt;failure message="assertEquals failed." type="failure-error-code-1"&gt;RED BLACK GREEN&lt;/failure&gt;
            &lt;output&gt;RED BLUE GREEN&lt;/output&gt;
        &lt;/testcase&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="functions4" class="bang:functions4"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="nodepath" class="bang:nodepath"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="nodepath-reverse" class="bang:nodepath-reverse"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="nodes1" class="bang:nodes1"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="nodes2" class="bang:nodes2"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="numbers1" class="bang:numbers1"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="position1" class="bang:position1"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="position2" class="bang:position2"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="position3" class="bang:position3"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="position4" class="bang:position4"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="position5" class="bang:position5"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="precedence1" class="bang:precedence1"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="precedence2" class="bang:precedence2"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="precedence3" class="bang:precedence3"/&gt;
        &lt;testcase name="sequence" class="bang:sequence"/&gt;
    &lt;/testsuite&gt;
&lt;/testsuites&gt;</programlisting>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>