<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>Database Deployment</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>operations</keyword>
      <keyword>java-development</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>This article explains how to install eXist-db as a stand-alone or embedded server.</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>There are <emphasis>three</emphasis> ways to deploy the eXist-db database:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>In a Servlet Context</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The database is deployed as part of a web application. eXist will happily live together with other servlets. This is the default mode
            established when the database is deployed according to instructions provided in the <link xlink:href="basic-installation">Basic
              Installation Guide</link>.</para>
          <para>In this mode all resources used by eXist-db will have paths relative to the web application's current context. For example, eXist will
            store all its database files in the <literal>WEB-INF/data</literal> directory of the web application (unless specifically configured
            otherwise).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Stand-alone Server Process</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>In stand-alone mode, eXist-db runs in its own Java virtual machine (JVM). Clients have to access the database through the network,
            either using the XML-RPC, WebDAV protocol or the REST-style HTTP API.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Embedded in an Application</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>In embedded mode, the database is basically used as a Java library, controlled by the client application. It runs in the same JVM as
            the client, no network connection is needed. The client has full access to the database.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>All three deployments are thread-safe and allow concurrent operations by multiple users. Servlets running in the same web application
      context will have direct access to the database. External client applications may still use the supplied network interfaces.</para>
    <para>Detailed instructions on how to set up eXist-db for use with a servlet-engine are provided in the <link xlink:href="basic-installation">Basic Installation Guide</link>. The sections in this document address the other two deployment options. </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Section 2 introduces the XML:DB URI and explain how different servers are addressed by Java clients.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Section 3 deals with running eXist as a stand-alone server</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Section 4 addresses the required steps to directly embed eXist into an application, including how to embed it in the <link xlink:href="http://titanium.dstc.edu.au" condition="_blank">XMLdbGUI</link>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Addressing Servers using the XML:DB URI</title>

    <para>One way to access eXist-db from Java applications is to use the XML:DB API. The XML:DB API uses a specific URI scheme to locate a collection
      of XML resources on the server. You will encounter XML:DB URIs when working with the Java client, the backup tools and sometimes in XQuery
      functions. It is therefore important to understand how the URI scheme addresses servers and resources.</para>
    <para>eXist's XML:DB API implementation supports transparent access to remote as well as embedded database servers. This means the database on the
      server is available on the client as though it were locally connected to the client. The user should not have to be aware of where a resource is
      physically located. Applications need not be affected by how the database has been deployed.</para>

    <para>The XML:DB URI identifies the database implementation, the name of the collection, and optionally the location of the database server on the
      network. </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>In a Servlet Context</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use the following URI to points to the Shakespeare collection on a remote server which is running in a <emphasis>servlet
              engine</emphasis>:</para>
          <programlisting>xmldb:exist://localhost:8080/exist/xmlrpc/db/shakespeare</programlisting>
          <para>The host part: <literal>localhost:8080/exist/xmlrpc</literal> describes the path to the XML-RPC listener, which is running as a
            servlet. The collection part (<literal>/db/shakespeare</literal>) defines the collection to retrieve.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Stand-alone Server Process</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If eXist had started as a stand-alone server, the URI would change its port to <literal>8088</literal>:</para>
          <programlisting>xmldb:exist://localhost:8088/xmlrpc/db/shakespeare</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Embedded in an Application</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>To access an <emphasis>embedded instance</emphasis> of the database, we simply drop the host part altogether and use three forward
            slashes (<literal>///</literal>) in front of the collection path:</para>
          <programlisting>xmldb:exist:///db/shakespeare</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>You can use the <link xlink:href="java-admin-client">Java Admin Client</link>, which utilizes the XML:DB API to access the database, to
      experiment with these settings. The <guimenuitem>Login</guimenuitem> dialog offers a text field where you can specify an XML:DB URI to connect
      to.</para>
    <para>By default, the client tries to access the database engine located at the base URI:</para>
    <programlisting>xmldb:exist://localhost:8080/exist/xmlrpc/</programlisting>
    <para>Change the entry in the GUI to try another URI or pass it using the <literal>-ouri</literal> option on the command line. For example:</para>
    <programlisting>bin/client.sh -ouri=xmldb:exist://</programlisting>
    <para>This will cause a local database instance to run in the same Java virtual machine as the client.</para>
    <para>There is also a short form for this command. The <literal>-l</literal> option causes the client to launch a local database instance. For
      instance:</para>
    <programlisting>bin/client.sh -l</programlisting>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Deploying in a Servlet Container</title>

    <para>The standard distribution by default launches eXist-db as a web application deployed in a <link xlink:href="http://eclipse.org/jetty/" condition="_blank">Jetty</link> servlet container.</para>
    <para>The Jetty configuration can be found in <literal>tools/jetty/webapps/exist-webapp-context.xml</literal>. It defines a single web application context value <literal>&lt;Set name="contextPath"&gt;/exist&lt;/Set&gt;</literal>, mapped to the <literal>webapp</literal> directory. This value can be set to either <literal>/exist</literal> or <literal>/</literal>. Users modifying this value should subsequently remove the <literal>portal</literal> folder at <literal> /tools/jetty/webapps</literal>, which contains the default exist-db splashscreen displayed during certain redirects.</para>
    <para>Jetty is small, efficient and stable, so there is no need to switch to a different servlet engine unless your server setup requires this.
      However, it is not difficult to deploy eXist in a different servlet container, e.g. Apache's Tomcat.</para>
    <para>We usually provide a <literal>.war</literal> web archive for all major releases. You may either download that or, if you already installed
      the standard distribution, build a <code>.war</code> archive yourself. For details on how to do this, see <link xlink:href="exist-building">Building eXist-db</link>
    </para>
    <para>To install the <code>.war</code>, just copy it into the corresponding folder below your servlet engine installation (usually
        <literal>webapps</literal>) and rename it to <literal>exist.war</literal>. The servlet engine will normally unpack the file when you restart
      the server. To have better control of where the file is unpacked, you can also create a directory <literal>exist</literal> below the
        <literal>webapps</literal> folder and manually extract the <code>.war</code> there. For instance:</para>
    <programlisting>jar xfv exist.war</programlisting>
    <important>
      <para>Please remember that the <literal>data</literal> and <literal>log</literal> directories need to be writable!</para>
    </important>

    <para>There are a few differences between the standard distribution and the <code>.war</code> install. In particular, the configuration files are
      found in the <literal>WEB-INF</literal> directory, including the important files <literal>conf.xml</literal> (eXist configuration) and
        <literal>log4j.xml</literal> (logging). The example data is in <literal>samples</literal>.</para>
    <para>To start the <link xlink:href="java-admin-client">Java Admin Client</link>, use the following command (from within <literal>exist</literal>
      web application's root directory):</para>
    <programlisting>java -jar WEB-INF/lib/start.jar client -ls</programlisting>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Running as a Stand-alone Server</title>

    <para>There are many cases in which it is preferable to have the database engine running in its own Java virtual machine. In stand-alone mode,
      eXist will launch its own, embedded web server to provide XML-RPC, WebDAV and REST services to the outside world. The embedded server is based
      on a stripped-down Jetty. It uses a limited configuration, excluding all the additional services available in a full-blown servlet
      environment.</para>
    <para>The stand-alone deployment is more reliable and performs better than the web application setup, since no other threads (simultaneous tasks)
      are running. The stand-alone database server offers XML-RPC, WebDAV and REST-style HTTP interfaces for external client access. Please note that it does
      not support SOAP. </para>
    <para>By default, the stand-alone server listens on port <literal>8088</literal>, though this can be changed (see configuration below). The Java
      class for launching the server is <literal>org.exist.jetty.StandaloneServer</literal>.</para>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Starting the Stand-alone Server</title>

      <para>To start the server use either the <code>bin/server.sh</code> (Unix) or the <code>bin\server.bat</code> (Windows) command.</para>

      <para>The server is multi-threaded, a server thread is assigned to each client request. If the specified maximum number of threads is reached,
        the server will block the client until one of the server-threads is available to respond. By default, the maximum number of threads is 5. To
        change this, use the <literal>-t</literal> option, e.g.:</para>
      <programlisting>bin\server.bat -t 20</programlisting>
      <para>To access the stand-alone server using the <link xlink:href="java-admin-client">Java Admin Client</link> (or by your own Java classes),
        start the XML:DB server URI to <code>xmldb:exist://localhost:8088/xmlrpc</code>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Standalone Server Configuration</title>

      <para>The <literal>tools/jetty/etc/standalone/WEB-INF/web.xml</literal> configuration file is used when the server operates in standalone mode.
        An instance of the Jetty web server is configured using its settings. The services offered with eXist have their own configuration servlet
        element in this file.</para>
      <para>Currently, the servlet API alternatives are "<literal>webdav</literal>, "<literal>xmlrpc</literal>", and "<literal>rest</literal>". Any of
        these servlets can be disabled by setting a init-param <literal>enabled</literal> attribute to "<literal>no</literal>".</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Controlling the Binding Address (&lt;indexer&gt;)</title>

        <para>You can control the binding address by changing the addConnector <tag>Call</tag> element in
          <code>tools/jetty/etc/standalone.xml</code>:</para>
        <variablelist spacing="compact">
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>port</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The port on which the server will listen. The Jetty web server will bind to port <literal>8088</literal> by default.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>host</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The host-name on which the server will respond.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>address</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The IP address on which the server should bind. This may be useful when the server has multiple addresses that serve the same
                host-name.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>WebDAV Servlet</title>

        <para>The WebDAV servlet provides services at the context address specified. This servlet is represented by the <tag>webdav</tag> element in
          the <literal>server.xml</literal> configuration file. For this element, the <literal>context</literal> attribute controls the web server
          context at which the WebDAV services are provided. If the <literal>context</literal> attribute is not specified, it defaults to
            <literal>/webdav/</literal>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>XML-RPC Servlet</title>

        <para>The XML-RPC servlet provides database API services to clients, like the Admin GUI client. This servlet is represented by the
            <tag>xmlrpc</tag> element in the <literal>server.xml</literal> configuration file. For this element, the <literal>context</literal>
          attribute controls the web server context at which the XMLRPC services are provided. If the <literal>context</literal> attribute is not
          specified, it defaults to <literal>/xmlrpc/</literal>. </para>
        <warning>
          <para>If you disable this servlet, you disable the use of the <link xlink:href="java-admin-client">Java Admin Client</link>.</para>
        </warning>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>REST Servlet</title>

        <para>The REST servlet provides HTTP/REST-style interactions with the database. It is configured by a <tag>servlet</tag> element with
            <tag>servlet-class</tag>
          <code>org.exist.http.servlets.EXistServlet</code> in the <literal>tools/jetty/etc/standalone/WEB-INF/web.xml</literal> configuration file.
          It depends on the <code>XQueryURLRewrite</code> filter for context, default is <literal>/</literal>.</para>
        <para>The REST Servlet has a number of other parameters that can be set by child elements:</para>
        <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-15.xml"/>
        <variablelist spacing="compact">
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>form-encoding</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The default encoding of form POSTs.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>container-encoding</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The default encoding of the servlet container for all HTTP interactions except POSTs.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>use-default-user</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A boolean value (<literal>true</literal>/<literal>false</literal>) that indicates whether the effective user must be used for
                non-authenticated interactions. If any of these fails a simple AUTH interaction is undertaken. </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>user</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The username of the default user.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <code>password</code>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The password of the default user.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Custom Servlets</title>

        <para>Any servlet can be configured to run in the Jetty server by adding a <tag>servlet</tag> element to the <code>server.xml</code>
          configuration file. The <tag>servlet</tag> element has the standard attributes of <code>enabled</code> and <code>context</code>, as well as
          the <code>class</code> attribute to specify the servlet implementation class.</para>
        <para>This element can have any number of <tag>param</tag> child-elements to set parameters for the servlet. For example:</para>

        <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-16.xml"/>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Forwarding Requests</title>

        <para>The forwarding-request settings allow you to map incoming URL requests to specific resources on the server (e.g. queries). This is done
          with the <tag>forwarding</tag> element. Inside this element is a single <tag>root</tag> element and any number of <tag>forward</tag>
          elements. </para>
        <para>Each <tag>forward</tag> element specifies a specific primary URL that is forwarded to secondary URL. This allows you to map a "clean"
          URL to an XQuery or some other resource within the server. The target is always specified by a <literal>destination</literal> attribute. For
          instance:</para>
        <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-18.txt"/>
        <para>Here the first <tag>forward</tag> element maps the URI path <literal>/admin</literal> to the XQuery resource
            <literal>/db/admin/admin.xql</literal>, the second one maps the URI path <literal>/docs</literal> to the document
            <literal>/db/products/docs.xml</literal>.</para>

        <para>The <tag>root</tag> element maps requests to the root directory of the server (for instance <literal>/</literal>) to a specified
          resource. For example:</para>
        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;root destination="/db/admin/admin.xql" /&gt;</programlisting>
        <para>This maps a requests for the (default) server root to the XQuery resource <literal>/db/admin/admin.xql</literal>.</para>

      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Shutting Down the Database</title>

      <para>Use the <literal>shutdown.bat</literal> (Windows/DOS) and <literal>shutdown.sh</literal> (Unix) scripts to shutdown the database. These
        commands connect to the default server URI, usually <code>xmldb:exist://localhost:8080/exist/xmlrpc</code>.</para>
      <para>If your database is running in stand-alone mode, you must specify a different server URI. For instance, to stop eXist when running in
        stand-alone mode, listening on port <literal>8088</literal>, use:</para>
      <programlisting>java -jar start.jar shutdown --uri=xmldb:exist://localhost:8088/xmlrpc</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <!-- STOPPED HERE ! -->
  <sect1>
    <title>Embedding eXist in an Application</title>

    <para>In the embedded mode, the database runs in the same Java virtual machine as the client application. The database will not be accessible by
      any outside application and no network listeners are started. You can embed eXist-db into any Java application using the XML:DB API.</para>
    <para>To prepare the environment for using an embedded eXist, follow the steps below:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Copy <literal>conf.xml</literal> and <literal>log4j.xml</literal> to the target directory.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create a subdirectory <literal>data</literal> in the target directory.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Edit the <literal>files</literal> attribute in the <tag>db-connection</tag> section of <literal>conf.xml</literal> to point to this data
          directory.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Do the same for the <literal>journal-dir</literal> in the <tag>recovery</tag> element.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>To see logging output, edit <literal>log4j.xml</literal>. The simplest way is to change the <literal>appender-ref</literal> in the
            <tag>root</tag> category to <literal>console</literal>. This will result in most log messages being written to the console.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create a <literal>lib</literal> directory below the target directory and copy the following <literal>.jar</literal> files from eXist-db
          into it:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>exist.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/extensions/exist-modules.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/core/antlr-X.X.X.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/core/commons-pool-X.X.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/core/commons-collections-X.X.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/core/commons-logging-X.X.X.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/core/log4j-X.X.X.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/optional/slf4j-api-X.X.X.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/optional/slf4j-log4j12-X.X.X.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/core/quartz-X.X.X.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/core/sunxacml.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/core/xmldb.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/core/xmlrpc-client-X.X.X.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/core/xmlrpc-common-X.X.X.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/core/xmlrpc-server-X.X.X.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/core/jta.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lib/core/pkg-repo.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>If you plan to use extension modules (like the n-gram index), copy the corresponding jars from <literal>lib/extensions</literal>. The
          default eXist configuration needs:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>exist-ngram-module.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>exist-lucene-module.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>exist-versioning.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>For the Lucene module copy the jars from <literal>extensions/indexes/lib</literal>:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lucene-core-X.X.X.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>lucene-regex-X.X.X.jar</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The <literal>lib/endorsed</literal> directory furthermore plays a special role: the Java releases come with their own XML support
          libraries, including Xalan (for XSLT processing), an XML parser, and the standard Java interfaces for SAX and DOM. Some features of eXist
          will not work properly with a wrong version of Xerces or the resolver <code>.jar</code> (schema validation, catalog loading, ...). To ensure
          the correct versions are available, we have included these versions of Xerces, Xalan and Saxon, plus the standard interfaces used by both of
          them. You can use Java's endorsed library loading mechanism to ensure the correct XML support libraries are loaded. </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Create a directory <literal>lib/endorsed</literal>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Copy all <code>.jar</code> files from eXist's <literal>lib/endorsed</literal> directory into the newly created directory</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Specifying the <literal>-Djava.endorsed.dirs=lib/endorsed</literal> system property on the Java command line will force the JVM to
          prefer any library it finds in the endorsed directory over its own system libraries (copying the jars into
            <literal>$JAVA_HOME/jre/lib/endorsed</literal> will do the same thing). Note that the batch and shell scripts included with eXist all set
          the <literal>java.endorsed.dirs</literal> system property to point to <literal>lib/endorsed</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Make sure your <code>CLASSPATH</code> includes these <code>.jar</code> files.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Internally, eXist has two different XML:DB driver implementations: the first communicates with a remote database engine using XML-RPC calls;
      the second has direct access to a local instance of eXist. Which implementation is selected depends on the XML:DB URI as described above.</para>
    <para>To access an embedded database, simply drop the host portion (for instance <literal>localhost:8088/xmlrpc/</literal>) from the URI. For
      instance: <code>xmldb:exist:///db</code>
        </para>
    <para>To start an embedded database instance, simply set the system property <literal>exist.initdb</literal> to <literal>true</literal>. This will
      notify the XML:DB driver to read the configuration settings when starting the database if none has been previously started. For example, to
      launch your own Java application with an embedded instance, you may enter the command:</para>
    <programlisting>java -Dexist.initdb=true MyApp</programlisting>
    <para>The driver will try to read the eXist configuration file, create the required database files (if absent) and launch the database. </para>
    <para>The driver must be able to read the configuration file <literal>conf.xml</literal>. It seraches for <literal>conf.xml</literal> in the
      directory specified by the <literal>exist.home</literal> system property. You should therefore ensure a copy of <literal>conf.xml</literal> is
      present in the correct directory. For example, to launch your own application, while setting <literal>exist.home</literal>:</para>
    <programlisting>java -Dexist.initdb=true -Dexist.home=/home/exist/eXist MyApp</programlisting>
    <important>
      <para>The paths to the data and log directories in <literal>conf.xml</literal> need to point to <emphasis>writable</emphasis>
        directories.</para>
    </important>
    <para>Instead of using the <literal>-Dexist.initdb</literal> property, you can also tell the database driver to create a local database instance
      during the initialization of the XML:DB database manager within your Java code. Set the <literal>create-database</literal> property on the
      created <literal>Database</literal> object to <literal>true</literal>. For example:</para>
    <programlisting language="java" xlink:href="listings/listing-24.txt"/>

    <para>When running eXist in embedded mode, ensure proper shutdown the database before your application exits. The main reason is to flush all of
      the unwritten data buffers to disk. The database uses a background thread to periodically synchronize its buffers with the data files on disk,
      and this thread will keep running unless you shutdown the database.</para>
    <para>There is a special XML:DB service, <literal>DatabaseInstanceManager</literal>, which contains a single method: <literal>shutdown</literal>.
      To properly shutdown the database instance, retrieve the service from the <literal>/db-collection</literal> and call
        <literal>shutdown()</literal>. For example:</para>
    <programlisting language="java" xlink:href="listings/listing-25.txt"/>
    <para>To summarize, a minimal working class with a single static main to start/stop the db may look like this:</para>

    <programlisting language="java" xlink:href="listings/listing-26.txt"/>
    <para>Put this code into a Java file <literal>TestDB.java</literal>, store it into the target directory (which we prepared above), and compile and
      run it with:</para>
    <programlisting>javac TestDB.java java -Dexist.initdb=true -Dexist.home=. TestDB</programlisting>
  </sect1>
</article>
