<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>Upgrade Guide</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>operations</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->


  <para>This article explains the best practices for upgrading eXist-db. It provides instructions
    for several different types of upgrades. Following these instructions will ensure your data is
    properly backed up and preserved during the upgrade process.</para>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="key-concepts">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The primary goal of an upgrade is to migrate your eXist application to a new version,
      while preserving the contents of your database.</para>
    <para>Before embarking on an upgrade, you should first review the new version's release notes
      (see the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://exist-db.org/exist/apps/wiki/blogs/eXist/" condition="_blank">eXist
        Developer's Blog</link> for an archive of all past release notes). The release notes
      introduce the new version's features, improvements and bug fixes. They can also outline any
      new requirements (for instance the required version of Java). </para>
    <para>For the purpose of this guide, the most important item in the release notes is whether the
      new version is <emphasis>binary-compatible</emphasis> with the previous version or not. Pay
      close attention to these notes, as they will tell you which upgrade route to follow.</para>
    <para>If a new version is binary-compatible with the previous version, it means the format eXist
      uses to store the contents of the database has not changed. The data can be used by new
      version without modification. </para>
    <para>However, if a new version is <emphasis>not</emphasis> binary-compatible, the new version
      of eXist has changed the way it reads data from or stores data into the database. Additional
      steps are required to migrate your data to the new version of eXist.</para>
    <para>Always back up your data before upgrading to any new version of eXist.</para>
    <para>Do not install the new version of eXist over the previous version. Instead, install the
      new version into a fresh new directory.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="binary-compatible-upgrades">
    <title>Binary Compatible Upgrades</title>

    <para>Follow these steps if the new version of eXist is binary-compatible with the your old
      version (as can be found in the release notes):</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Stop the existing installation of eXist.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create a <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="backup.xml">backup</link> of the data from your existing installation.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Install the new version of eXist. Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> install one eXist
          version over the existing one. Always install the new version into a fresh new
          directory.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Remove the still <emphasis>empty</emphasis>
          <code>data</code> directory from the new installation. By default the data directory is
          located in <code>webapp/WEB-INF/data</code>. If you are not sure where the data directory
          is, check the main logfile <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="troubleshooting.xml#logs">
            <code>exist.log</code>
          </link>, searching for entries after start-up pertaining to <code>DATA_DIR</code>. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Copy the entire existing data directory, and paste it to the location of the new data directory (the directory you
           deleted in the previous step).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Start the new eXist instance.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Check the <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="troubleshooting.xml#logs">
            <code>exist.log</code>
          </link> for any errors during startup.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="non-binary-compatible-upgrades">
    <title>Binary Non-compatible Upgrades</title>

    <para>Follow these steps if the new version of eXist is not binary-compatible with the your old
      version (as can be found in the release notes). The key difference with upgrading to a binary-compatible new version
      is that you have to perform a <emphasis>full restore</emphasis> of your backed-up data into the
      new installation.</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create a <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="backup">server-side backup</link>. This can be done in a number
          of ways: </para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use Backup Central from the Dashboard (with "Zip" option for databases with less
              then 4GB)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The Emergency Backup Tool (GUI) for installer based systems:</para>
            <programlisting language="shell">java -jar start.jar -Xmx2048m org.exist.backup.ExportGUI</programlisting>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The Emergency Backup Tool (CLI) for headless sytems:</para>
            <programlisting language="shell">java -jar start.jar org.exist.backup.ExportMain -x -z</programlisting>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Via XQuery:</para>
            <programlisting xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-3.txt"/>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Once the backup is complete, you should check the backup report in the
            <code>export</code> directory within either the <code>data</code> directory (for backups created via
          the Dashboard or Xquery) or <code>$EXIST-HOME</code> (for backups created by the
          Emergency Backup Tool).</para>
        <para>Normally this report just contains the list of collections which were backed up. If
          you see any warnings or errors, it is even more  important to perform a “full
          restore” of your backed-up data.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Stop the existing installation of eXist.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Install the new version of eXist. DO not install one eXist version over
          another one. Always install the new version into a fresh new directory.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Perform a full <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="backup.xml#restore">restore</link> of the backup onto the new version of
          eXist.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="compatibility-history">
    <title>History of Non-compatible Upgrades</title>

    <para>This is a list of binary non-compatible releases for quick reference.</para>
    <para>If a non-incremental upgrade across multiple non-compatible releases is necessary,
      foir instance from 1.4 to 3.6, we strongly recommend to first check past release notes to understand
      how breaking changes might affect you.</para>
    
    <table xml:id="old-news">
      <title>Notes on previous releases</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>latest</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://exist-db.org/exist/apps/wiki/blogs/eXist/search.html?field=tags&amp;q=release">release notes</link>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>3.0</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="incompatibilities.xml#v3.0">special notes</link>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>2.2</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="incompatibilities.xml#v2.2">special notes</link>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>2.0</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="incompatibilities.xml#v2.0">special notes</link>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>1.4.0</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="incompatibilities.xml#v1.4">special notes</link>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect1>
</article>