<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>REST-Style Web API</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>application-development</keyword>
      <keyword>interfaces</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>eXist-db provides a REST-style (or <emphasis>RESTful</emphasis>) API through HTTP, which provides a simple and quick way to access the
    database. To use this API, all one needs is an HTTP client, which is provided by nearly all programming languages and environments. Or simply use
    a web-browser…</para>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="rest">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>In the standard eXIst-db configuration, the system will listen for REST request at:</para>
    <programlisting>http://localhost:8080/exist/rest/</programlisting>

    <para>The server treats all HTTP request paths as paths to a database collection (instead of the file system). Relative paths are resolved
      relative to the database root collection. For instance:</para>
    <programlisting>http://localhost:8080/exist/rest/db/shakespeare/plays/hamlet.xml</programlisting>
    <para>The server will receive an HTTP GET request for the resource <literal>hamlet.xml</literal> in the collection
        <literal>/db/shakespeare/plays</literal>. Itr will look for this collection and check if the resource is available. If so, it will retrieve
      its contents and send this back to the client. If the document does not exist, an <emphasis>HTTP 404 (Not Found)</emphasis> status response will
      be returned.</para>

    <para>To keep the interface simple, the basic database operations are directly mapped to HTTP request methods wherever possible:</para>
    <variablelist spacing="compact">
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>GET</code>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Retrieves a resource or collection from the database. XQuery and XPath queries may also be specified using GET's optional parameters
            applied to the selected resource. See <xref linkend="get-requests"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>PUT</code>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Uploads a resource to the database. If required, collections are automatically created and existing resources overwritten. See <xref linkend="put-requests"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>DELETE</code>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Removes a resource (document or collection) from the database. See <xref linkend="delete-requests"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>POST</code>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Submits an XML fragment in the content of the request. This fragment specifies the action to take. The fragment can be either an
            XUpdate document or a query request. Query requests are used to pass complex XQuery expressions too large to be URL-encoded. See <xref linkend="post-requests"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <note>
      <para> When running eXist-db as a stand-alone server(when the database has been started using the shell-script <literal>bin/server.sh</literal>
        (Unix) or batch file <literal>bin/server.bat</literal> (Windows/DOS)), HTTP access is supported through a simple, built-in web server. This
        web server has limited capabilities, restricted to the basic operations defined by eXist's REST API (<literal>GET</literal>,
          <literal>POST</literal>, <literal>PUT</literal> and <literal>DELETE</literal>).</para>
      <para>When running in a servlet-context (the usual way of starting eXist-db), this same server functionality is provided by the
          <literal>EXistServlet</literal>.</para>
      <para>Both the stand-alone server and the servlet rely on Java class <literal>org.exist.http.RESTServer</literal> to do the actual work.</para>
    </note>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>HTTP Authentication</title>

    <para>Authentication is done through the basic HTTP authentication mechanism so only authenticated users can access the database. If no username
      and password are specified, the server assumes a "guest" user identity, which has limited capabilities. If the username submitted is not known,
      or an incorrect password is submitted, an error page (<code>403</code> - Forbidden) is returned.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="get-requests">
    <title>GET Requests</title>

    <para>If the server receives an HTTP <code>GET</code> request, it first checks the request for known parameters. If no parameters are given or
      known it will try to locate the collection or document specified in the URI database path and return a representation of this resource the
      client.</para>
    <note>
      <para>When the located resource is XML, the returned <emphasis>content-type</emphasis> attribute value is <literal>application/xml</literal> and
        for binary resources <literal>application/octet-stream</literal>.</para>
    </note>
    <para>If the path resolves to a database collection, the retrieved results are returned as an XML fragment. For example:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-3.xml"/>

    <para>If an <literal>xml-stylesheet</literal> processing instruction is found in a requested XML document, the database will try to apply this
      stylesheet before returning the document. A relative path will be resolved relative to the location of the source document. For example, if the
      document <literal>hamlet.xml</literal>, which is stored in collection <literal>/db/shakespeare/plays</literal> contains the XSLT processing
      instruction:</para>
    <programlisting>&lt;?xml-stylesheet type="application/xml" href="shakes.xsl"?&gt;</programlisting>
    <para>The database will load the stylesheet from <literal>/db/shakespeare/plays/shakes.xsl</literal>.</para>
    <para>
      <code>GET</code> accepts the following optional request parameters (which must be URL-encoded):</para>
    <variablelist spacing="compact">
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>_xsl=XSL Stylesheet</code>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Applies an XSL stylesheet to the requested resource. A relative path is considered relative to the database root collection. This
            option will override any XSL stylesheet processing instructions found in the source XML file.</para>
          <para>Setting <literal>_xsl</literal> to <literal>no</literal> disables any stylesheet processing. This is useful for retrieving unprocessed
            XML from documents that have a stylesheet declaration.</para>
          <warning>
            <para>If your document has a valid XSL stylesheet declaration, the web browser may still decide to apply the XSL. In this case, passing
                <literal>_xsl=no</literal> has no visible effect, though the XSL is now rendered by the browser, <emphasis>not</emphasis>
              eXist.</para>
          </warning>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>_query=XPath/XQuery Expression</code>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Executes the query specified. The collection or resource referenced in the request path is added to the set of statically known
            documents for the query. </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>_indent=yes | no</code>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Whether to return indented pretty-printed XML. The default value is <literal>yes</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>_encoding=Character Encoding Type</code>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sets the character encoding for the resulting XML. The default value is <literal>UTF-8</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>_howmany=Number of Items</code>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the maximum number of items to return from the result sequence. The default value is <literal>10</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>_start=Starting Position in Sequence</code>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies the index position of the first item in the result sequence to return. The default value is <literal>1</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>_wrap=yes | no</code>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies whether the returned query results must be wrapped in a parent <tag>exist:result</tag> element. The default value is
              <literal>yes</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>_source=yes | no</code>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies whether the query should display its source code instead of being executed. The default value is <literal>no</literal>. See
            the <tag>allow-source</tag> section in <literal>descriptor.xml</literal> about explicitly allowing this behaviour.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>_cache=yes | no</code>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If set to <code>yes</code>, the results of the current query are stored in a session on the server. A session id will be returned with
            the response. Subsequent requests can pass this session id via the <literal>_session</literal> parameter. If the server finds a valid
            session id, it will return the cached results instead of re-evaluating the query. See below. </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>_session=session id</code>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies a session id returned by a previous query request. Query results will be read from the cached session.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <code>_release=session id</code>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Release the session identified by session id.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>As an example: The following URI will find all <tag>SPEECH</tag> elements in the collection <literal>/db/shakespeare</literal> with "Juliet"
      as the <tag>SPEAKER</tag>. As specified, it will return 5 items from the result sequence, starting at position 3:</para>
    <programlisting>http://localhost:8080/exist/rest/db/shakespeare?_query=//SPEECH[SPEAKER=%22JULIET%22]&amp;_start=3&amp;_howmany=5</programlisting>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="put-requests">
    <title>PUT Requests</title>

    <para>Documents can be stored or updated in the database using an HTTP <code>PUT</code> request. The request URI points to the location where the
      document must be stored. As defined by the HTTP specifications, an existing document at the specified path will be updated. Any collections
      defined in the path that do not exist are created automatically.</para>
    <para>For example, the following Python script stores a document (the name is specified on the command-line) in the database collection
        <literal>/db/test</literal>,. This will be created if it does not exist. Note that the HTTP header field <literal>content-type</literal> is
      specified as <literal>application/xml</literal>, since otherwise the document would be stored as a binary resource.</para>

    <programlisting language="java" xlink:href="listings/listing-6.txt"/>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="delete-requests">
    <title>DELETE Requests</title>

    <para>
      <code>DELETE</code> removes a collection or resource from the database.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="post-requests">
    <title>POST Requests</title>

    <para>
      <code>POST</code> requests require an XML fragment in the content of the request. This fragment specifies the action to take.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the root node of the fragment uses the XUpdate namespace (<literal>http://www.xmldb.org/xupdate</literal>), the fragment is sent to
          the XUpdateProcessor to be processed.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Otherwise the root node must have the namespace for eXist requests (<literal>http://exist.sourceforge.net/NS/exist</literal>). The
          fragment is interpreted as an <emphasis>extended query request</emphasis>. Extended query requests can be used to post complex XQuery
          scripts that are too large to be encoded in a <code>GET</code> request.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>


    <para>The structure of the POST XML request is as follows:</para>

    <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-7.xml"/>
    <para>The root element <literal>query</literal> identifies the fragment as an extended query request. The XQuery expression for this request is
      enclosed in the <literal>text</literal> element. The <code>start</code>, <code>max</code>, <code>cache</code> and <code>session-id</code>
      attributes have the same meaning as the corresponding <code>GET</code> parameters (see <xref linkend="get-requests"/>).</para>
    <note>
      <para>You may have to enclose the XQuery expression in a CDATA section (i.e. &lt;![CDATA[ ... ]]&gt;) to avoid parsing errors. </para>
    </note>
    <para>Optional output properties, such as <code>pretty-print</code>, can be passed in the <tag>properties</tag> element.</para>
    <para> An example of <code>POST</code> for Perl is provided below:</para>
    <programlisting language="java" xlink:href="listings/listing-8.txt"/>

    <para>The returned query results are enclosed in an <tag>exist:result</tag> element:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-9.xml"/>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Calling Stored XQueries</title>

    <para>The REST interface supports executing stored XQueries on the server. If the target resource of a <code>GET</code> or <code>POST</code>
      request is a binary resource with the mime-type <literal>application/xquery</literal>, the REST server will try to compile and execute it as an
      XQuery script. The script has access to the entire HTTP context, including parameters and session attributes.</para>
    <para>Stored XQueries are a good way to provide dynamic views on data or create small services. However, they can do more: because you can also
      store binary resources like images, CSS stylesheets or Javascript files into a database collection, it is entirely possible to serve a complex
      application out of the database. For instance, have a look at the example <link xlink:href="http://demo.exist-db.org/exist/apps/demo/examples/web/index.html">Using XQuery for Web Applications</link> on the demo
      server.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="cached-results">
    <title>Cached Query Results</title>

    <para>When executing queries using <code>GET</code> or <code>POST</code>, the server is able to cache query results in a server-side session.
      These results are cached in memory.</para>
    <note>
      <para>Memory consumption will be low for query results which reference nodes stored in the database and high for nodes constructed within the
        XQuery itself.</para>
    </note>
    <para>To create a session and store query results, pass <literal>_cache=yes</literal> with a <code>GET</code> request or set attribute
        <literal>cache="yes"</literal> within the XML payload of a <code>POST</code> query request. The server will execute the query as usual. If the
      result sequence contains more than one item, the entire sequence will be stored into a newly created session.</para>
    <para>The id of the created session is included in the response. For requests which return a <tag>exist:result</tag> wrapper element, the session
      id will be specified in the <literal>exist:session</literal> attribute. The session id is also available in the HTTP header
        <literal>X-Session-Id</literal>. </para>
    <para>The following example shows an example of the HTTP header and <tag>exist:result</tag> tag returned by the server:</para>

    <programlisting xlink:href="listings/listing-10.txt"/>
    <para>The session id can be passed with subsequent requests to retrieve further chunks of data without re-evaluating the query. For a
        <code>GET</code> request, pass the session id with parameter <literal>_session</literal>. For a <code>POST</code> request, add an attribute
        <literal>session="sessionId"</literal> to the XML content of the request.</para>
    <para>If the session does not exist or has timed out, the server will re-evaluate the query. The timeout is set to 2 minutes.</para>
    <para>A session can be deleted by sending a GET <code>request</code> to an arbitrary collection URL. Pass the session id in the
        <literal>_release</literal> parameter:</para>
    <programlisting>http://localhost:8080/exist/rest/db?_release=0</programlisting>
  </sect1>

</article>