<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>XInclude Support</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>application-development</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>eXist-db comes with partial support for the XInclude standard. By default, eXist-db's XML
    serializer will scan all XML fragments for XInclude tags. </para>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The XInclude processor is implemented as a filter in between the serializer's output event
      stream and the receiver. If it finds an XInclude element, it will try to expand it. XInclude
      processing is therefore applied whenever eXist-db serializes an XML fragment,whether it's a
      document, the result of an XQuery or an XSLT stylesheet.</para>
    <para>eXist-db's does not support the full XInclude standard:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para> You cannot include raw text, only XML.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para> XPointers are restricted to XPath. Additional features defined in the XPointer spec
          (points and locations) are not supported. However, you can use XPath functions to partly
          work around this and substitute XPointer's important <code>string-range()</code> function.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>eXist-db expands XIncludes at serialization, which means that the query engine will see
      the XInclude tags <emphasis>before</emphasis> they are expanded. You therefore cannot query
      across XIncludes, unless you create your own code (e.g. an XQuery function) for it.</para>
    <para>DTD entity declarations can be used for some of the things that XInclude can be used for.
      In general, however, XInclude is more powerful (with the exception that entity declarations
      are able include raw text). </para>

    <para>The XInclude namespace (in the examples below bound to the prefix <code>xi:</code>)
      is:</para>
    <programlisting>http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude</programlisting>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Including entire documents</title>

    <para>To include an entire document, simply specify its path in the <literal>href</literal>
      attribute of an <tag>xi:include</tag> element.</para>
    <para>For example, one can include a standard disclaimer, stored in the file
      <code>short-disclaimer.xml</code>, as follows:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;xi:include href="/db/apps/doc/data/disclaimer-short.xml"/&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>If the URI in the <code>href</code> attribute specifies a known scheme (like
      <code>http:</code> or <code>file:</code>), eXist-db will try to load it as an external
      resource. For example:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;xi:include href="http://localhost:8080/exist/rest/db/apps/doc/data/disclaimer-short.xml"/&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>If no scheme is specified, the XInclude processor will first try to load the referenced
      document from the database (relative to the current collection), and if that fails, from the
      file system.</para>
    <para>If the document that contains the XInclude has been constructed in an XQuery (see <xref linkend="sect-xquery-results"/>), relative file system paths will be resolved relative to the
      main XQuery module source file.</para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Selecting parts of a resource</title>

    <para>The <literal>xpointer</literal> attribute of the <tag>xi:include</tag> element can be used
      to identify which part of the resource to include.</para>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Selection by identifier</title>

      <para>If the XPointer contains a simple value it is interpreted as an identifier. This will
        select the element in the target document that has a matching attribute of type identifier
        (<code>ID</code>) (usually <code>xml:id</code>).</para>
      <para> For example, assume an XInclude target document <code>disclaimer.xml</code> looks like
        this:</para>
      <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/disclaimer.xml"/>
      <para>the following XInclude selects the element from <literal>disclaimer.xml</literal> with
        an <code>identifier</code> attribute with value <code>p1</code>:</para>
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;xi:include href="disclaimer.xml" xpointer="p1"/&gt;</programlisting>
      <para>When there are multiple instances of the same identifier attribute, only the first
        instance will be used.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Selecting by XPath expression</title>

      <para>We can also use an XPath expression to select fragments. For this the
        <literal>xpointer</literal> attribute must contain an XPointer, which consists of so called
        "schemes". An XPath expression can be passed through the <literal>xpointer()</literal>
        XPointer scheme. </para>
      <para> The following expression includes the first stage direction in Shakespeare's
        Macbeth:</para>
      <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-8.txt"/>

    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Selecting by a search expression</title>

      <para>XIncludes can also perform searches, for instance using a full-text search:</para>
      <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-10.txt"/>
      <para>The XPath expression will be applied to the entire collection if the path in
        <code>href</code> points to a collection and not a single document:</para>
      <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-12.txt"/>
      <para>In all cases, only the first hit is retrieved.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Namespace mappings</title>

      <para>All namespace/prefix mappings declared in the source document are passed to the query
        context. If necessary you can declare additional namespace mappings using
        <code>xmlns()</code>, like this:</para>
      <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-14.txt"/>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>


  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1 xml:id="sect-xquery-results">
    <title>Including XQuery results</title>

    <para>It is possible to include the result of an XQuery script by XInclude. If the target of an
      XInclude reference points to an XQuery document stored in the database (binary resource with
      MIME type <code>application/xquery</code>), the XInclude processor will attempt to compile and
      execute this query and use its results. </para>
    <para>For example:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;xi:include href="display-collection.xq"/&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>The XInclude processor declares two variables in the XQuery's static context:</para>
    <variablelist spacing="compact">
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
                    <code>$xinclude:current-doc</code>
                </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The name of the document which XInclude-s the query (without its collection
            path)</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
                    <code>$xinclude:current-collection</code>
                </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>the collection in which the current document resides</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>You can also pass additional parameters to the XQuery script:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;xi:include href="testvars.xq?var1=Hello&amp;var2=World"/&gt;</programlisting>
    <para>The parameters <literal>var1</literal> and <literal>var2</literal> will be available to
      the XQuery as an external global variable. The XQuery needs to declare them:</para>
    <programlisting language="xquery" xlink:href="listings/listing-25.txt"/>

  </sect1>
  
  <!-- ================================================================== -->
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Error Handling</title>
    
    <para>An error is raised if you try to XInclude a resource which does not exist. You can specify
      a fallback to avoid this. The result of the XInclude will be the content of the
      <tag>xi:fallback</tag> element:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-4.txt"/>
    
    <para>A fallback element itself cannot contain XInclude elements.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Implementing XPointer <code>string-range()</code>
        </title>

    <para>One reason why the XPointer spec has hardly seen any implementation is that it operates
      with "points" and "locations" which have no equivalent in the XPath Data Model. However, a
      major use case for the XPointer specification is to allow pointing at a range of characters
      inside an element. Luckily, we can work around the absence of this using the XPath functions
      <code>string-join()</code> and <code>substring()</code>.</para>
    <para>In the following example, a range of characters in the text node of a <tag>LINE</tag>
      element is extracted, 20 characters long, starting at the 22nd character:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-18.txt"/>
    <para>Since only string contents is involved, these ranges can also work on text nodes belonging
      to different elements. In the following example, parts of succeeding lines are extracted from
      the SPEECH element: </para>
    <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-20.txt"/>
  </sect1>


  <!-- ================================================================== -->


</article>