<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng"
        schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml"
        schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>Production Use - Good Practice</title>
    <date>1Q18</date>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>operations</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <para>From our and our clients' experiences of developing and using eXist-db in production
    environments a number of lessons have been learned. This Good Practice guide is an attempt to
    cover some of the considerations that should be taken into account when deploying eXist-db for
    use in a production environment.</para>
  <para>The concepts laid out within this document should not be considered absolute or accepted
    wholesale - they should rather be used as suggestions to guide users in their eXist-db
    deployments.</para>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>The Server</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Ensure that your server is up-to-date and patched with any necessary security
          fixes.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>eXist-db is written in Java - so for performance and security reasons, please ensure
          that you have the latest and greatest Java JDK release that is compatible with your
          version of eXist. The latest version can always be found here at: <link xlink:href="http://java.sun.com" condition="_blank">http://java.sun.com</link> and the recommended major version for a
          given eXist release can be found at: <link xlink:href="https://bintray.com/existdb/releases/exist#read" condition="_blank">https://bintray.com/existdb/releases/exist#read</link>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>



  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Install from Source or Release?</title>

    <para>Most users will install an officially released version of eXist-db on their production
      systems and usually this is perfectly fine. However, for production systems there can be
      advantages to installing eXist-db from source code.</para>
    <para>eXist-db may be installed and build (see <link xlink:href="exist-building">Building
        eXist-db</link>) from source code to a production system in one of two ways:</para>
    <variablelist spacing="compact">
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Via Local Build Machine (preferred)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>You checkout the eXist-db code for a release branch (or trunk) from our GitHub
            repository to a local machine. From here you build a distribution which you test and
            then deploy to your live server.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Directly from GitHub</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>In this case you don't use a local machine for building an eXist-db distribution,
            but you checkout the code from a release branch (or the develop branch) directly from
            our GitHub repository on your server and build it in-situ.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>Some advantages of installing eXist-db from source code are:</para>
    <variablelist spacing="compact">
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Patches</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If patches or fixes are developed that are relevant to your specific needs, you can
            update your code and re-build eXist.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Features</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If you are following trunk and new features are developed which you are interested
            in, you can update your code and re-build to take advantage of these. </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <warning>
      <para> eXist's code trunk is generally <emphasis>not</emphasis> recommended for production
        use! Although it should always compile and be relatively stable, it may also contain as yet
        unrecognised regressions or result in unexpected behaviour. </para>
    </warning>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Upgrading</title>

      <para>If you are upgrading the version of eXist-db that you use in your production system,
        please always follow these two points:</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Backup</term>
          <listitem>
            <para> Always make sure you have a full database backup before you upgrade.</para>
            <para/>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Test</term>
          <listitem>
            <para> Always test your application in the new version of eXist-db in a development
              environment to ensure expected behaviour before you upgrade your production
              system.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>


    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Configuring eXist</title>

    <para>There are four main things to consider here:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><xref linkend="sect-permissions"/></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Ensure that eXist-db is installed in a secure manner.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><xref linkend="sect-attack-surface"/></term>
        <listitem>
          <para> Configure eXist-db so it provides <emphasis>only</emphasis> what you need for your
            application.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><xref linkend="resources"/></term>
        <listitem>
          <para> Configure your system and eXist-db so that eXist-db has access to enough resources
            and the system starts and stops eXist-db in a clean manner.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><xref linkend="performance"/></term>
        <listitem>
          <para> Configure your system and eXist-db so that you get the maximum performance
            possible.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2 xml:id="sect-permissions">
      <title>Security - Permissions</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>eXist-db Permissions</title>

        <para>eXist-db ships with fairly relaxed permissions to facilitate rapid application
          development. However, for production systems these should be constrained:</para>
        <variablelist spacing="compact">
          <varlistentry>
            <term><code>admin</code> account</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The password of the admin account is blank by default! Ensure that you set a
                decent password.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><code>default-permissions</code></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The default permissions for creating resources and collections in eXist-db are
                set in <literal>conf.xml</literal>. The current settings are ok, but you may like to
                improve on them for your own application security.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><code>/db</code> permissions</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The default permissions for <code>/db</code> are <code>0755</code>, which should
                be sufficient in most cases. In case you needed to change this, you could do that
                with (here for <code>0775</code>):</para>
              <programlisting language="xquery">sm:chmod(xs:anyURI("/db"), "rwxrwxr-x")</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Operating System Permissions</title>

        <para>eXist-db should be deployed and configured to run whilst following the security best
          practices of the operating system on which it is deployed.</para>
        <para>Typically we would recommend creating an <code>exist</code> user account and
            <code>exist</code> user group with <emphasis>no</emphasis> login privileges (no shell
          and empty password), changing the permissions of the eXist-db installation to be owned by
          that user and group. Then run eXist-db using those credentials. An example of this on
          OpenSolaris might be:</para>
        <programlisting language="bash" xlink:href="listings/listing-2.txt"/>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2 xml:id="sect-attack-surface">
      <title>Security - Attack Surface</title>

      <para>For any live application it is best practice to keep the attack surface of the
        application as small as possible. There are three aspects to this:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Limiting means of arbitrary code execution.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Reducing the application itself to the absolute essentials.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Limiting access routes to the application.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>eXist-db is no exception and should be configured for your production systems so that it
        provides only what you need and no more. For example, the majority of applications will be
        unlikely to require the WebDAV or SOAP Admin features for operation in a live environment.
        These and other services can be disabled easily.</para>
      <para>Means for anonymous users to execute arbitrary code require special attention. There are
        two means of code execution in eXist, which make sense during development, but should be
        reconsidered for production systems:</para>
      <variablelist spacing="compact">
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Java binding</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The ability to execute java code from inside the XQuery processor is disabled by
              default in <literal>conf.xml</literal>:</para>
            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;xquery enable-java-binding="no" .../&gt;</programlisting>
            <para> It is strongly recommended to keep it disabled on production systems.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>REST server</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>We recommend to prevent eXist's REST server from directly receiving web requests,
              and use URL Rewriting <emphasis>only</emphasis> to control code execution. The REST
              server feature is enabled by default in
                <literal>$EXIST_HOME/webapp/WEB-INF/web.xml</literal>. Changing the
                <code>param-value</code> to <code>true</code>, allows you to filter request via your
              own XQuery controller.</para>
            <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-4.xml"/>
            <para>The following options allow a more fine-grained control over the REST server's
              functionality:</para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>XQuery submissions</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>We recommend to restrict the REST servers ability to execute XQuery code to
                    authenticated users, by modifying:
                      <literal>$EXIST_HOME/webapp/WEB-INF/web.xml</literal>:</para>
                  <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-5.xml"/>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>XUpdate statements</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>In addition, we recommend to restrict the REST servers ability to execute
                    XUpdate statements. Simply modify
                      <literal>$EXIST_HOME/webapp/WEB-INF/web.xml</literal>by changing the
                      <code>param-value</code> from <code>enabled</code> to
                    <code>disabled</code>:</para>
                  <programlisting language="xml" xlink:href="listings/listing-6.xml"/>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>
      <para>Further considerations for a live environment:</para>
      <variablelist spacing="compact">
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Standalone mode</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>eXist-db can be operated in a cut-down standalone mode (see
                <code>server.(sh|bat)</code>). This provides just the core services from the
              database (no webapp file system access and no documentation). The entire application
              has to be stored in the database and is served from there. This is an ideal starting
              place for a production system.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Services</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>eXist-db provides services for accessing the database. You should reduce these to
              the absolute minimum you need for your production application. If you are operating in
              standalone mode, this is done via <code>server.xml</code>, otherwise
                <code>webapp/WEB-INF/web.xm</code>l. You should look at each configured service,
              servlet or filter and ask yoursel: do we use this? Most production environments are
              unlikely to need WebDAV or SOAP Admin (Axis).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Extension Modules</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>eXist-db loads several XQuery and Index extension modules by default. You should
              modify the <tag>builtin-modules</tag> section of <literal>conf.xml</literal> and
                <emphasis>only</emphasis> load what you need for your application.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2 xml:id="resources">
      <title>Resources</title>

      <para>You should ensure that you have enough memory and disk space in your system so that
        eXist-db can cope with peak demands.</para>
      <variablelist spacing="compact">
        <varlistentry>
          <term><code>-Xmx</code></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>However you decide to deploy and start eXist, please ensure that you allocate
              enough maximum memory to eXist-db uwing the Java <code>-Xmx</code> setting. See
                <code>backup.sh</code> and <code>startup.sh</code>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><code>cacheSize</code> and <code>collectionCache</code></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>These two settings in <tag>db-connection</tag> of <literal>conf.xml</literal>
              should be adjusted appropriately based on your <code>-Xmx</code> setting (see above).
              See the <link xlink:href="tuning">tuning
                guide</link> for advice on sensible values.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Disk space</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Please ensure that you have plenty of space for your database to grow.
              Unsurprisingly, running out of disk space can result in database corruptions or having
              to rollback the database to a known state.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2 xml:id="performance">
      <title>Performance</title>

      <para>Keeping the eXist-db application, data and journal on separate disks, connected to
        different I/O channels, can have a positive impact on performance. The location of the data
        files and journals can be changed in <literal>conf.xml</literal>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Backups</title>

    <para>
      <emphasis>This is fundamental</emphasis>: Make sure you have them, that they are up-to-date
      and that a restore is possible!</para>
    <para>eXist-db provides 3 different mechanisms for performing backups - </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Full database backup.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Differential database backup.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Snapshot of the database data files.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>Each of these backup mechanisms can be scheduled, either with eXist-db or with your
      operating system scheduler. See the <link xlink:href="backup">backup</link> article and <literal>conf.xml</literal> for further
      details.</para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================== -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Web Deployments</title>

    <para>eXist-db, like any Web Application Server (Tomcat, WebLogic, GlassFish, etc.), should not
      be directly exposed to the Web. Instead, we strongly recommend proxying eXist-db through a Web
      Server such as <link xlink:href="http://wiki.nginx.org/Main" condition="_blank">Nginx</link> or <link xlink:href="http://httpd.apache.org/" condition="_blank">Apache HTTPD</link>. See <link xlink:href="production_web_proxying.xml">here</link> for further details.</para>
    <para>If you proxy eXist-db through a Web Server, you can also configure your firewall to allow
      external access directly to the Web Server only. If done correctly this means that web users
      will not be able to access any eXist-db services directly, except your application, which is
      proxyied into the Web Servers namespace.</para>

    <!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->

    <sect2>
      <title>Enable GZip Compression</title>

      <para>eXist-db by default operates inside the Jetty Application Server. Jetty (and most other
        Java Application Servers) provides a mechanism for enabling dynamic GZip compression of
        resources. In other words: Jetty can be configured to dynamically GZip compress any resource
        received from the server by HTTP. Enabling dynamic GZip compression can reduce the size of
        transfers, and as such reduce the transfer time of resources from the server to the client,
        hopefully resulting in a faster experience for the end-user.</para>
      <para>GZip Compression can be enabled in <code>web.xml</code>, which can be found in either
          <code>$EXIST_HOME/webapp/WEB-INF/web.xml</code> for default deployments or
          <code>$EXIST_HOME/tools/jetty/etc/standalone/WEB-INF/web.xml</code> for standalone
        deployments.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>